<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - upgrade</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/upgrade/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2014-10-30T19:44:00+01:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Migrating to SELinux userspace 2.4 (small warning for users)</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/10/migrating-to-selinux-userspace-2-4-small-warning-for-users/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-10-30T19:44:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-10-30T19:44:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-10-30:/2014/10/migrating-to-selinux-userspace-2-4-small-warning-for-users/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a few moments, SELinux users which have the \~arch KEYWORDS set
(either globally or for the SELinux utilities in particular) will notice
that the SELinux userspace will upgrade to version 2.4 (release
candidate 5 for now). This upgrade comes with a manual step that needs
to be performed …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a few moments, SELinux users which have the \~arch KEYWORDS set
(either globally or for the SELinux utilities in particular) will notice
that the SELinux userspace will upgrade to version 2.4 (release
candidate 5 for now). This upgrade comes with a manual step that needs
to be performed after upgrade. The information is mentioned as
post-installation message of the &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; package, and
basically sais that you need to execute:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~# /usr/libexec/selinux/semanage_migrate_store
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason is that the SELinux utilities expect the SELinux policy
module store (and the semanage related files) to be in
&lt;code&gt;/var/lib/selinux&lt;/code&gt; and no longer in &lt;code&gt;/etc/selinux&lt;/code&gt;. Note that this does
not mean that the SELinux policy itself is moved outside of that
location, nor is the basic configuration file (&lt;code&gt;/etc/selinux/config&lt;/code&gt;).
It is what tools such as &lt;strong&gt;semanage&lt;/strong&gt; manage that is moved outside that
location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to automate the migration as part of the packages themselves,
but this would require the &lt;code&gt;portage_t&lt;/code&gt; domain to be able to move,
rebuild and load policies, which it can't (and to be honest, shouldn't).
Instead of augmenting the policy or making updates to the migration
script as delivered by the upstream project, we currently decided to
have the migration done manually. It is a one-time migration anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If for some reason end users forget to do the migration, then that does
not mean that the system breaks or becomes unusable. SELinux still
works, SELinux aware applications still work; the only thing that will
fail are updates on the SELinux configuration through tools like
&lt;strong&gt;semanage&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;setsebool&lt;/strong&gt; - the latter when you want to persist
boolean changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~# semanage fcontext -l
ValueError: SELinux policy is not managed or store cannot be accessed.

~# setsebool -P allow_ptrace on
Cannot set persistent booleans without managed policy.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you get those errors or warnings, all that is left to do is to do the
migration. Note in the following that there is a warning about 'else'
blocks that are no longer supported: that's okay, as far as I know (and
it was mentioned on the upstream mailinglist as well as not something to
worry about) it does not have any impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~# /usr/libexec/selinux/semanage_migrate_store
Migrating from /etc/selinux/mcs/modules/active to /var/lib/selinux/mcs/active
Attempting to rebuild policy from /var/lib/selinux
sysnetwork: Warning: &amp;#39;else&amp;#39; blocks in optional statements are unsupported in CIL. Dropping from output.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also add in &lt;code&gt;-c&lt;/code&gt; so that the old policy module store is cleaned
up. You can also rerun the command multiple times:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~# /usr/libexec/selinux/semanage_migrate_store -c
warning: Policy type mcs has already been migrated, but modules still exist in the old store. Skipping store.
Attempting to rebuild policy from /var/lib/selinux
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can manually clean up the old policy module store like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~# rm -rf /etc/selinux/mcs/modules
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So... don't worry - the change is small and does not break stuff. And
for those wondering about CIL I'll talk about it in one of my next
posts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="cil"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="migrate"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="semanage"></category><category term="upgrade"></category><category term="userspace"></category></entry><entry><title>Upgrading old Gentoo installations</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/upgrading-old-gentoo-installations/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-29T14:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-29T14:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-29:/2013/12/upgrading-old-gentoo-installations/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I got "pinged" on &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=463240"&gt;bug
#463240&lt;/a&gt; about the
difficulty of upgrading a Gentoo Linux deployment after a long time of
inactivity on the system. We already have an &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Upgrading_Gentoo"&gt;Upgrading
Gentoo&lt;/a&gt; article on the
Gentoo wiki that describes in great detail how upgrades can be
accomplished. But one of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I got "pinged" on &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=463240"&gt;bug
#463240&lt;/a&gt; about the
difficulty of upgrading a Gentoo Linux deployment after a long time of
inactivity on the system. We already have an &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Upgrading_Gentoo"&gt;Upgrading
Gentoo&lt;/a&gt; article on the
Gentoo wiki that describes in great detail how upgrades can be
accomplished. But one of the methods I personally suggest most is to do
small, incremental upgrades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say you have a system from early 2009. Not too long ago, but also not
that recent anymore. If you would upgrade that system using the regular
approach, your system would probably be using a non-existing profile
(the &lt;code&gt;/etc/make.profile&lt;/code&gt; symlink would point to a non-existing
location), and if you switch the profile to an existing one, you might
have to deal with problems like the profile requiring certain features
(or EAPI version) that the software currently available on your system
doesn't support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem is mentioned in the upgrade guide through the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure your Portage is updated before performing any profile
changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it does not tell how to update Portage. In my opinion the best
way forward is to install an older Portage tree snapshot (somewhat more
recent than your own deployment) and upgrade &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; portage, perhaps
also the packages belonging to the &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; set. So for a system that
has not been updated since January 2009, you might want to try the
portage tree snapshot of July 2009, then January 2010, then July 2010,
etc. until you have a recent deployment again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that is left for you to do is to find such a snapshot (as the
Portage tree snapshots from the mirrors are cleaned out after a few
months). I try to keep a set of &lt;a href="http://dev.gentoo.org/~swift/snapshots/"&gt;Portage tree snapshots
available&lt;/a&gt; with a 2-month
period which should be sufficient for most users to gradually upgrade
their systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering I've used this method a few times already I'm going to add
them to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Upgrading_Gentoo"&gt;upgrading
instructions&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="portage"></category><category term="snapshot"></category><category term="upgrade"></category></entry></feed>