<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - documentation</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/documentation/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2021-07-08T09:20:00+02:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Organizing service documentation</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/07/organizing-service-documentation/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-08T09:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-08T09:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-07-08:/2021/07/organizing-service-documentation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;An IT services overview&lt;/a&gt;
I try to keep track of the architecture and designs of the IT services and
solutions in a way that I feel helps me keep in touch with all the various
services and solutions out there. Similar to how system administrators try to
find a balance while working on documentation (which is often considered a
chore) and using a structure that is sufficiently simple and standard for the
organization to benefit from, architects should try to keep track of
architecturally relevant information as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this post, I'm going to explain a bit more on how I approach documenting
service and solution insights for architectural relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;An IT services overview&lt;/a&gt;
I try to keep track of the architecture and designs of the IT services and
solutions in a way that I feel helps me keep in touch with all the various
services and solutions out there. Similar to how system administrators try to
find a balance while working on documentation (which is often considered a
chore) and using a structure that is sufficiently simple and standard for the
organization to benefit from, architects should try to keep track of
architecturally relevant information as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this post, I'm going to explain a bit more on how I approach documenting
service and solution insights for architectural relevance.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why I tend to document some of it myself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the company I currently work for, not all architecture and designs are
handled by a central repository, but that doesn't mean there is no architecture
and design available. They are more commonly handled through separate documents,
online project sites and the like. If we had a common way of documenting
everything in the same tool using the same processes and the same taxonomy, it
wouldn't make sense to document things myself... unless even then I would find
that I am missing some information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all started when I tried to keep track of past decisions for a service or
solution. Decisions on architecture boards, on risk forums, on department
steering committees and what not. &lt;em&gt;Historical insights&lt;/em&gt; I call it, and it often
provides a good sense of why a solution or service came up, what the challenges
were, which principles were used, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I started tracking the historical decisions and topics, I quickly moved on
to a common structure: an entry page with the most common information about the
service or solution, and then subpages for the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Administration (processes, authorizations, procedures)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authentication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authorizationn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Auditing and logging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configuration management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cost management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cryptography and privacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data management (data handling, definitions, governance, lineage,
  backup/restore, ...)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design and development (incl. naming convention)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Figures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High availability and disaster recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;History&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operations (actor groups, source systems &amp;amp; interactions/external interfacing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organization (management, organisational structure within the company, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quality assurance &amp;amp; reporting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roadmap and restrictions (incl. lifecycle)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risks and technical debt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Runtime information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Terminology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I won't go in depth about all the different categories listed. Perhaps some
areas warrant closer scrutiny in later posts, but for now the names of the
categories should be sufficiently self-explanatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is an internal service (website or similar) that covers the
details properly, then I will of course not duplicate that information. Instead,
I will add a link to that resource and perhaps just document how to interpret
the information on that resource.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The entry page&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entry page of a service or solution always looks the same. It starts off
with a few attributes associated with the service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The taxonomy used within the company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The main point of contact(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The backlog where the responsible team tracks its progress and evolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A link to the main documentation resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The internal working name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;taxonomy&lt;/em&gt; is something I strongly appreciate in my current company. It is
a uniform identifier associated with the product, service or solution, and is
used for several of the operational processes the company has. This taxonomy
comes up in things like chargeback, service level agreements, responsibility
overviews, data classifications, enterprise architectural overviews, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, a managed macbook (asset) might have a taxonomy identifier of
&lt;code&gt;mmac&lt;/code&gt;, or we have a service for exchanging internal company data identified as
&lt;code&gt;cd70&lt;/code&gt; (it doesn't need to have an identifier that "reads" properly). Of course,
people don't just run around shouting the identifiers, but when we go through
the information available at the company, this identifier is often the primary
key so to speak to find the information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the &lt;em&gt;main points of contacts&lt;/em&gt;, I usually just document the person that is
my go-to person to get some quick insights. The full list of all contacts (like
product owner, product manager, system architect, business analyst, release
manager, etc.) is managed in a central tool (and uses the taxonomy to quickly
find the right person), so I just have the few names that I quickly need listed
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;backlog&lt;/em&gt; is something I recently added to support any questions on "when
will we have feature XYZ". In the past, I had to contact the people to get this
information, but that often became cumbersome, especially when the team uses a
proper tool for tracking the work on the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;main documentation&lt;/em&gt; is often the most important part. It is a link to the
documentation that the team provides for end users, architects or other roles.
Some teams still have their information on a NAS, others in a document library
on SharePoint, others use a wiki, and there are teams that use a structured
document management system. Working for a big company has its consequences...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the &lt;em&gt;internal working name&lt;/em&gt; is the name that a service or solution
receives the most. For infrastructure services, this is often the name of the
product from the time the product entered the organization. While the vendor has
switched the name of the product numerous times since, the old name sticks. For
instance, while I will document IBM's cloud offering as "IBMCloud" (its current
name) I will list its working name as "Bluemix" because that's how the company
internally often refers to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the basic attributes, I have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a few paragraphs for &lt;em&gt;description&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a diagram or architecture view to give a &lt;em&gt;high level design&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;most important questions&lt;/em&gt; surrounding the service or solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some &lt;em&gt;tips and titbits&lt;/em&gt; for myself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high level design is often a view that I maintain myself, which uses the
&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/"&gt;abstraction&lt;/a&gt; that I
mentioned earlier in my blog. It is not covering everything, but to a sufficient
level that I can quickly understand the context of the service or solution and
how it is generally implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important questions are mostly a refresher for questions that pop up
during discussions. For instance, for an API gateway, common questions might be
"What are the security controls that it enforces" or "Does the API GW perform
schema validation on JSON structures?".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The history of a service&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below the entry page, the various categories come up. As I mentioned, it all
started with the historical insights on the service. By having a chronological
overview of all decisions and related material per service, I can quickly find
the most important information in many cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to know the latest architecture for a service? Let's look in the history
when the last architectural review was, and at which decision body or board it
came up. Once found, I just need to go to the meeting minutes or case details to
find it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to know why the decision was taken to allow a non-standard integration?
Take a look at the history where this decision was taken, and consult its
meeting minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Need to ask for a continuance for something but you're just new in the team and
don't know why or how it was approved in the past? No worries, I'll share with
you the history of the service, where you can find the information, and coach
you a bit through our organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the history for services and solutions available has been a massive
efficiency gain for myself and my immediate stakeholders. Of course, I would
have loved if the organization tracked this themselves, but as long as they
don't (especially since organization changes more often than technology) I will
put time and effort to track it myself (at least for the services and solutions
that I am interested in).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The historical information I track myself is not a copy/paste of the meeting
minutes of those entries. I try to use a single paragraph explaination, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;ARB  2020/12/05     &amp;quot;Switch of PostgreSQL authentication provider to PAM+sssd&amp;quot;
    Approval to switch the authentication provider of the PostgreSQL
    database assets from the internal authentication to a PAM-supported
    method, and use the RHEL sssd solution as a facilitator. Link with
    Active Directory.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;ARB&lt;/code&gt; is the name of the decision body (here it could be the &lt;em&gt;Architecture
Review Board&lt;/em&gt;) and tells me where I can find more details if needed. I don't
really bother with trying to add actual links, because that takes time and often
the links become invalid after we switch from one solution to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, I also started adding information related to the service that isn't
just decision body oriented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;Incident    2021/06/08  &amp;quot;Fastly major outage&amp;quot;
    A major outage occurred on Fastly, a widely used cloud edge provider,
    between 09:47 UTC and 12:35 UTC. This impacted service ABC and DEF.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidents can be internal or external, and if they are internal I'll document
the incident and root cause analysis numbers associated with the incident as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also doesn't need to be about problems. It can be announcements from the
vendor as well, as long as the announcement is or can be impactful for my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How complete is this overview&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My overview is far, far, far from complete. It is also not my intention to make
it a complete overview, but instead use it as a quick reference when needed.
Services that are commonly discussed (for instance because they have wide
implications on other domain's architectures) are documented more in depth than
services that are barely influential to my meetings and projects. And that
doesn't mean that the services themselves are not important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the only areas that I truly want to have up-to-date, is the entry
page and the history. For all the other information I always hope to be able to
link to existing documentation that is kept up-to-date by the responsible teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in case the information isn't available, using the same structure for noting
down what insights that I gather helps out tremendously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also don't want my overview to become a critical asset. It is protected from
prying eyes (as there is occasionally confidential information inside) and I am
coaching the organization to take up a lot of the information gathering and
documentation in a structured way. For instance, for managing EOL information,
we are publishing this in a standard way for all internal stakeholders to see
(and report on). The roadmap and strategy for the services within the domain are
now being standardized within the backlog tool as well, so that everybody can
clearly document when they expect to work on something, when certain investments
are needed, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, architects often had to scramble all that information together
(hence one of my categories on &lt;em&gt;Roadmap&lt;/em&gt;) whereas we can now use the backlog
tools of the teams themselves to report on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which tool to use?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I use a wiki-alike service for this, so that I can search through
the pages, move and merge information, use tagging and labels and what not. I
also think that, unless the company already has a central tool for this, a well
maintained wiki with good practices and agreements on how to use it would do
wonders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been playing around in my spare time with several wiki technologies.
&lt;a href="https://www.dokuwiki.org/dokuwiki"&gt;Dokuwiki&lt;/a&gt; is still one of my favorites due
to its simplicity, whereas &lt;a href="https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/MediaWiki"&gt;MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt;
is one of my go-to's for when the organization really wants to pursue a scalable
and flexible organization-wide wiki. However, considering that I try to
structure the information in a hierarchical way, I am planning to play around
with &lt;a href="https://www.bookstackapp.com/"&gt;BookStack&lt;/a&gt; a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while having a good tool is important, it isn't the critical part of
documenting information. Good documentation, in my opinion, comes from a good
structure and a coherent way of working. If you do it yourself, then of course
it is coherent, but it takes time and effort to maintain it. If you collaborate
on it, you have to make sure everybody follows the same practices and agreements
- so don't make them too complex.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category><category term="architecture"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="structure"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Wiki is growing</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2015/01/gentoo-wiki-is-growing/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-01-03T10:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-01-03T10:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-01-03:/2015/01/gentoo-wiki-is-growing/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is because of the winter holidays, but the last weeks I've
noticed a lot of updates and edits on the Gentoo wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Website/Tyrian"&gt;Tyrian&lt;/a&gt; layout,
whose purpose is to eventually become the unified layout for all Gentoo
resources, happened first. Then, three common templates (&lt;code&gt;Code …&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is because of the winter holidays, but the last weeks I've
noticed a lot of updates and edits on the Gentoo wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Website/Tyrian"&gt;Tyrian&lt;/a&gt; layout,
whose purpose is to eventually become the unified layout for all Gentoo
resources, happened first. Then, three common templates (&lt;code&gt;Code&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;File&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;Kernel&lt;/code&gt;) where deprecated in favor of their "*Box" counterparts
(&lt;code&gt;CodeBox&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;FileBox&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;KernelBox&lt;/code&gt;). These provide better parameter
support (which should make future updates on the templates easier to
implement) as well as syntax highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the wiki also saw a number of contributions being added. I added a
short article on &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Efibootmgr"&gt;Efibootmgr&lt;/a&gt;
as the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Handbook:Main_Page"&gt;Gentoo
handbook&lt;/a&gt; now also uses
it for its EFI related instructions, but other users added quite a few
additional articles as well. As they come along, articles are being
marked by editors for translation. For me, that's a trigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever a wiki article is marked for translations, it shows up on the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Special:PageTranslation"&gt;PageTranslation&lt;/a&gt;
list. When I have time, I pick one of these articles and try to update
it to move to a common style (the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Gentoo_Wiki:Guidelines"&gt;Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; page
is the "official" one, and I have a
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User:SwifT/Styleguide"&gt;Styleguide&lt;/a&gt; in
which I elaborate a bit more on the use). Having a common style gives a
better look and feel to the articles (as they are then more alike),
gives a common documentation development approach (so everyone can join
in and update documentation in a similar layout/structure) and - most
importantly - reduces the number of edits that do little more than
switch from one formatting to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an article has been edited, I mark it for translation, and then the
real workhorse on the wiki starts. We have several active translators on
the Gentoo wiki, who we cannot thank hard enough for their work (I used
to start at Gentoo as a translator, I have some feeling about their
work). They make the Gentoo documentation reachable for a broader
audience. Thanks to the use of the translation extension (kindly offered
by the Gentoo wiki admins, who have been working quite hard the last few
weeks on improving the wiki infrastructure) translations are easier to
handle and follow through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of a translation-marked article is that any change on the
article also shows up on the list again, allowing me to look at the
change and perform edits when necessary. For the end user, this is
behind the scenes - an update on an article shows up immediately, which
is fine. But for me (and perhaps other editors as well) this gives a
nice overview of changes to articles (watchlists can only go so far) and
also shows the changes in a simple yet efficient manner. Thanks to this
approach, we can more actively follow up on edits and improve where
necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, editing is not always just a few minutes of work. Consider the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/GRUB2"&gt;GRUB2&lt;/a&gt; article on the wiki. It was
marked for translation, but had some issues with its style. It was very
verbose (which is not a bad thing, but suggests to split information
towards multiple articles) and quite a few open discussions on its
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Talk:GRUB2"&gt;Discussions&lt;/a&gt; page. I started
editing the article around 13.12h local time, and ended at 19.40h.
Unlike with offline documentation, the entire process of the editing can
be followed through the page'
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/index.php?title=GRUB2&amp;amp;offset=&amp;amp;limit=100&amp;amp;action=history"&gt;history&lt;/a&gt;).
And although I'm still not 100% satisfied with the result, it is imo
easier to follow through and read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, don't get me wrong - I do not feel that the article was wrong
in any way. Although I would appreciate articles that immediately follow
a style, I rather see more contributions (which we can then edit towards
the new style) than that we would start penalizing contributors that
don't use the style. That would work contra-productive, because it is
far easier to update the style of an article than to write articles. We
should try and get more contributors to document aspects of their Gentoo
journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, please keep them coming. If you find a lack of (good) information
for something, start jotting down what you know in an article. We'll
gladly help you out with editing and improving the article then, but the
content is something you are probably best to write down.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>Revamped our SELinux documentation</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/05/revamped-our-selinux-documentation/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-12T22:15:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-05-12T22:15:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-05-12:/2014/05/revamped-our-selinux-documentation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the move to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo wiki&lt;/a&gt;, I have
updated and revamped most of our SELinux documentation. The end result
can be seen through the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux"&gt;main SELinux
page&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the content is
below this page (as subpages).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start with a new &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux/Quick_introduction"&gt;introduction to
SELinux&lt;/a&gt;
article which goes over …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the move to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo wiki&lt;/a&gt;, I have
updated and revamped most of our SELinux documentation. The end result
can be seen through the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux"&gt;main SELinux
page&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the content is
below this page (as subpages).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We start with a new &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux/Quick_introduction"&gt;introduction to
SELinux&lt;/a&gt;
article which goes over a large set of SELinux' features and concepts.
Next, we cover the various concepts within SELinux. This is mostly
SELinux features but explained more in-depth. Then we go on to the user
guides. We start of course with the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux/Installation"&gt;installation of SELinux on
Gentoo&lt;/a&gt; and then
cover the remainder of administrative topics within SELinux (user
management, handling AVC denials, label management, booleans, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above is most likely sufficient for the majority of SELinux users. A
few more expert-specific documents are provided as well (some of them
still work in progress, but I didn't want to wait to get some feedback)
and there is also a section specific for (Gentoo) developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give it a review and tell me what you think.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>GPT or MBR in the Gentoo Handbook</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/gpt-or-mbr-in-the-gentoo-handbook/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-18T12:25:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-18T12:25:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-18:/2013/12/gpt-or-mbr-in-the-gentoo-handbook/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just committed a set of changes against the Gentoo Handbook (x86 and
amd64) with the intent to have better instructions on GPT (GUID
Partition Table) layout versus MBR (Master Boot Record) or MSDOS-style
layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The part on "Preparing the Disks" saw the most changes. It starts with
explaining the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just committed a set of changes against the Gentoo Handbook (x86 and
amd64) with the intent to have better instructions on GPT (GUID
Partition Table) layout versus MBR (Master Boot Record) or MSDOS-style
layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The part on "Preparing the Disks" saw the most changes. It starts with
explaining the differences between the two layouts with advantages and
disadvantages. It then helps the user decide what layout is best for him
(or her).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the &lt;em&gt;example&lt;/em&gt; (and let me stress that one out again, because
many people have reported bugs on it: it is an &lt;em&gt;example&lt;/em&gt;) partition
layout now includes a BIOS boot partition in the beginning, 2 MB in
size. This is to support GRUB2 on GPT, but doesn't hurt for GRUB2 with
the MSDOS-style layout either. That means that the partition numbers now
move up one (the &lt;em&gt;example&lt;/em&gt; /boot is now at sda2, the swap at sda3 and
root on sda4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The partitioning instructions now also include the proper alignment
instructions (using MB alignment), and use parted as the default
partitioning method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The changes are submitted to CVS so will show up on the Gentoo site in
an hour or so (documentation on the sites is synchronized hourly if I'm
not mistaken). Please do give it a good read and report bugs on
&lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org"&gt;bugs.gentoo.org&lt;/a&gt;. You might also want to ping
me on IRC if it is urgent, although no guarantees that I'm behind my
computer at any point.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="fdisk"></category><category term="gdp"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="gpt"></category><category term="handbook"></category><category term="mbr"></category><category term="parted"></category></entry><entry><title>Updated Linux Sea, now with viewport thingie</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/updated-linux-sea-now-with-viewport-thingie/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-16T23:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-16T23:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-16:/2013/12/updated-linux-sea-now-with-viewport-thingie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just pushed out an update to &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; (an online resource to introduce
you to Linux, using Gentoo Linux as an example), including its PDF and
ePub versions. The changes are pretty small (see its
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sjvermeu/Linux-Sea/blob/master/ChangeLog"&gt;ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with the update, it now also includes a
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;meta name="viewport"...&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; so …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just pushed out an update to &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; (an online resource to introduce
you to Linux, using Gentoo Linux as an example), including its PDF and
ePub versions. The changes are pretty small (see its
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sjvermeu/Linux-Sea/blob/master/ChangeLog"&gt;ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with the update, it now also includes a
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;meta name="viewport"...&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; so that the document renders better on a
mobile device. Not perfect, but at least it's not small text anymore
where you need to pinch-zoom and then scroll left/right all over the
place. Same with my blog btw.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="css"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="linux sea"></category><category term="mobile"></category></entry><entry><title>Majority of GDP documents moved to Gentoo wiki</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/majority-of-gdp-documents-moved-to-gentoo-wiki/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-10T16:03:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-10T16:03:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-10:/2013/12/majority-of-gdp-documents-moved-to-gentoo-wiki/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The majority of the English gentoo documents that resided in
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en"&gt;www.gentoo.org/doc/en&lt;/a&gt; have now been
moved to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. All those documents
have been made available in the main namespace, meaning that
non-developers can continue to contribute on those articles and guides,
fully in the spirit …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The majority of the English gentoo documents that resided in
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en"&gt;www.gentoo.org/doc/en&lt;/a&gt; have now been
moved to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. All those documents
have been made available in the main namespace, meaning that
non-developers can continue to contribute on those articles and guides,
fully in the spirit of a wiki and community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are now working on &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Documentation/Overview"&gt;a method for displaying an overview of
documents&lt;/a&gt;
that have been moved, or have seen enough development on the wiki that
they are deemed of proper quality and stable (not too many changes
left). Currently, such documents are (requested to be) marked for
translation, allowing me or other developers to review if the guides are
indeed ok to move forward. If so, they are marked as translatable
(allowing the various translation members on the wiki to move forward
with translating the guides) and will be made part of the overview as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the few documents that has not been moved yet is the Gentoo
Handbook as it is of a different format than the guides, and includes
dynamic documentation generation features which I have yet to fully
investigate (wiki-wise). I currently focused mainly on the non-handbook
guides, so the handbook itself will get more attention later (after the
documentation overview is completed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User:A3li"&gt;Alex Legler&lt;/a&gt; for
assisting me and providing the necessary features and functionality in
the Gentoo wiki to make this all possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit:&lt;/em&gt; added link to overview page.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="documents"></category><category term="gdp"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>Moving Gentoo docs to the wiki</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/07/moving-gentoo-docs-to-the-wiki/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-28T11:22:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-07-28T11:22:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-07-28:/2013/07/moving-gentoo-docs-to-the-wiki/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slowly but surely Gentoo documentation guides are being moved to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to the translation
support provided by the infrastructure, all "reasons" not to go forward
with this have been resolved. At first, I'm focusing on documentation
with open bugs that have not been picked up (usually due …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slowly but surely Gentoo documentation guides are being moved to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to the translation
support provided by the infrastructure, all "reasons" not to go forward
with this have been resolved. At first, I'm focusing on documentation
with open bugs that have not been picked up (usually due to (human)
resource limits), but other documents will follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of already moved documents are the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Xorg/Configuration"&gt;Xorg configuration
guide&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/GCC_optimization"&gt;GCC
optimization guide&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/UTF-8"&gt;UTF-8&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User-mode_Linux/System_testing_with_UML"&gt;System testing with
UML&lt;/a&gt;.
Many more have been moved as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The migrations are assisted by a conversion script that translates
GuideXML into wiki style content, although manual corrections remain
needed. For instance, all &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;pre caption="..."&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; stuff is changed into
&lt;code&gt;{{Code|...}}&lt;/code&gt; even though the Wiki has several templates for code, such
as &lt;code&gt;{{Kernel|...}}&lt;/code&gt; for kernel configurations, &lt;code&gt;{{RootCmd|...}}&lt;/code&gt; for
commands ran as a privileged user and &lt;code&gt;{{Cmd|...}}&lt;/code&gt; for unprivileged
user commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I updated the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/list.xml"&gt;documentation
list&lt;/a&gt; on the main Gentoo site to
reflect the movement of documents as well, as this list will be slowly
shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="docs"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="gdp"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>Added "predictable network interface" info into the handbook</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/05/added-predictable-network-interface-info-into-the-handbook/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-07T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-05-07T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-05-07:/2013/05/added-predictable-network-interface-info-into-the-handbook/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being long overdue - like many of our documentation-reported bugs :-( I
worked on &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=466262"&gt;bug 466262&lt;/a&gt;
to update the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/"&gt;Gentoo Handbook&lt;/a&gt;
with information about &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=4&amp;amp;chap=2#doc_chap4"&gt;Network Interface
Naming&lt;/a&gt;.
Of course, the installation instructions have also seen the necessary
updates to refer to this change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some luck (read: time) I might be able …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being long overdue - like many of our documentation-reported bugs :-( I
worked on &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=466262"&gt;bug 466262&lt;/a&gt;
to update the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/"&gt;Gentoo Handbook&lt;/a&gt;
with information about &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=4&amp;amp;chap=2#doc_chap4"&gt;Network Interface
Naming&lt;/a&gt;.
Of course, the installation instructions have also seen the necessary
updates to refer to this change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some luck (read: time) I might be able to fix various other
documentation-related ones soon. I had some problems with the new
SELinux userspace that I wanted to get fixed before, and then I worked
on the new SELinux policies as well as trying to figure out how SELinux
deals with network related aspects. Hence I saw time fly by at the speed
of a neutrino...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTW, the 20130424 policies are in the tree.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="gdp"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="udev"></category></entry><entry><title>SELinux tutorial series</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/03/selinux-tutorial-series/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-03-15T00:34:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-03-15T00:34:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-03-15:/2013/03/selinux-tutorial-series/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As we get a growing number of SELinux users within Gentoo Hardened and
because the SELinux usage at the firm I work at is most likely going to
grow as well, I decided to join the bunch of documents on SELinux that
are "out there" and start a series of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As we get a growing number of SELinux users within Gentoo Hardened and
because the SELinux usage at the firm I work at is most likely going to
grow as well, I decided to join the bunch of documents on SELinux that
are "out there" and start a series of my own. After all, too much
documentation probably doesn't hurt, and SELinux definitely deserves a
lot of documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to use the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt; for this
endeavour instead of a GuideXML approach (which is the format used for
Gentoo documentation on the main site). The set of tutorials that I
already wrote can be found under the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux"&gt;SELinux&lt;/a&gt; : &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux/Tutorials"&gt;Gentoo Hardened
SELinux Tutorials&lt;/a&gt;
location. Although of course meant to support the Gentoo Hardened
SELinux users, I'm hoping to keep the initial set of tutorial articles
deliberately distribution-independent so I can refer to them at work as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now (this is a week's work, so don't expect this amount of tutorials
to double in the next few days) I wrote about the security context of a
process, how SELinux controls file and directory accesses, where to find
SELinux permission denial details, controlling file contexts yourself
and how a process gets into a certain context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope I can keep the articles in good shape and with a gradual step-up
in complexity. That does mean that most articles are not complete (for
instance, when talking about domain transitions, I don't talk about
constraints that might prohibit them, or about the role and type
mismatches (invalid context) that you might get, etc.) and that those
details will follow in later articles. Hopefully that allows users to
learn step by step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of each tutorial, you will find a "What you need to remember"
section. This is a very short overview of what was said in the tutorial
and that you will need to know in future articles. If you ever read a
tutorial article, then this section might be sufficient for you to
remember again what it was about - no need to reread the entire article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider it an attempt at a &lt;code&gt;tl;dr&lt;/code&gt; for articles ;-) Enjoy your reading,
and if you have any remarks, don't hesitate to contribute on the wiki or
talk through the "Talk" pages.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="SELinux"></category><category term="articles"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="tutorials"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry></feed>