<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - u2f</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 18:25:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Authenticating with U2F</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2017/09/authenticating-with-u2f/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In order to further secure access to my workstation, after the &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2017/08/switch-to-gentoo-sources/"&gt;switch to Gentoo
sources&lt;/a&gt;, I now enabled two-factor authentication through my Yubico U2F
USB device. Well, at least for local access - remote access through SSH requires
both userid/password as well as the correct SSH key, by &lt;a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/544640/"&gt;chaining authentication
methods in OpenSSH&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling U2F on (Gentoo) Linux is fairly easy. The various guides online which talk
about the &lt;code&gt;pam_u2f&lt;/code&gt; setup are indeed correct that it is fairly simple. For completeness
sake, I've documented what I know on the Gentoo Wiki, as the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Pam_u2f"&gt;pam_u2f article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2017 18:25:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-09-11:/2017/09/authenticating-with-u2f/</guid><category>gentoo</category><category>security</category><category>yubico</category><category>u2f</category><category>pam</category></item><item><title>Using multiple OpenSSH daemons</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2015/09/using-multiple-openssh-daemons/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I administer a couple of systems which provide interactive access by end users,
and for this interactive access I position &lt;a href="http://www.openssh.com/"&gt;OpenSSH&lt;/a&gt;. 
However, I also use this for administrative access to the system, and I tend to
have harder security requirements for OpenSSH than most users do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, on one system, end users with a userid + password use the
sFTP server for publishing static websites. Other access is prohibited,
so I really like this OpenSSH configuration to use chrooted users, internal
sftp support, whereas a different OpenSSH is used for administrative access
(which is only accessible by myself and some trusted parties).&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 16:37:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-09-06:/2015/09/using-multiple-openssh-daemons/</guid><category>openssh</category><category>ssh</category><category>u2f</category><category>selinux</category></item></channel></rss>