<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - baseline</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/baseline/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2018-03-03T13:20:00+01:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Automating compliance checks</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/03/automating-compliance-checks/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-03T13:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-03T13:20:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2018-03-03:/2018/03/automating-compliance-checks/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the configuration baseline for a technical service being described fully (see the &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-configuration-changes/"&gt;first&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/structuring-a-configuration-baseline/"&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-a-rule/"&gt;third&lt;/a&gt; post in this series), it is time to consider the validation of the settings in an automated manner. The preferred method for this is to use &lt;em&gt;Open Vulnerability and Assessment Language (OVAL)&lt;/em&gt;, which is nowadays managed by the &lt;a href="https://oval.cisecurity.org/"&gt;Center for Internet Security&lt;/a&gt;, abbreviated as CISecurity. Previously, OVAL was maintained and managed by Mitre under NIST supervision, and Google searches will often still point to the old sites. However, documentation is now maintained on CISecurity's &lt;a href="https://github.com/OVALProject/Language/tree/5.11.2/docs"&gt;github repositories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I digress...&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the configuration baseline for a technical service being described fully (see the &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-configuration-changes/"&gt;first&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/structuring-a-configuration-baseline/"&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-a-rule/"&gt;third&lt;/a&gt; post in this series), it is time to consider the validation of the settings in an automated manner. The preferred method for this is to use &lt;em&gt;Open Vulnerability and Assessment Language (OVAL)&lt;/em&gt;, which is nowadays managed by the &lt;a href="https://oval.cisecurity.org/"&gt;Center for Internet Security&lt;/a&gt;, abbreviated as CISecurity. Previously, OVAL was maintained and managed by Mitre under NIST supervision, and Google searches will often still point to the old sites. However, documentation is now maintained on CISecurity's &lt;a href="https://github.com/OVALProject/Language/tree/5.11.2/docs"&gt;github repositories&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I digress...&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read-only compliance validation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main ideas with OVAL is to have a language (XML-based) that represents state information (what something should be) which can be verified in a read-only fashion. Even more, from an operational perspective, it is very important that compliance checks &lt;em&gt;do not alter&lt;/em&gt; anything, but only report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within its design, OVAL engineering has considered how to properly manage huge sets of assessment rules, and how to document this in an unambiguous manner. In the previous blog posts, ambiguity was resolved through writing style, and not much through actual, enforced definitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OVAL enforces this. You can't write a generic or ambiguous rule in OVAL. It is very specific, but that also means that it is daunting to implement the first few times. I've written many OVAL sets, and I still struggle with it (although that's because I don't do it enough in a short time-frame, and need to reread my own documentation regularly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The capability to perform read-only validation with OVAL leads to a number of possible use cases. In the &lt;a href="http://oval.mitre.org/language/version5.10/OVAL_Language_Specification_09-14-2011.pdf"&gt;5.10 specification&lt;/a&gt; a number of use cases are provided. Basically, it boils down to vulnerability discovery (is a system vulnerable or not), patch management (is the system patched accordingly or not), configuration management (are the settings according to the rules or not), inventory management (detect what is installed on the system or what the systems' assets are), malware and threat indicator (detect if a system has been compromised or particular malware is active), policy enforcement (verify if a client system adheres to particular rules before it is granted access to a network), change tracking (regularly validating the state of a system and keeping track of changes), and security information management (centralizing results of an entire organization or environment and doing standard analytics on it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post series, I'm focusing on configuration management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OVAL structure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the OVAL standard (just like the XCCDF standard actually) entails a number of major components, I'm going to focus on the OVAL definitions. Be aware though that the results of an OVAL scan are also standardized format, as are results of XCCDF scans for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OVAL definitions have 4 to 5 blocks in them:
- the &lt;strong&gt;definition&lt;/strong&gt; itself, which describes what is being validated and how. It refers to one or more tests that are to be executed or validated for the definition result to be calculated
- the &lt;strong&gt;test&lt;/strong&gt; or tests, which are referred to by the definition. In each test, there is at least a reference to an object (what is being tested) and optionally to a state (what should the object look like)
- the &lt;strong&gt;object&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a unique representation of a resource or resources on the system (a file, a process, a mount point, a kernel parameter, etc.). Object definitions can refer to multiple resources, depending on the definition.
- the &lt;strong&gt;state&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a sort-of value mapping or validation that needs to be applied to an object to see if it is configured correctly
- the &lt;strong&gt;variable&lt;/strong&gt;, an optional definition which is what it sounds like, a variable that substitutes an abstract definition with an actual definition,  allowing to write more reusable tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's get an example going, but without the XML structure, so in human language. We want to define that the Kerberos definition on a Linux system should allow forwardable tickets by default. This is accomplished by ensuring that, inside the &lt;code&gt;/etc/krb5.conf&lt;/code&gt; file (which is an INI-style configuration file), the value of the &lt;code&gt;forwardable&lt;/code&gt; key inside the &lt;code&gt;[libdefaults]&lt;/code&gt; section is set to &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In OVAL, the definition itself will document the above in human readable text, assign it a unique ID (like &lt;code&gt;oval:com.example.oval:def:1&lt;/code&gt;) and mark it as being a definition for configuration validation (&lt;code&gt;compliance&lt;/code&gt;). Then, it defines the criteria that need to be checked in order to properly validate if the rule is applicable or not. These criteria include validation if the OVAL statement is actually being run on a Linux system (as it makes no sense to run it against a Cisco router) which is Kerberos enabled, and then the criteria of the file check itself. Each criteria links to a test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The test of the file itself links to an object and a state. There are a number of ways how we can check for this specific case. One is that the object is the &lt;code&gt;forwardable&lt;/code&gt; key in the &lt;code&gt;[libdefaults]&lt;/code&gt; section of the &lt;code&gt;/etc/krb5.conf&lt;/code&gt; file, and the state is the value &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;. In this case, the state will point to those two entries (through their unique IDs) and define that the object must exist, and all matches must have a matching state. The "all matches" here is not that important, because there will generally only be one such definition in the &lt;code&gt;/etc/krb5.conf&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note however that a different approach to the test can be declared as well. We could state that the object is the &lt;code&gt;[libdefaults]&lt;/code&gt; section inside the &lt;code&gt;/etc/krb5.conf&lt;/code&gt; file, and the state is the value &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; for the &lt;code&gt;forwardable&lt;/code&gt; key. In this case, the test declares that multiple objects must exist, and (at least) one must match the state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the OVAL language tries to map definitions to unambiguous definitions. So, how does this look like in OVAL XML?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The OVAL XML structure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/static/2018/oval.xml"&gt;full example&lt;/a&gt; contains a few more entries than those we declare next, in order to be complete. The most important definitions though are documented below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the definition. As stated, it will refer to tests that need to match for the definition to be valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;definitions&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;definition id=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:def:1&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot; class=&amp;quot;compliance&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;metadata&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;libdefaults.forwardable in /etc/krb5.conf must be set to true&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;affected family=&amp;quot;unix&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
        &amp;lt;platform&amp;gt;Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7&amp;lt;/platform&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;/affected&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;description&amp;gt;
        By default, tickets obtained from the Kerberos environment must be forwardable.
      &amp;lt;/description&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/metadata&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;criteria operator=&amp;quot;AND&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;criterion test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:tst:1&amp;quot; comment=&amp;quot;Red Hat Enterprise Linux is installed&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
      &amp;lt;criterion test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:tst:2&amp;quot; comment=&amp;quot;/etc/krb5.conf&amp;#39;s libdefaults.forwardable is set to true&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;/criteria&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/definition&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/definitions&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to keep in mind is the (weird) identification structure. Just like with XCCDF, it is not sufficient to have your own id convention. You need to start an id with &lt;code&gt;oval:&lt;/code&gt; followed by the reverse domain definition (here &lt;code&gt;com.example.oval&lt;/code&gt;), followed by the type (&lt;code&gt;def&lt;/code&gt; for definition) and a sequence number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, take a look at the criteria. Here, two tests need to be compliant (hence the &lt;code&gt;AND&lt;/code&gt; operator). However, more complex operations can be done as well. It is even allowed to nest multiple criteria, and refer to previous definitions, like so (taken from the &lt;a href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/GovReady/ubuntu-scap/master/ssg-rhel6-oval.xml"&gt;ssg-rhel6-oval.xml file&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;criteria comment=&amp;quot;package hal removed or service haldaemon is not configured to start&amp;quot; operator=&amp;quot;OR&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;extend_definition comment=&amp;quot;hal removed&amp;quot; definition_ref=&amp;quot;oval:ssg:def:211&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;criteria operator=&amp;quot;AND&amp;quot; comment=&amp;quot;service haldaemon is not configured to start&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;criterion comment=&amp;quot;haldaemon runlevel 0&amp;quot; test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:ssg:tst:212&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;criterion comment=&amp;quot;haldaemon runlevel 1&amp;quot; test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:ssg:tst:213&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;criterion comment=&amp;quot;haldaemon runlevel 2&amp;quot; test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:ssg:tst:214&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;criterion comment=&amp;quot;haldaemon runlevel 3&amp;quot; test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:ssg:tst:215&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;criterion comment=&amp;quot;haldaemon runlevel 4&amp;quot; test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:ssg:tst:216&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;criterion comment=&amp;quot;haldaemon runlevel 5&amp;quot; test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:ssg:tst:217&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;criterion comment=&amp;quot;haldaemon runlevel 6&amp;quot; test_ref=&amp;quot;oval:ssg:tst:218&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/criteria&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/criteria&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, let's look at the tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;tests&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix:file_test id=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:tst:1&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot; check_existence=&amp;quot;all_exist&amp;quot; check=&amp;quot;all&amp;quot; comment=&amp;quot;/etc/redhat-release exists&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;unix:object object_ref=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:obj:1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/unix:file_test&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;ind:textfilecontent54_test id=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:tst:2&amp;quot; check=&amp;quot;all&amp;quot; check_existence=&amp;quot;all_exist&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot; comment=&amp;quot;The value of forwardable in /etc/krb5.conf&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;ind:object object_ref=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:obj:2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;ind:state state_ref=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:ste:2&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/ind:textfilecontent54_test&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/tests&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two tests defined here. The first test just checks if &lt;code&gt;/etc/redhat-release&lt;/code&gt; exists. If not, then the test will fail and the definition itself will result to false (as in, not compliant). This isn't actually a proper definition, because you want the test to not run when it is on a different platform, but for the sake of example and simplicity, let's keep it as is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second test will check for the value of the &lt;code&gt;forwardable&lt;/code&gt; key in &lt;code&gt;/etc/krb5.conf&lt;/code&gt;. For it, it refers to an object and a state. The test states that all objects must exist (&lt;code&gt;check_existence="all_exist"&lt;/code&gt;) and that all objects must match the state (&lt;code&gt;check="all"&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The object definition looks like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;objects&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix:file_object id=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:obj:1&amp;quot; comment=&amp;quot;The /etc/redhat-release file&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;unix:filepath&amp;gt;/etc/redhat-release&amp;lt;/unix:filepath&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/unix:file_object&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;ind:textfilecontent54_object id=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:obj:2&amp;quot; comment=&amp;quot;The forwardable key&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;ind:filepath&amp;gt;/etc/krb5.conf&amp;lt;/ind:filepath&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;ind:pattern operation=&amp;quot;pattern match&amp;quot;&amp;gt;^\s*forwardable\s*=\s*((true|false))\w*&amp;lt;/ind:pattern&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;ind:instance datatype=&amp;quot;int&amp;quot; operation=&amp;quot;equals&amp;quot;&amp;gt;1&amp;lt;/ind:instance&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/ind:textfilecontent54_object&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/objects&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first object is a simple file reference. The second is a text file content object. More specifically, it matches the line inside &lt;code&gt;/etc/krb5.conf&lt;/code&gt; which has &lt;code&gt;forwardable = true&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;forwardable = false&lt;/code&gt; in it. An expression is made on it, so that we can refer to the subexpression as part of the test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This test looks like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;states&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;ind:textfilecontent54_state id=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:ste:2&amp;quot; version=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;ind:subexpression datatype=&amp;quot;string&amp;quot;&amp;gt;true&amp;lt;/ind:subexpression&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/ind:textfilecontent54_state&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/states&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This test refers to a subexpression, and wants it to be &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Testing the checks with Open-SCAP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Open-SCAP tool is able to test OVAL statements directly. For instance, with the above definition in a file called &lt;code&gt;oval.xml&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~$ oscap oval eval --results oval-results.xml oval.xml
Definition oval:com.example.oval:def:1: true
Evaluation done.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The output of the command shows that the definition was evaluated successfully. If you want more information, open up the &lt;code&gt;oval-results.xml&lt;/code&gt; file which contains all the details about the test. This results file is also very useful while developing OVAL as it shows the entire result of objects, tests and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the &lt;code&gt;/etc/redhat-release&lt;/code&gt; file was only checked to see if it exists, but the results file shows what other parameters can be verified with it as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;unix-sys:file_item id=&amp;quot;1233781&amp;quot; status=&amp;quot;exists&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:filepath&amp;gt;/etc/redhat-release&amp;lt;/unix-sys:filepath&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:path&amp;gt;/etc&amp;lt;/unix-sys:path&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:filename&amp;gt;redhat-release&amp;lt;/unix-sys:filename&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:type&amp;gt;regular&amp;lt;/unix-sys:type&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:group_id datatype=&amp;quot;int&amp;quot;&amp;gt;0&amp;lt;/unix-sys:group_id&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:user_id datatype=&amp;quot;int&amp;quot;&amp;gt;0&amp;lt;/unix-sys:user_id&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:a_time datatype=&amp;quot;int&amp;quot;&amp;gt;1515186666&amp;lt;/unix-sys:a_time&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:c_time datatype=&amp;quot;int&amp;quot;&amp;gt;1514927465&amp;lt;/unix-sys:c_time&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:m_time datatype=&amp;quot;int&amp;quot;&amp;gt;1498674992&amp;lt;/unix-sys:m_time&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:size datatype=&amp;quot;int&amp;quot;&amp;gt;52&amp;lt;/unix-sys:size&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:suid datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:suid&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:sgid datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:sgid&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:sticky datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:sticky&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:uread datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;true&amp;lt;/unix-sys:uread&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:uwrite datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;true&amp;lt;/unix-sys:uwrite&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:uexec datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:uexec&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:gread datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;true&amp;lt;/unix-sys:gread&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:gwrite datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:gwrite&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:gexec datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:gexec&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:oread datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;true&amp;lt;/unix-sys:oread&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:owrite datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:owrite&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:oexec datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:oexec&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;unix-sys:has_extended_acl datatype=&amp;quot;boolean&amp;quot;&amp;gt;false&amp;lt;/unix-sys:has_extended_acl&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/unix-sys:file_item&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this is just on OVAL level. The final step is to link it in the XCCDF file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Referring to OVAL in XCCDF&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The XCCDF Rule entry allows for a &lt;code&gt;check&lt;/code&gt; element, which refers to an automated check for compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the above rule could be referred to like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Rule id=&amp;quot;xccdf_com.example_rule_krb5-forwardable-true&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Enable forwardable tickets on RHEL systems&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
  ...
  &amp;lt;check system=&amp;quot;http://oval.mitre.org/XMLSchema/oval-definitions-5&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;check-content-ref href=&amp;quot;oval.xml&amp;quot; name=&amp;quot;oval:com.example.oval:def:1&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/check&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/Rule&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this set in the Rule, Open-SCAP can validate it while checking the configuration baseline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~$ oscap xccdf eval --oval-results --results xccdf-results.xml xccdf.xml
...
Title   Enable forwardable kerberos tickets in krb5.conf libdefaults
Rule    xccdf_com.example_rule_krb5-forwardable-tickets
Ident   RHEL7-01007
Result  pass
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge advantage here is that, alongside the detailed results of the run, there is also better human readable output as it shows the title of the Rule being checked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The detailed capabilities of OVAL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above example I've used two examples: a file validation (against &lt;code&gt;/etc/redhat-release&lt;/code&gt;) and a file content one (against &lt;code&gt;/etc/krb5.conf&lt;/code&gt;). However, OVAL has many more checks and support for it, and also has constraints that you need to be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://github.com/OVALProject/Language/tree/master/docs"&gt;OVAL Project&lt;/a&gt; github account, the Language repository keeps track of the current documentation. By browsing through it, you'll notice that the OVAL capabilities are structured based on the target technology that you can check. Right now, this is AIX, Android, Apple iOS, Cisco ASA, Cisco CatOS, VMWare ESX, FreeBSD, HP-UX, Cisco iOS and iOS-XE, Juniper JunOS, Linux, MacOS, NETCONF, Cisco PIX, Microsoft SharePoint, Unix (generic), Microsoft Windows, and independent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://github.com/OVALProject/Language/blob/master/docs/independent-definitions-schema.md"&gt;independent&lt;/a&gt; one contains tests and support for resources that are often reusable toward different platforms (as long as your OVAL and XCCDF supporting tools can run it on those platforms). A few notable supporting tests are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;filehash58_test&lt;/code&gt; which can check for a number of common hashes (such as SHA-512 and MD5). This is useful when you want to make sure that a particular (binary or otherwise) file is available on the system. In enterprises, this could be useful for license files, or specific library files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;textfilecontent54_test&lt;/code&gt; which can check the content of a file, with support for regular expressions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;xmlfilecontent_test&lt;/code&gt; which is a specialized test toward XML files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind though that, as we have seen above, INI files specifically have no specialization available. It would be nice if CISecurity would develop support for common textual data formats, such as CSV (although that one is easily interpretable with the existing ones), JSON, YAML and INI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://github.com/OVALProject/Language/blob/master/docs/unix-definitions-schema.md"&gt;unix&lt;/a&gt; one contains tests specific to Unix and Unix-like operating systems (so yes, it is also useful for Linux), and together with the &lt;a href="https://github.com/OVALProject/Language/blob/master/docs/linux-definitions-schema.md"&gt;linux&lt;/a&gt; one a wide range of configurations can be checked. This includes support for generic extended attributes (&lt;code&gt;fileextendedattribute_test&lt;/code&gt;) as well as SELinux specific rules (&lt;code&gt;selinuxboolean_test&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;selinuxsecuritycontext_test&lt;/code&gt;), network interface settings (&lt;code&gt;interface_test&lt;/code&gt;), runtime processes (&lt;code&gt;process58_test&lt;/code&gt;), kernel parameters (&lt;code&gt;sysctl_test&lt;/code&gt;), installed software tests (such as &lt;code&gt;rpminfo_test&lt;/code&gt; for RHEL and other RPM enabled operating systems) and more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Security"></category><category term="xccdf"></category><category term="oval"></category><category term="scap"></category><category term="baseline"></category></entry><entry><title>Documenting a rule</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-a-rule/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-24T20:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-24T20:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2018-01-24:/2018/01/documenting-a-rule/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-configuration-changes/"&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt; I talked about why configuration documentation is important. In the &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/structuring-a-configuration-baseline/"&gt;second post&lt;/a&gt; I looked into a good structure for configuration documentation of a technological service, and ended with an XCCDF template in which this documentation can be structured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to document the rules themselves, i.e. the actual content of a configuration baseline.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-configuration-changes/"&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt; I talked about why configuration documentation is important. In the &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/structuring-a-configuration-baseline/"&gt;second post&lt;/a&gt; I looked into a good structure for configuration documentation of a technological service, and ended with an XCCDF template in which this documentation can be structured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is to document the rules themselves, i.e. the actual content of a configuration baseline.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fine-grained rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While from a high-level point of view, configuration items could be documented in a coarse-grained manner, a proper configuration baseline documents rules very fine-grained. Let's first consider a bad example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All application code files are root-owned, with read-write privileges for owner and group, and executable where it makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While such a rule could be interpreted correctly, it also leaves room for misinterpretation and ambiguity. Furthermore, it is not explicit. What are application code files? Where are they stored? What about group ownership? The executable permission, when does that make sense? Does the rule also imply that there is no privilege for world-wide access, or does it just ignore that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better example (or set of examples) would be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/postgresql&lt;/code&gt; is recursively user-owned by root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/postgresql&lt;/code&gt; is recursively group-owned by root&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No files under &lt;code&gt;/opt/postgresql&lt;/code&gt; are executable except when specified further&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All files in &lt;code&gt;/opt/postgresql/bin&lt;/code&gt; are executable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/postgresql&lt;/code&gt; has &lt;code&gt;system_u:object_r:usr_t:s0&lt;/code&gt; as SELinux context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/postgresql/bin/postgres&lt;/code&gt; has &lt;code&gt;system_u:object_r:postgresql_exec_t:s0&lt;/code&gt; as SELinux context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And even that list is still not complete, but you get the gist. The focus here is to have fine-grained rules which are explicit and not ambiguous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the above configuration rule is still a "simple" permission set. Configuration baselines go further than that of course. They can act on file content ("no PAM configuration files can refer to pam_rootok.so except for runuser and su"), run-time processes ("The processes with /usr/sbin/sshd as command and with -D as option must run within the sshd_t SELinux domain"), database query results, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This granularity is especially useful later on when you want to automate compliance checks, because the more fine-grained a description is, the easier it is to develop and maintain checks on it. But before we look into remediation, let's document the rule a bit further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metadata on the rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's consider the following configuration rule:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/opt/postgresql/bin/postgres&lt;/code&gt; has &lt;code&gt;system_u:object_r:postgresql_exec_t:s0&lt;/code&gt; as SELinux context&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the configuration baseline, we don't just want to state that this is the rule, and be finished. We need to describe the rule in more detail, as was described in the &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/structuring-a-configuration-baseline/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. More specifically, we definitely want to
- know the rule's severity is, or how "bad" it would be if we detect a deviation from the rule
- have an indication if the rule is security-sensitive or more oriented to manageability
- a more elaborate description of the rule than just the title
- an indication why this rule is in place (what does it solve, fix or simplify)
- information on how to remediate if a deviation is found
- know if the rule is applicable to our environment or not&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The severity in the &lt;em&gt;Security Content Automation Protocol (SCAP)&lt;/em&gt; standard, which defines the XCCDF standard as well as OVAL and a few others like CVSS, uses the following possible values for severity: unknown, info, low, medium, high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To indicate if a rule is security-oriented or not, XCCDF's role attribute is best used. With the role attribute, you state if a rule is to be included in the final scoring (a weighted value given to the compliance of a system) or not. If it is, then it is security sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indication of a rule applicability in the environment might seem strange. If you document the configuration baseline, shouldn't it include only those settings you want? Well, yes and no. Personally, I like to include recommendations that we &lt;em&gt;do not follow&lt;/em&gt; in the baseline as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose for instance that an audit comes along and says you need to enable data encryption on the database. Let's put aside that an auditor should focus mainly/solely on the risks, and let the solutions be managed by the team (but be involved in accepting solutions of course), the team might do an assessment and find that data encryption on the database level (i.e. the database files are encrypted so non-DBA users with operating system interactive rights cannot read the data) is actually not going to remediate any risk, yet introduce more complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that situation, and assuming that the auditor agrees with a different control, you might want to add a rule to the configuration baseline about this. Either you document the wanted state (database files do not need to be encrypted), or you document the suggestion (database files should be encrypted) but explicitly state that you do not require or implement it, and document the reasoning for it. The rule is then augmented with references to the audit recommendation for historical reasons and to facilitate future discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, I know the rule "database files should be encrypted" is still ambiguous. The actual rule should be more specific to the technology).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documenting a rule in XCCDF&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In XCCDF, a rule is defined through the &lt;code&gt;Rule&lt;/code&gt; XML entity, and is placed within a &lt;code&gt;Group&lt;/code&gt;. The Group entities are used to structure the document, while the &lt;code&gt;Rule&lt;/code&gt; entities document specific configuration directives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The postgres related rule of above could be written as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Rule id=&amp;quot;xccdf_com.example_rule_pgsql-selinux-context&amp;quot;
      role=&amp;quot;full&amp;quot;
      selected=&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;
      weight=&amp;quot;5.1&amp;quot;
      severity=&amp;quot;high&amp;quot;
      cluster-id=&amp;quot;network&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;
    /opt/postgresql/bin/postgres has system_u:object_r:postgresql_exec_t:s0 as SELinux context
  &amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;description&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;xhtml:p&amp;gt;
      The postgres binary is the main binary of the PostgreSQL database daemon. Once started, it launches the necessary workers. To ensure that PostgreSQL runs in the proper SELinux domain (postgresql_t) its binary must be labeled with postgresql_exec_t.
    &amp;lt;/xhtml:p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;xhtml:p&amp;gt;
      The current state of the label can be obtained using stat, or even more simple, the -Z option to ls:
    &amp;lt;/xhtml:p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;xhtml:pre&amp;gt;~$ ls -Z /opt/postgresql/bin/postgres
-rwxr-xr-x. root root system_u:object_r:postgresql_exec_t:s0 /opt/postgresql/bin/postgres
    &amp;lt;/xhtml:pre&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/description&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;rationale&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;xhtml:p&amp;gt;
      The domain in which a process runs defines the SELinux controls that are active on the process. Services such as PostgreSQL have an established policy set that controls what a database service can and cannot do on the system.
    &amp;lt;/xhtml:p&amp;gt;
    &amp;lt;xhtml:p&amp;gt;
      If the PostgreSQL daemon does not run in the postgresql_t domain, then SELinux might either block regular activities of the database (service availability impact), block behavior that impacts its effectiveness (integrity issue) or allow behavior that shouldn&amp;#39;t be allowed. The latter can have significant consequences once a vulnerability is exploited.
    &amp;lt;/xhtml:p&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;/rationale&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;fixtext&amp;gt;
    Restore the context of the file using restorecon or chcon.
  &amp;lt;/fixtext&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;fix strategy=&amp;quot;restrict&amp;quot; system=&amp;quot;urn:xccdf:fix:script:sh&amp;quot;&amp;gt;restorecon /opt/postgresql/bin/postgres
  &amp;lt;/fix&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;ident system=&amp;quot;http://example.com/configbaseline&amp;quot;&amp;gt;pgsql-01032&amp;lt;/ident&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/Rule&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is lots of XML, it is easy to see what each element declares. The &lt;a href="https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Publications/nistir/7275/rev-4/final/documents/nistir-7275r4_updated-march-2012_clean.pdf"&gt;NIST IR 7275 document&lt;/a&gt; is a very good resource to continuously consult in order to find the right elements and their interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one element added that is "specific" to the content of this blog post series and not the XCCDF standard, namely the identification. As mentioned in an earlier post, organizations might have their own taxonomy for technical service identification, and requirements on how to number or identify rules. In the above example, the rule is identified as &lt;code&gt;pgsql-01032&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is another attribute in use above that might need more clarification: the weight of the rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abusing CVSS for configuration weight scoring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above example, a weight is given to the rule scoring (weight of 5.1). This number is obtained through a &lt;a href="https://www.first.org/cvss/calculator/3.0#CVSS:3.0/AV:N/AC:H/PR:N/UI:N/S:C/C:L/I:L/A:N/E:U/RL:O/CR:H/IR:H/AR:H/MAV:N/MAC:H/MPR:N/MUI:N/MS:U/MC:L/MI:N/MA:L"&gt;CVSS calculator&lt;/a&gt;, which is generally used to identify the risk of a security issue or vulnerability. CVSS stands for &lt;em&gt;Common Vulnerability Scoring System&lt;/em&gt; and is a popular way to weight security risks (which are then associated with vulnerability reports, &lt;em&gt;Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures (CVE)&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Misconfigurations can also be slightly interpreted as a security risk, although it requires some mental bridges. Rather than scoring the rule, you score the risk that it mitigates, and consider the worst thing that could happen if that rule is not implemented correctly. Now, worst-case thinking is subjective, so there will always be discussion on the weight of a rule. It is therefore important to have a consensus in the team (if the configuration baseline is team-owned) if this weight is actively used. Of course, an organization might choose to ignore the weight, or use a different scoring mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above situation, I scored what would happen if a vulnerability in PostgreSQL was successfully exploited, and SELinux couldn't mitigate the risk as the label of the file was wrong. The result of a wrong label &lt;em&gt;could be&lt;/em&gt; that the PostgreSQL service runs in a higher privileged domain, or even in an unconfined domain (no SELinux restrictions active), so there is a heightened risk of confidentiality loss (beyond the database) and even integrity risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the confidentiality risk is scored as low, and integrity even in between (base risk is low, but due to other constraints put in place integrity impact is reduced further) because PostgreSQL runs as a non-administrative user on the system, and perhaps because the organization uses dedicated systems for database hosting (so other services are not easily impacted).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, this is somewhat abusing the CVSS methodology, but is imo much more effective than trying to figure out your own scoring methodology. With CVSS, you start with scoring the risk regardless of context (CVSS Base), then adjust based on recent state or knowledge (CVSS Temporal), and finally adjust further with knowledge of the other settings or mitigating controls in place (CVSS Environmental).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I prefer to only use the CVSS Base scoring for configuration baselines, because the other two are highly depending on time (which is, for documentation, challenging) and the other controls (which is more of a concern for service technical documentation). So in my preferred situation, the rule would be scored as 5.4 rather than 5.1. But that's just me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isn't this CCE?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who use SCAP a bit more might already be thinking if I'm not reinventing the wheel here. After all, SCAP also has a standard called &lt;em&gt;Common Configuration Enumeration (CCE)&lt;/em&gt; which seems to be exactly what I'm doing here: enumerating the configuration of a technical service. And indeed, if you look at the &lt;a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/config/cce/index"&gt;CCE list&lt;/a&gt; you'll find a number of Excel sheets (sigh) that define common configurations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, for Red Hat Enterprise Linux v5, there is an enumeration identified as CCE-4361-2, which states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;File permissions for /etc/pki/tls/ldap should be set correctly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CCE description then goes on stating that this is a permission setting (CCE Parameter), which can be rectified with &lt;code&gt;chmod&lt;/code&gt; (CCE Technical Mechanism), and refers to a source for the setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, CCE has a number of downsides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, it isn't being maintained anymore. And although XCCDF itself is also a quite old standard, it is still being looked into (a draft new version is being prepared) and is actively used as a standard. Red Hat is investing time and resources into secure configurations and compliancy aligned with SCAP, and other vendors publish SCAP-specific resources as well. CCE however would be a list, and thus requires continuous management. That RHELv5 is the most recent RHEL CCE list is a bad thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, CCE's structure is for me insufficient to use in configuration baselines. XCCDF has a much more mature and elaborate set of settings for this. What CCE does is actually what I use in the above example as the organization-specific identifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there aren't many tools that actively use CCE, unlike CVSS, XCCDF, OVAL, CVSS and other standards under the SCAP umbrella, which are all still actively used and developed upon by tools such as Open-SCAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Profiling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before finishing this post, I want to talk about profiling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within an XCCDF benchmark, several profiles can be defined. In the XCCDF template I defined a single profile that covers all rules, but this can be fine-tuned to the needs of the organization. In XCCDF profiles, you can select individual rules (which ones are active for a profile and which ones aren't) and even fine-tune values for rules. This is called tailoring in XCCDF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A first use case for profiles is to group different rules based on the selected setup. In case of Nginx for instance, one can consider Nginx being used as either a reverse proxy, a static website hosting or a dynamic web application hosting. In all three cases, some rules will be the same, but several rules will be different. Within XCCDF, you can document all rules, and then use profiles to group the rules related to a particular service use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XCCDF allows for profile inheritance. This means that you can define a base Profile (all the rules that need to be applied, regardless of the service use) and then extend the profiles with individual rule selections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With profiles, you can also fine-tune values. For instance, you could have a password policy in place that states that passwords on internal machines have to be at least 10 characters long, but on DMZ systems they need to be at least 15 characters long. Instead of defining two rules, the rule could refer to a particular variable (Value in XCCDF) which is then selected based on the Profile. The value for a password length is then by default 10, but the Profile for DMZ systems selects the other value (15).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, value-based tailoring is imo already a more advanced use of XCCDF, and is best looked into when you also start using OVAL or other automated checks. The tailoring information is then passed on to the automated compliance check so that the right value is validated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Value-based tailoring also makes rules either more complex to write, or ambiguous to interpret without full profile awareness. Considering the password length requirement, the rule could become:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The /etc/pam.d/password-auth file must refer to pam_passwdqc.so for the password service with a minimal password length of 10 (default) or 15 (DMZ) for the N4 password category&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least the rule is specific. Another approach would be to document it as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The /etc/pam.d/password-auth file must refer to pam_passwdqc.so with the proper organizational password controls&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation of the rule might document the proper controls further, but the rule is much less specific. Later checks might report that a system fails this check, referring to the title, which is insufficient for engineers or administrators to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating the guide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To close off this post, let's finish with how to generate the guide based on an XCCDF document. Personally, I use two approaches for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first one is to rely on Open-SCAP. With Open-SCAP, you can generate guides easily:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~$ oscap xccdf generate guide xccdf.xml &amp;gt; ConfigBaseline.html
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second one, which I use more often, is a custom XSL style sheet, which also introduces the knowledge and interpretations of what this blog post series brings up (including the organizational identification). The end result is similar (the same content) but uses a structure/organization that is more in line with expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, in my company, the information security officers want to have a tabular overview of all the rules in a configuration baseline. So the XSL style sheet generates such a tabular overview, and uses in-documenting linking to the more elaborate descriptions of all the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/static/2018/xccdf.xsl"&gt;older version&lt;/a&gt; is online for those interested. It uses JavaScript as well (in case you are security sensitive you might want to look into it) to allow collapsing rule documentation for faster online viewing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The custom XSL has an additional advantage, namely that there is no dependency on Open-SCAP to generate the guides (even though it is perfectly possible to copy the XSL and continue). I can successfully generate the guide using &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=21714"&gt;Microsoft's msxml&lt;/a&gt; utility, using xsltproc, etc depending on the platform I'm on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Security"></category><category term="xccdf"></category><category term="scap"></category><category term="baseline"></category></entry><entry><title>Structuring a configuration baseline</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/structuring-a-configuration-baseline/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-17T09:10:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-17T09:10:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2018-01-17:/2018/01/structuring-a-configuration-baseline/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A good configuration baseline has a readable structure that allows all stakeholders to quickly see if the baseline is complete, as well as find a particular setting regardless of the technology. In this blog post, I'll cover a possible structure of the baseline which attempts to be sufficiently complete and technology agnostic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't read the blog post on &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-configuration-changes/"&gt;documenting configuration changes&lt;/a&gt;, it might be a good idea to do so as it declares the scope of configuration baselines and why I think XCCDF is a good match for this.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A good configuration baseline has a readable structure that allows all stakeholders to quickly see if the baseline is complete, as well as find a particular setting regardless of the technology. In this blog post, I'll cover a possible structure of the baseline which attempts to be sufficiently complete and technology agnostic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't read the blog post on &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-configuration-changes/"&gt;documenting configuration changes&lt;/a&gt;, it might be a good idea to do so as it declares the scope of configuration baselines and why I think XCCDF is a good match for this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chaptered documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned previously, a configuration baseline describes the configuration of a particular technological service (rather than a business service which is an integrated set of technologies and applications). To document and maintain the configuration state of the technology, I suggest the following eight chapters (to begin with):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Architecture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operating system and services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Software deployment and file system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical service settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Authentication, authorization, access control and auditing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service specific settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cryptographic services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data and information handling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within each chapter, sections can be declared depending on how the technology works. For instance, for database technologies one can have a distinction between system-wide settings, instance-specific settings and even database-specific settings. Or, if the organization has specific standards on user definitions, a chapter on "User settings" can be used. The above is just a suggestion in an attempt to cover most aspects of a configuration baseline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the sections of the chapter, rules are then defined which specify the actual configuration setting (or valid range) applicable to the technology. But the rule goes further than just a single-line configuration setting description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each rule should have a &lt;em&gt;unique identifier&lt;/em&gt; so that other documents can reliably link to the rules in the document. Although XCCDF has a convention for this, I feel that the XCCDF way here is more useful for technical referencing while the organization is better off with a more human addressable approach. So while a rule in XCCDF has the identifier &lt;code&gt;xccdf_com.example.postgresql_rule_selinux-enforcing&lt;/code&gt; the human addressable identifier would be &lt;code&gt;postgresql_selinux-enforcing&lt;/code&gt; or even &lt;code&gt;postgresql-00001&lt;/code&gt;. In the company that I work for, we already have a taxonomy for services and a decision to use numerical identifiers on the configuration baseline rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each rule should be properly described, documenting what the rule is for. In case of a ranged value, it should also document how this range can be properly applied. For instance, if the number of worker threads is based on the number of cores available in the system, document the formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each rule should also document the risk that it wants to mitigate (be it a security risk, or a manageability aspect of the service, or a performance related tuning parameter). This aspect of the baseline is important whenever an implementation wants an exception to the rule (not follow it) or a deviation (different value). Personally, to make sure that the baseline is manageable, I don't expect engineers to immediately fill in the risk in great detail, but rather holistically. The actual risk determination is then only done when an implementation wants an exception or deviation, and then includes a list of potential mitigating actions to take. This way, a 300+ rule document does not require all 300+ rules to have a risk determination, especially if only a dozen or so rules have exceptions or deviations in the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each rule should have sources linked to it. These sources help the reader understand what the rule is based on, such as a publicly available secure configuration baseline, an audit recommendation, a specific incident, etc. If the rule is also controversial, it might benefit from links to meeting minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each rule might have consequences listed as well. These are known changes or behavior aspects that follow the implementation of the rule. For instance, a rule might state that TLS mutual authentication is mandatory, and the consequence is that all interacting clients must have a properly defined certificate (so proper PKI requirements) as well as client registration in the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, and importantly as well, each rule identifies the scope at which exceptions or deviations can be granted. For smaller groups and organizations, this might not matter that much, but for larger organizations, some configuration baseline rules can be "approved" by a small team or by the application owner, while others need formal advise of a security officer and approval on a decision body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finding a balanced approval hierarchy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exception management for configuration baselines should not be underestimated. It is not viable to have all settings handled by top management decision bodies, but some configuration changes might result in such a huge impact that a formal decision needs to be taken somewhere, with proper accountability assigned (yes, this is the architect in me speaking).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than attempting to create a match for all rules, I again like to keep the decision here in the middle, just like I do with the risk determination. The maintainer of the configuration baseline can leave the "scope" of a rule open, and have an intermediate decision body as the main decision body. Whenever an exception or deviation is asked, the risk determination is made and filled in, and with this documented rule now complete a waiver is asked on the decision body. Together with the waiver request, the maintainer also asks this decision body if the rule in the future also needs to be granted on that decision body or elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope is most likely tied to the impact of the rule towards other services. A performance specific rule that only affects the application hosted on the technology can be easily scoped as being application-only. This means that the application or service owner can decide to deviate from the baseline. A waiver for a rule that influences system behavior might need to be granted by the system administrator (or team) as well as application or service owners that use this system. Following this logic, I generally use the following scope terminology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tbd (to be determined), meaning that there is no assessment done yet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;application, meaning that the impact is only on a single application and thus can be taken by the application owner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;instance, meaning that the impact is on an instance and thus might be broader than a single application, but is otherwise contained to the technology. Waivers are granted by the responsible system administrator and application owner(s)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;system, meaning that the impact is on the entire system and thus goes beyond the technology. Waivers are granted by the responsible system administrator, application owner(s) and with advise from a security officer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;network, meaning that the impact can spread to other systems or influence behavior of other systems, but remains technical in nature. Waivers are granted by an infrastructure architecture board with advise from a security officer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;organization, meaning that the impact goes beyond technical influence but also impacts business processes. Waivers are granted by an architecture board with advise from a security officer and senior service owner, and might even be redirected to a higher management board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;group, meaning that the impact influences multiple businesses. Waivers are granted by a specific management board&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each scope also has a "-pending" value, so "network-pending". This means that the owner of the configuration baseline suggests that this is the scope on which waivers can be established, but still needs to receive formal validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main decision body is then a particular infrastructure architecture board, which will redirect requests to other decision bodies if the scope goes beyond what that architecture board handles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Architectural settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first chapter in a baseline is perhaps the more controversial one, as it is not a technical setting and hard to validate. However, in my experience, tying architectural constraints in a configuration baseline is much more efficient than having a separate track for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, I strongly believe that architecture deviations are like configuration deviations. They should be documented similarly, and follow the same path as configuration baseline deviations. The scope off architectural rules are also all over the place, from application-level impact up to organization-wide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, architectural positioning of services should not be solely an (infrastructure) architecture concern, but supported by the other stakeholders as well, and especially the responsible for the technology service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, a rule could be that no databases should be positioned within an organizations &lt;em&gt;DeMilitarized Zone (DMZ)&lt;/em&gt;, which is a network design that shields off internally positioned services from the outside world. Although this is not a configuration setting, it makes sense to place it in the configuration baseline of the database technology. There are several ways to validate automatically if this rule is followed, depending for instance the organization IP plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another rule could be that web applications that host browser-based applications should only be linked through a reverse proxy, or that a load balancer must be put in front of an application server, etc. This might result in additional rules in the chapter that covers access control as well (such as having a particular IP filter in place), but these rules are the consequence of the architectural positioning of the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operating system and services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second chapter covers settings specific to the operating system on which the technology is deployed. Such settings can be system-wide settings like Linux' sysctl parameters, services which need to be enabled or disabled when the technology is deployed, and deviations from the configuration baseline of the operating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example of the latter depends of course on the configuration baseline of the operating system (assuming this is a baseline for a technology deployed on top of an operating system, it could very well be a different platform). Suppose for instance that the baseline has the &lt;code&gt;squashfs&lt;/code&gt; kernel module disabled, but the technology itself requires squashfs, then a waiver is needed. This is the level where this is documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another setting could be an extension of the SSH configuration (the term "services" in the chapter title here focuses on system services, such as OpenSSH), or the implementation of additional audit rules on OS-level (although auditing can also be covered in a different section).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software deployment and file system&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third chapter focuses on the installation of the technology itself, and the file system requirements related to the technology service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rules here look into file ownership and permissions, mount settings, and file system declarations. Some baselines might even define rules about integrity of certain files (the &lt;em&gt;Open Vulnerability and Assessment Language (OVAL)&lt;/em&gt; supports checksum-based validations) although I think this is better tackled through a specific integrity process. Still, if such an integrity process does not exist and automated validation of baselines is implemented, then integrity validation of critical files could be in scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical service settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fourth chapter, settings are declared regarding the service without being service-specific. A service-specific setting is one that requires functional knowledge of the service, whereas technical service settings can be interpreted without functionally understanding the technology at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's take PostgreSQL as an example. A service-specific setting would be the maximum number of non-frozen transaction IDs before a VACUUM operation is triggered (the &lt;code&gt;autovacuum_freeze_max_age&lt;/code&gt; parameter). If you are not working with PostgreSQL much, then this makes as much sense as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prisencolinensinainciusol"&gt;Prisencolinensinainciusol&lt;/a&gt;. It sounds like English, but that's about as far as you get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A technical service setting on PostgreSQL that is likely more understandable is the runtime account under which the database runs (you don't want it to run as root), or the TCP port on which it listens. Although both are technical in nature, they're much more understandable for others and, perhaps the most important reason of all, often more reusable in deployments across technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reusability is key for larger organizations as they will have numerous technologies to support, and the technical service settings offer a good baseline for initial secure setup. They focus on the runtime account of the service, the privileges of the runtime account (be it capability-based on Linux or account rights on Windows), the interfaces on which the service is reachable, the protocol or protocols it supports, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authentication, authorization, access control and auditing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next chapter focuses on the &lt;em&gt;Authentication, Authorization and Accounting (AAA)&lt;/em&gt; services, but slightly worded differently (AAA is commonly used in networking related setups, I just borrow it and extend it). If the configuration baseline is extensive, then it might make sense to have separate sections for each of these security concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some technologies have a strong focus on user management as well. In that case, it might make sense to first describe the various types of users that the technology supports (like regular users, machine users, internal service users, shared users, etc.) and then, per user type, document how these security services act on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service specific settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next chapter covers settings that are very specific to the service. These are often the settings that are found in the best practices documentation, secure deployment instructions of the vendor, performance tuning parameters, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tend to look first at the base configuration and administration guides for technologies, and see what the main structure is that those documents follow. Often, this can be borrowed for the configuration baseline. Next, consider performance related tuning, as that is often service specific and not related to the other chapters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cryptographic services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this chapter, the focus is on the cryptographic services and configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most well-known example here is related to any TLS configuration and tuning. Whereas the location of the private key (used for TLS services) is generally mentioned in the third chapter (or at least the secure storage of the private key), this section will focus on using this properly. It looks at selecting proper TLS version, making a decent and manageable set of ciphers to support, enabling &lt;em&gt;Online Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP)&lt;/em&gt; on web servers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But services often use cryptographic related algorithms in various other places as well. Databases can provide transparent data file encryption to ensure that offline access to the database files does not result in data leakage for instance. Or they implement column-level encryption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application servers might support crypto related routines to the applications they host, and the configuration baseline can then identify which crypto modules are supported and which ones aren't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Services might be using cryptographic hashes which are configurable, or could be storing user passwords in a database using configurable settings. OpenLDAP for instance supports multiple hashing methods (and also supports storing in plain-text if you want this), so it makes sense to select a hashing method that is hard to brute-force (slow to compute for instance) and is salted (to make certain types of attacks more challenging).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the service makes use of stored credentials or keytabs, document how they are protected here as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data and information handling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Information handling covers both the regular data management activities (like backup/restore, data retention, archival, etc.) as well as sensitive information handling (to comply with privacy rules).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regular data management related settings look into both the end user data handling (as far as this is infrastructurally related - this isn't meant to become a secure development guide) as well as service-internal data handling. When the technology is meant to handle data (like a database or LDAP) then certain related settings could be both in the service specific settings chapter or in this one. Personally, I tend to prefer that technology-specific and non-reusable settings are in the former, while the data and information handling chapter covers the integration and technology-agnostic data handling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the service handles sensitive information, it is very likely that additional constraints or requirements were put in place beyond the "traditional" cryptographic requirements. Although such requirements are often implemented on the application level (like tagging the data properly and then, based on the tags, handle specific fine-grained access controls, archival and data retention), more and more technologies provide out-of-the-box (or at least reusable) methods that can be configured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An XCCDF template&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support the above structure, I've made an &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/static/2018/xccdf-template.xml"&gt;XCCDF template&lt;/a&gt; that might be a good start for documenting the configuration baseline of a technology. It also structures the chapters a bit more with various sections, but those are definitely not mandatory to use as it strongly depends on the technology being documented, the maturity of the organization, etc.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Security"></category><category term="xccdf"></category><category term="scap"></category><category term="baseline"></category></entry><entry><title>Documenting configuration changes</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2018/01/documenting-configuration-changes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-07T21:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-07T21:20:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2018-01-07:/2018/01/documenting-configuration-changes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;IT teams are continuously under pressure to set up and maintain infrastructure services quickly, efficiently and securely. As an infrastructure architect, my main concerns are related to the manageability of these services and the secure setup. And within those realms, a properly documented configuration setup is in my opinion very crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post series, I'm going to look into using the &lt;em&gt;Extensible Configuration Checklist Description Format (XCCDF)&lt;/em&gt; as the way to document these. This first post is an introduction to XCCDF functionally, and what I position it for.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;IT teams are continuously under pressure to set up and maintain infrastructure services quickly, efficiently and securely. As an infrastructure architect, my main concerns are related to the manageability of these services and the secure setup. And within those realms, a properly documented configuration setup is in my opinion very crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post series, I'm going to look into using the &lt;em&gt;Extensible Configuration Checklist Description Format (XCCDF)&lt;/em&gt; as the way to document these. This first post is an introduction to XCCDF functionally, and what I position it for.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation is a good thing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the ongoing struggle for time and resources, documenting configurations and architectures is often not top-of-mind. However, the lack of this information also leads to various problems: incidents due to misconfiguration, slow recovery timings due to incomprehensible setups, and not to forget: meetings. Yes, meetings, which are continuously discussing service aspects that influence one or more parameters, without any good traceability of past decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some technologies allow to keep track of some metadata regarding to configurations. In configuration management tools like &lt;a href="https://puppet.com"&gt;Puppet&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://saltstack.com"&gt;Saltstack&lt;/a&gt; engineers define the target state of their infrastructure, and the configuration management tool enforces this state on the service. Engineers can add in historical information as comments into these systems, and use version control on the files to have traceability of the settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, although in-line comments are very important, even for configuration sets, it is not a full documentation approach. In larger environments, where you are regularly audited for quality and security, or where multiple roles and stakeholders need to understand the settings and configuration of services, pointing to the code is not going to cut it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Configuration items need to be documented not solely with the documentation rule itself, but with the motivation related to it, and additional fields of interest depending on how the organization deals with it. This documentation can then be referred to from the configuration management infrastructure (so engineers and technical stakeholders can trace back settings) but also vice-versa: the documentation can refer to the configuration management implementation (so other stakeholders can deduce how the settings are implemented or even enforced).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a proper configuration document at hand, especially if it is supported through the configuration management tool(s) in the organization (regardless if it is one or multiple), it is much easier to have the necessary interviews with auditors, project leaders, functional and technical analysts, architects or even remote support teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two-part documentation hierarchy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to decide upon is at which level a team will document the settings. Is a single document possible for all infrastructure services? Most likely not. I believe that settings should be documented on the technology level (as it is specific to a particular technology) and on the 'business service' level (as it is specific to a particular implementation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the technology level, we're talking about configuration documentation for "PostgreSQL", "Apache Knox" or "Nginx". At this level, the baseline is defined for a technology. The resulting document is then the &lt;em&gt;configuration baseline&lt;/em&gt; for that component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the business service level, we're talking about configuration documentation for a particular service that is a combination of multiple implementations. For instance, a company intranet portal service is operationally implemented through a reverse proxy (HAProxy), an intelligent load balancer (Seesaw), next-gen firewall (pfSense), web server (Nginx), application server (Node.js), database (PostgreSQL), and operating systems (Linux). And more technologies come into play when we consider software deployment, monitoring, backup/restore, software-defined network, storage provisioning, archival solutions, license management services, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, a configuration document should be available on this service level ("company intranet portal") which defines the usage profile of a service (more about that later) and the specific parameters related to this service, but only when they either deviate from the configuration baseline, or take a particular value within a range defined in the configuration baseline. This document is the &lt;em&gt;service technical configuration&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as an example, on the Nginx configuration baseline, a rule might state that the maximum file size per upload is 12M (through the &lt;code&gt;client_max_body_size&lt;/code&gt; parameter). If the service has no problem with this rule, then it does not need to be documented on the service technical configuration. However, if this needs to be adapted (say that for the company portal the maximum file size is 64M) then it is documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example is a ranged setting, where the baseline identifies a set of valid values and the service technical configuration makes a particular selection. For instance, the Nginx configuration baseline might mention that there must be between 5 and 50 worker processes (through the &lt;code&gt;worker_processes&lt;/code&gt; parameter). In the service technical configuration the particular value is then selected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an architecture and security point of view, the first example is a deviation which must consider the risks and consequences that are applicable to the rule. These are (or should be) documented in the configuration baseline, including where this deviation can be approved (assuming the organization has a decision body for such things). The second example is not a deviation and, as such, is free to be chosen by the implementation team. The configuration baseline will generally inform the implementation teams about how to pick a proper value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service usage profiles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've talked about a &lt;em&gt;service usage profile&lt;/em&gt; earlier up, but didn't expand on it yet. So, what are these service usage profiles?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, most technologies can be implemented for a number of targets and functional purposes. A database could be implemented as a dedicated service (one set of databases on a dedicated set of instances for a single business service) or a shared service (multiple databases, possibly on multiple instances for several business services). It can be tuned for online transactional purposes (OLTP) or online analytical processing (OLAP), often through data warehouse designs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A service usage profile is part of the configuration baseline, with settings specific to that particular usage. So for a database the engineering team responsible for the database technology setup might devise that the following usage profiles are applicable to their component:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dedicated OLTP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shared OLTP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dedicated DWH&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shared DWH&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each usage profile has a number of configuration settings (of which many, if not most, are shared across other usage profiles) and a range of valid values (fine-tuning for a service). The service technical configuration for a particular business service then selects the particular usage profile. For instance, the company intranet portal might use a Dedicated OLTP usage profile for its PostgreSQL database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How XCCDF supports this structure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now, I've only spoken about the values related to configuration documentation, and a high-level introduction to the hierarchy on the configurations. But how does the &lt;a href="https://scap.nist.gov/specifications/xccdf/"&gt;Extensible Configuration Checklist Description&lt;/a&gt; position itself in this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A number of reasons why XCCDF is a valid choice for configuration documentation are given next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XCCDF allows technical writers to write the documentation in (basic) HTML while still linking the documentation to specific rules. Rather than having to use a tabular expression on all the valid configuration sets (like using a large spreadsheet table for all rules) and trying to force some documentation in it (Excel is not a text editor), XCCDF uses a hierarchical approach to structure documentation in logical sections (which it calls &lt;em&gt;Groups&lt;/em&gt;) and then refers to the rules applicable to that section (using the &lt;em&gt;Rule&lt;/em&gt; identifier).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XCCDF has out-of-the-box support for service profiles (through &lt;em&gt;Profile&lt;/em&gt; declarations). Fine-tuning and selecting profiles is called &lt;em&gt;tailoring&lt;/em&gt; in XCCDF. This also includes support for ranged values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XCCDF is meant to (but does not have to) refer to the (automated or interview-based) validation of the rules as well. Automated validation of settings means that an engine can read the XCCDF document (and the referred statements) and check if an implementation adheres to the baseline. The standard for this is called &lt;em&gt;Open Vulnerability and Assessment Language (OVAL)&lt;/em&gt;, and a popular free software engine for this is &lt;a href="https://www.open-scap.org"&gt;OpenSCAP&lt;/a&gt;. The standard for interview-based validation is &lt;em&gt;Open Checklist Interactive Language (OCIL)&lt;/em&gt;. I have not played around with OCIL and supporting tooling, so comments on this are always welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XCCDF is an XML-based format, so its "source code" can easily be versioned in common version control systems like Git. This allows organizations to not only track changes on the documentation, but also have an active development lifecycle management on the configuration documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XCCDFs schema implies a set of metadata to be defined during various declarations. It includes support for the &lt;a href="http://www.dublincore.org/specifications/"&gt;Dublin core metadata&lt;/a&gt; terms for content, references to link other resources structurally, and most importantly has a wide set of supporting entities for rules (which is the level on which configuration items are documented). This includes the rationale (why is the rule defined as is), fix text (human readable), fix (machine readable), rule role (is it security-sensitive and as such must be taken up in a security assessment report or not), severity (how bad is it if this rule is not followed), and many more. This both forces the user to consider the consequences of the rule, as well as guide the writer into properly structured documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XCCDF also suggests a number of classes for the documentation to standardize certain information types. This includes warnings, critical text, examples, and instructions. Such semantic declarations allow for a more uniform set of documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a few constraints exist that you need to be aware of when approaching XCCDF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XCCDF is an XML-based document format, and although NIST offers the necessary XML Schema definitions, writing proper XML has always been a challenge for many people. Also, no decent GUI or WYSIWYG tool that manages XCCDF files exists in my opinion. Yes, we have the &lt;a href="https://www.open-scap.org/tools/scap-workbench/"&gt;SCAP Workbench&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="https://www.g2-inc.com/scap.html"&gt;eSCAPe editor&lt;/a&gt;, but I feel that they are not as effective as they should be. As a result, the team or teams that write the baselines should either be XML-savvy, or you need to provide supporting infrastructure and services for it. However, YMMV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the organization is not interested in compliance checks themselves (i.e. automated validation of adherence to the configuration baseline and service technical configuration) then XCCDF will entail too much overhead versus just having a template or approach (such as documenting items in a wiki). However, with some support (and perhaps automation) writing and maintaining XCCDF based configuration baselines becomes much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past I've &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/tag/xccdf/"&gt;blogged about XCCDF&lt;/a&gt; already, but that was with a previous blog technology and the migration wasn't as successful as I originally thought. XML snippets were all removed, and I'm too lazy to go back to my backups from 2013 and individually correct blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good resource on XCCDF is the &lt;a href="https://csrc.nist.gov/CSRC/media/Publications/nistir/7275/rev-4/final/documents/nistir-7275r4_updated-march-2012_clean.pdf"&gt;NIST IR-7275 publication (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; which covers the XCCDF standard in much detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Center for Internet Security (CISecurity) maintains more than a hundred &lt;a href="https://www.cisecurity.org/cis-benchmarks/"&gt;CIS Benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;, all available for free as PDFs, and are often based on XCCDF (available to subscribed members).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next blog post, I'll talk about the in-document structure of a good configuration baseline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Security"></category><category term="xccdf"></category><category term="scap"></category><category term="baseline"></category></entry><entry><title>Putting OVAL at work</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/08/putting-oval-at-work/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-01T15:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-08-01T15:01:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-08-01:/2013/08/putting-oval-at-work/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When we look at the &lt;a href="http://scap.nist.gov/"&gt;SCAP security standards&lt;/a&gt;,
you might get the feeling of "How does this work". The underlying
interfaces, like OVAL and XCCDF, might seem a bit daunting to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is correct, but you need to remember that the standards are
protocols, agreements that can be made &lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When we look at the &lt;a href="http://scap.nist.gov/"&gt;SCAP security standards&lt;/a&gt;,
you might get the feeling of "How does this work". The underlying
interfaces, like OVAL and XCCDF, might seem a bit daunting to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is correct, but you need to remember that the standards are
protocols, agreements that can be made across products so that several
products, each with their own expertise, can work together easily. It is
a matter of interoperability between components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at the following diagram to see how OVAL and XCCDF &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be
used. I'm not saying this is the only way forward, but it is a possible
approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Diagram lost during blog conversion)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the local side (and local here doesn't mean a single server, but
rather an organization or company) a list of checks is maintained. These
checks are OVAL checks, which can be downloaded from reputable sites
like NVD or are given to you by vendors (some vendors provide OVAL as
part of vulnerability reports). Do not expect this list to be hundreds
of checks - start small, the local database of checks will grow anyhow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage is that the downloaded checks (OVALs) already have a
unique identifier (the OVAL ID). For instance, the check "Disable Java
in Firefox" for Windows is &lt;code&gt;oval:org.mitre.oval:def:12609&lt;/code&gt;. If
additional Windows operating systems are added, this ID remains the same
(it is updated) because the check (and purpose) remains the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locally, the OVAL checks are ran against targets by an OVAL interpreter.
Usually, you will have multiple interpreters in the organization, some
of them focused on desktops, some on servers, some perhaps on network
equipment, etc. By itself that doesn't matter, as long as they interpret
the OVAL checks. The list of targets to check against are usually
managed in a configuration management database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Targets can be of various granularity. The "Disable Java in Firefox"
will be against an operating system (where the check then sees if the
installed Firefox indeed has the setting disabled), but a check that
validates the permissions (rights) of a user will be against this user
account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results of the OVAL checks are stored in a database that maps the
result against the target. By itself this result database does not
contain much more logic than "This rule is OK against this target and
that rule isn't" (well, there is some granularity, but not much more)
and the time stamp when this was done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next comes the XCCDF. XCCDF defines the state that you want the system
to be in. It is a benchmark, a document describing how the system /
target should be configured. XCCDF documents usually contain the whole
shebang of configuration settings, and then differentiate them based on
profiles. For instance, a web server attached to the Internet might have
a different profile than a web server used internally or for development
purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The XCCDF document refers to OVAL checks, and thus uses the results from
the OVAL result database to see if a target is fully aligned with the
requirements or not. The XCCDF results themselves are also stored, often
together with exceptions (if any) that are approved (for instance, you
want to keep track of the workstations where Java &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; enabled in
Firefox and only report for those systems where it is enabled by the
user without approval). Based on these results, reports can be generated
on the state of your park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all checks are already available as OVAL checks. Of course you can
write them yourself, but there are also other possibilities. Next to
OVAL, there are (less standardized) methods for doing checks which
integrate with XCCDF as well. The idea you'll need to focus on then is
the same as with OVAL: what is your source, how do you store it, you
need interpreters that can "play" it, and on the reporting side you'll
need to store the results so you can combine them later in your
reporting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Security"></category><category term="baseline"></category><category term="benchmark"></category><category term="oval"></category><category term="security"></category><category term="xccdf"></category></entry></feed>