<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - openssh</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/openssh/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2017-05-18T18:20:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Matching MD5 SSH fingerprint</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2017/05/matching-md5-ssh-fingerprint/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-18T18:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-18T18:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-05-18:/2017/05/matching-md5-ssh-fingerprint/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I was attempting to update a local repository, when SSH complained
about a changed fingerprint, something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@
@    WARNING: REMOTE HOST IDENTIFICATION HAS CHANGED!     @
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@
IT IS POSSIBLE THAT SOMEONE IS DOING SOMETHING NASTY!
Someone could be eavesdropping on you right now (man-in-the-middle attack)!
It is also possible that a host key has just been changed.
The fingerprint for the ECDSA key sent by the remote host is
SHA256:p4ZGs+YjsBAw26tn2a+HPkga1dPWWAWX+NEm4Cv4I9s.
Please contact your system administrator.
Add correct host key in /home/user/.ssh/known_hosts to get rid of this message.
Offending ECDSA key in /home/user/.ssh/known_hosts:9
ECDSA host key for 192.168.56.101 has changed and you have requested strict checking.
Host key verification failed.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I was attempting to update a local repository, when SSH complained
about a changed fingerprint, something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@
@    WARNING: REMOTE HOST IDENTIFICATION HAS CHANGED!     @
@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@
IT IS POSSIBLE THAT SOMEONE IS DOING SOMETHING NASTY!
Someone could be eavesdropping on you right now (man-in-the-middle attack)!
It is also possible that a host key has just been changed.
The fingerprint for the ECDSA key sent by the remote host is
SHA256:p4ZGs+YjsBAw26tn2a+HPkga1dPWWAWX+NEm4Cv4I9s.
Please contact your system administrator.
Add correct host key in /home/user/.ssh/known_hosts to get rid of this message.
Offending ECDSA key in /home/user/.ssh/known_hosts:9
ECDSA host key for 192.168.56.101 has changed and you have requested strict checking.
Host key verification failed.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;




&lt;p&gt;I checked if the host was changed recently, or the alias through
which I connected switched host, or the SSH key changed. But that
wasn't the case. Or at least, it wasn't the case recently, and I
distinctly remember connecting to the same host two weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, what happened I don't know yet, but I do know I didn't want
to connect until I reviewed the received SSH key fingerprint. I
obtained the fingerprint from the administration (who graceously
documented it on the wiki)...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... only to realize that the documented fingerprint are MD5
hashes (and in hexadecimal result) whereas the key shown by the
SSH command shows it in base64 SHA256 by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, a quick search revealed this &lt;a href="https://superuser.com/questions/929566/sha256-ssh-fingerprint-given-by-the-client-but-only-md5-fingerprint-known-for-se"&gt;superuser&lt;/a&gt;
post which told me to connect to the host using the
&lt;code&gt;FingerprintHash md5&lt;/code&gt; option:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;~$ ssh -o FingerprintHash=md5 192.168.56.11
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The result is SSH displaying the MD5 hashed fingerprint which I
can now validate against the documented one. Once I validated that
the key is the correct one, I accepted the change and continued
with my endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I later discovered (or, more precisely, have strong assumptions)
that I had an old elliptic curve key registered in my &lt;code&gt;known_hosts&lt;/code&gt;
file, which was not used for the communication for quite some time.
I recently re-enabled elliptic curve support in OpenSSH (with Gentoo's
USE="-bindist") which triggered the validation of the old key.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="openssh"></category><category term="fingerprint"></category><category term="md5"></category></entry><entry><title>Using multiple OpenSSH daemons</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2015/09/using-multiple-openssh-daemons/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-06T16:37:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-06T16:37:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-09-06:/2015/09/using-multiple-openssh-daemons/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I administer a couple of systems which provide interactive access by end users,
and for this interactive access I position &lt;a href="http://www.openssh.com/"&gt;OpenSSH&lt;/a&gt;. 
However, I also use this for administrative access to the system, and I tend to
have harder security requirements for OpenSSH than most users do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, on one system, end users with a userid + password use the
sFTP server for publishing static websites. Other access is prohibited,
so I really like this OpenSSH configuration to use chrooted users, internal
sftp support, whereas a different OpenSSH is used for administrative access
(which is only accessible by myself and some trusted parties).&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I administer a couple of systems which provide interactive access by end users,
and for this interactive access I position &lt;a href="http://www.openssh.com/"&gt;OpenSSH&lt;/a&gt;. 
However, I also use this for administrative access to the system, and I tend to
have harder security requirements for OpenSSH than most users do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, on one system, end users with a userid + password use the
sFTP server for publishing static websites. Other access is prohibited,
so I really like this OpenSSH configuration to use chrooted users, internal
sftp support, whereas a different OpenSSH is used for administrative access
(which is only accessible by myself and some trusted parties).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Running multiple instances&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I might get a similar result with a single OpenSSH instance, I
prefer to have multiple instances for this. The default OpenSSH port is used
for the non-administrative access whereas administrative access is on a
non-default port. This has a number of advantages...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, the SSH configurations are simple and clean. No complex
configurations, and more importantly: easy to manage through configuration
management tools like &lt;a href="http://saltstack.com/"&gt;SaltStack&lt;/a&gt;, my current favorite
orchestration/automation tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different instances also allow for different operational support services.
There is different monitoring for end-user SSH access versus administrative
SSH access. Also the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Fail2ban"&gt;fail2ban&lt;/a&gt; configuration
is different for these instances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can also easily shut down the non-administrative service while ensuring that
administrative access remains operational - something important in case of
changes and maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dealing with multiple instances and SELinux&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond enabling a non-default port for SSH (i.e. by marking it as &lt;code&gt;ssh_port_t&lt;/code&gt;
as well) there is little additional tuning necessary, but that doesn't mean that
there is no additional tuning possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, we could leverage MCS' categories to only allow users (and thus the
SSH daemon) access to the files assigned only that category (and not the rest)
whereas the administrative SSH daemon can access all categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On an MLS enabled system we could even use different sensitivity levels, allowing
the administrative SSH to access the full scala whereas the user-facing SSH can
only access the lowest sensitivity level. But as I don't use MLS myself, I won't go
into detail for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A third possibility would be to fine-tune the permissions of the SSH daemons. However,
that would require different types for the daemon, which requires the daemons to be
started through different scripts (so that we first transition to dedicated 
types) before they execute the SSHd binary (which has the &lt;code&gt;sshd_exec_t&lt;/code&gt; type
assigned).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requiring pubkey and password authentication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent OpenSSH daemons allow &lt;a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/544640/"&gt;chaining multiple authentication methods&lt;/a&gt;
before access is granted. This allows the systems to force SSH key authentication first, and then -
after succesful authentication - require the password to be passed on as well. Or a
second step such as &lt;a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Google_Authenticator"&gt;Google Authenticator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;AuthenticationMethods publickey,password
PasswordAuthentication yes
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don't use the Google Authenticator, but the &lt;a href="https://developers.yubico.com/yubico-pam/"&gt;Yubico PAM module&lt;/a&gt;
to require additional authentication through my U2F dongle (so ssh key, password
and u2f key). Don't consider this three-factor authentication: one thing I know
(password) and two things I have (U2F and ssh key). It's more that I have a couple
of devices with a valid SSH key (laptop, tablet, mobile) which are of course targets
for theft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chance that both one of those devices is stolen &lt;em&gt;together&lt;/em&gt; with the U2F
dongle (which I don't keep attached to those devices of course) is somewhat less.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="openssh"></category><category term="ssh"></category><category term="u2f"></category><category term="selinux"></category></entry><entry><title>Switching OpenSSH to ed25519 keys</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2015/08/switching-openssh-to-ed25519-keys/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-19T18:26:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-08-19T18:26:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-08-19:/2015/08/switching-openssh-to-ed25519-keys/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With Mike's &lt;a href="http://comments.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/96896"&gt;news item&lt;/a&gt;
on OpenSSH's deprecation of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Signature_Algorithm"&gt;DSA algorithm&lt;/a&gt;
for the public key authentication, I started switching the few keys I still had
using DSA to the suggested &lt;a href="http://ed25519.cr.yp.to/"&gt;ED25519&lt;/a&gt; algorithm. Of
course, I wouldn't be a security-interested party if I did not do some additional
investigation into the DSA versus Ed25519 discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With Mike's &lt;a href="http://comments.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/96896"&gt;news item&lt;/a&gt;
on OpenSSH's deprecation of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Signature_Algorithm"&gt;DSA algorithm&lt;/a&gt;
for the public key authentication, I started switching the few keys I still had
using DSA to the suggested &lt;a href="http://ed25519.cr.yp.to/"&gt;ED25519&lt;/a&gt; algorithm. Of
course, I wouldn't be a security-interested party if I did not do some additional
investigation into the DSA versus Ed25519 discussion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The issue with DSA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might find DSA a bit slower than RSA:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;~$ openssl speed rsa1024 rsa2048 dsa1024 dsa2048
...
                  sign    verify    sign/s verify/s
rsa 1024 bits 0.000127s 0.000009s   7874.0 111147.6
rsa 2048 bits 0.000959s 0.000029s   1042.9  33956.0
                  sign    verify    sign/s verify/s
dsa 1024 bits 0.000098s 0.000103s  10213.9   9702.8
dsa 2048 bits 0.000293s 0.000339s   3407.9   2947.0
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, RSA verification outperforms DSA in verification, while signing
with DSA is better than RSA. But for what OpenSSH is concerned, this speed
difference should not be noticeable on the vast majority of OpenSSH servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So no, it is not the speed, but the secure state of the DSS standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OpenSSH developers find that &lt;a href="http://www.openssh.com/legacy.html"&gt;ssh-dss (DSA) is too weak&lt;/a&gt;,
which is followed by &lt;a href="http://meyering.net/nuke-your-DSA-keys/"&gt;various&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href="https://docs.moodle.org/dev/SSH_key"&gt;sources&lt;/a&gt;. Considering the impact of these keys,
it is important that they follow the state-of-the-art cryptographic services. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, they suggest to switch to elliptic curve cryptography based algorithms,
with Ed25519 and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curve25519"&gt;Curve25519&lt;/a&gt; coming out
on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switch to RSA or ED25519?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that RSA is still considered very secure, one of the questions is of
course if &lt;a href="http://ed25519.cr.yp.to/"&gt;ED25519&lt;/a&gt; is the right choice here or not.
I don't consider myself anything in cryptography, but I do like to validate stuff
through academic and (hopefully) reputable sources for information (not that I don't
trust the OpenSSH and OpenSSL folks, but more from a broader interest in the subject).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ed25519 should be written fully as &lt;em&gt;Ed25519-SHA-512&lt;/em&gt; and is a signature
algorithm. It uses elliptic curve cryptography as explained on the
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EdDSA"&gt;EdDSA wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;. An often cited
paper is &lt;a href="http://aspartame.shiftleft.org/papers/fff/fff.pdf"&gt;Fast and compact elliptic-curve cryptography&lt;/a&gt;
by Mike Hamburg, which talks about the performance improvements, but the main
paper is called &lt;a href="http://ed25519.cr.yp.to/ed25519-20110705.pdf"&gt;High-speed high-security signatures&lt;/a&gt;
which introduces the Ed25519 implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the references I was able to (quickly) go through (not all papers are
publicly reachable) none showed any concerns about the secure state of the 
algorithm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The (simple) process of switching&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switching to Ed25519 is simple. First, generate the (new) SSH key (below
just an example run):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;~$ ssh-keygen -t ed25519
Generating public/private ed25519 key pair.
Enter file in which to save the key (/home/testuser/.ssh/id_ed25519): 
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase): 
Enter same passphrase again: 
Your identification has been saved in /home/testuser/.ssh/id_ed25519.
Your public key has been saved in /home/testuser/.ssh/id_ed25519.pub.
The key fingerprint is:
SHA256:RDaEw3tNAKBGMJ2S4wmN+6P3yDYIE+v90Hfzz/0r73M testuser@testserver
The key&amp;#39;s randomart image is:
+--[ED25519 256]--+
|o*...o.+*.       |
|*o+.  +o ..      |
|o++    o.o       |
|o+    ... .      |
| +     .S        |
|+ o .            |
|o+.o . . o       |
|oo+o. . . o ....E|
| oooo.     ..o+=*|
+----[SHA256]-----+
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then, make sure that the &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/authorized_keys&lt;/code&gt; file contains the public key
(as generated as &lt;code&gt;id_ed25519.pub&lt;/code&gt;). Don't remove the other keys yet until the
communication is validated. For me, all I had to do was to update the file in
the Salt repository and have the master push the changes to all nodes (starting
with non-production first of course).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, try to log on to the system using the Ed25519 key:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;~$ ssh -i ~/.ssh/id_ed25519 testuser@testserver
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Make sure that your SSH agent is not running as it might still try to revert
back to another key if the Ed25519 one does not work. You can validate if the
connection was using Ed25519 through the &lt;code&gt;auth.log&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;~$ sudo tail -f auth.log&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;Aug 17 21:20:48 localhost sshd[13962]: Accepted publickey for root from \&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;  192.168.100.1 port 43152 ssh2: ED25519 SHA256:-------redacted----------------&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If this communication succeeds, then you can remove the old key from the &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/authorized_keys&lt;/code&gt; files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the client level, you might want to hide &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/id_dsa&lt;/code&gt; from the SSH agent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Obsolete - keychain ~/.ssh/id_dsa&lt;/span&gt;
keychain ~/.ssh/id_ed25519
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If a server update was forgotten, then the authentication will fail and, depending
on the configuration, either fall back to the regular authentication or fail
immediately. This gives a nice heads-up to you to update the server, while keeping
the key handy just in case. Just refer to the old &lt;code&gt;id_dsa&lt;/code&gt; key during the authentication
and fix up the server.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="openssh"></category><category term="ssh"></category><category term="gentoo"></category></entry></feed>