<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - xsl</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/xsl/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-04-20T03:50:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Transforming GuideXML to DocBook</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/04/transforming-guidexml-to-docbook/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-20T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-04-20T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-04-20:/2013/04/transforming-guidexml-to-docbook/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently
&lt;a href="http://sources.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewvc.cgi/gentoo/xml/htdocs/xsl/docbook.xsl?sortby=date&amp;amp;view=log"&gt;committed&lt;/a&gt;
an XSL stylesheet that allows us to transform the GuideXML documents
(both guides and handbooks) to DocBook. This isn't part of a more
elaborate move to try and push DocBook instead of GuideXML for the
Gentoo Documentation though (I'd rather direct documentation development
more to the Gentoo …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently
&lt;a href="http://sources.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewvc.cgi/gentoo/xml/htdocs/xsl/docbook.xsl?sortby=date&amp;amp;view=log"&gt;committed&lt;/a&gt;
an XSL stylesheet that allows us to transform the GuideXML documents
(both guides and handbooks) to DocBook. This isn't part of a more
elaborate move to try and push DocBook instead of GuideXML for the
Gentoo Documentation though (I'd rather direct documentation development
more to the Gentoo wiki instead once translations are allowed): instead,
I use it to be able to generate our documentation in other formats (such
as PDF but also ePub) when asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're not experienced with XSL: XSL stands for &lt;em&gt;Extensible
Stylesheet Language&lt;/em&gt; and can be seen as a way of "programming" in XML. A
stylesheet allows developers to transform one XML document towards
another format (either another XML, or as &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2013/02/transforming-guidexml-to-wiki/"&gt;text-like output like
wiki&lt;/a&gt;)
while manipulating its contents. In case of documentation, we try to
keep as much structure in the document as possible, but other uses could
be to transform a large XML with only a few interesting fields towards a
very small XML (only containing those fields you need) for further
processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now (and probably for the foreseeable future), the stylesheet is to
be used in an offline mode (we are not going to provide auto-generated
PDFs of all documents) as the process to convert a document from
GuideXML to DocBook to XML:FO to PDF is quite resource-intensive. But
users that are interested can use the stylesheet as linked above to
create their own PDFs of the documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming you have a checkout of the Gentoo documentation, this process
can be done as follows (example for the AMD64 handbook):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ xsltproc docbook.xsl /path/to/handbook-amd64.xml &amp;gt; /somewhere/handbook-amd64.docbook
$ cd /somewhere
$ xsltproc --output handbook-amd64.fo --stringparam paper.type A4   
 /usr/share/sgml/docbook/xsl-stylesheets/fo/docbook.xsl handbook-amd64.docbook
$ fop handbook-amd64.fo handbook-amd64.pdf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The docbook stylesheets are offered by the
&lt;em&gt;app-text/docbook-xsl-stylesheets&lt;/em&gt; package whereas the &lt;strong&gt;fop&lt;/strong&gt; command
is provided by &lt;em&gt;dev-java/fop&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an example output available (temporarily) at my &lt;a href="http://dev.gentoo.org/~swift/tmp/handbook-amd64.pdf"&gt;dev space (amd64
handbook)&lt;/a&gt; but I'm
not going to maintain this for long (so the link might not work in the
near future).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="docbook"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="guidexml"></category><category term="pdf"></category><category term="xsl"></category></entry><entry><title>Transforming GuideXML to wiki</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/02/transforming-guidexml-to-wiki/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-02-12T20:12:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-02-12T20:12:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-02-12:/2013/02/transforming-guidexml-to-wiki/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo project&lt;/a&gt; has its own &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;official
wiki&lt;/a&gt; for some time now, and we are going to
use it more and more in the next few months. For instance, in the last
Gentoo Hardened meeting, we already discussed that most user-oriented
documentation should be put on the wiki, and I've …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo project&lt;/a&gt; has its own &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;official
wiki&lt;/a&gt; for some time now, and we are going to
use it more and more in the next few months. For instance, in the last
Gentoo Hardened meeting, we already discussed that most user-oriented
documentation should be put on the wiki, and I've heard that there are
ideas on moving Gentoo project pages at large towards the wiki. And also
for the regular &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/list.xml"&gt;Gentoo
documentation&lt;/a&gt; I will be moving
those guides that we cannot maintain ourselves anymore easily towards
the wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support migrations of documents, I created a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sjvermeu/small.coding/blob/master/gxml2docbook/gxml2wiki.xsl"&gt;gxml2wiki.xsl&lt;/a&gt;
stylesheet. Such a stylesheet can be used, together with tools like
&lt;strong&gt;xsltproc&lt;/strong&gt;, to transform GuideXML documents into text output
&lt;em&gt;somewhat&lt;/em&gt; suitable for the wiki. It isn't perfect (far from it
actually) but at least it allows for a more simple migration of
documents with minor editing afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, using it is as simple as invoking it against the GuideXML
document you want to transform:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;~$ xsltproc gxml2wiki.xsl /path/to/document.xml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The output shown on the screen can then be used as a page. The following
things still need to be corrected manually:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whitespace is broken, sometimes there are too many newlines. I had
    to make the decision to put in newlines when needed (which makes too
    many newlines) rather than a few newlines too few (which makes it
    more difficult to find where to add in).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Links need to be double/triple checked, but i'll try to fix that in
    later editions of the stylesheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commands will have "INTERNAL" in them - you'll need to move the
    commands themselves into the proper location and only put the
    necessary output in the pre-tags. This is because the wiki format
    has more structure than GuideXML in this matter, thus
    transformations are more difficult to write in this regard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stylesheet currently automatically adds in a link towards a Server
and security category, but of course you'll need to change that to the
proper category for the document you are converting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy documentation hacking!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="guidexml"></category><category term="stylesheet"></category><category term="wiki"></category><category term="xml"></category><category term="xsl"></category></entry></feed>