<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - cloud</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 17:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Scale is a cloud threat</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/scale-is-a-cloud-threat/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Not that long ago, a vulnerability was found in &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/"&gt;Microsoft Azure Cosmos
DB&lt;/a&gt;, a NoSQL SaaS database
within the Microsoft Azure cloud. The vulnerability, which is dubbed
&lt;a href="https://chaosdb.wiz.io/"&gt;ChaosDB&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/wiz_io"&gt;Wiz Research
Team&lt;/a&gt;, uses a vulnerability or misconfiguration in
the &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/cosmosdb-jupyter-notebooks"&gt;Jupyter Notebook
feature&lt;/a&gt;
within Cosmos DB. This vulnerability allowed an attacker to gain access to
other's Cosmos DB credentials. Not long thereafter, a second vulnerability
dubbed
&lt;a href="https://www.wiz.io/blog/omigod-critical-vulnerabilities-in-omi-azure"&gt;OMIGOD&lt;/a&gt;
showed that cloud security is not as simple as some vendors like you to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These vulnerabilities are a good example of how scale is a cloud threat. Companies
that do not have enough experience with public cloud might not assume this in
their threat models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-09-28:/2021/09/scale-is-a-cloud-threat/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>vulnerability</category></item><item><title>Disaster recovery in the public cloud</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/07/disaster-recovery-in-the-public-cloud/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The public cloud is a different beast than an on-premise environment, and that
also reflects itself on how we (should) look at the processes that are
actively steering infrastructure designs and architecture. One of these
is the business continuity, severe incident handling, and the
hopefully-never-to-occur disaster recovery. When building up procedures
for handling disasters (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disaster_recovery"&gt;DRP = Disaster Recovery Procedure or Disaster 
Recover Planning&lt;/a&gt;),
it is important to keep in mind what these are about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-07-30:/2021/07/disaster-recovery-in-the-public-cloud/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>DRP</category></item><item><title>Not sure if TOSCA will grow further</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/not-sure-if-TOSCA-will-grow-further/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;TOSCA is an OASIS open standard, and is an abbreviation for &lt;em&gt;Topology and
Orchestration Specification for Cloud Applications&lt;/em&gt;. It provides a
domain-specific language to describe how an application should be deployed
in the cloud (the topology), which and how many resources it needs, as well
as tasks to run when certain events occur (the orchestration). When I
initially came across this standard, I was (and still am) interested
in how far this goes. The promise of declaring an application (and even
bundling the necessary application artefacts) within a single asset and
then using this asset to deploy on whatever cloud is very appealing to
an architect. Especially in organizations that have a multi-cloud
strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 14:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-30:/2021/06/not-sure-if-TOSCA-will-grow-further/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>TOSCA</category><category>OASIS</category><category>topology</category><category>orchestration</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>IaC</category><category>NFV</category></item><item><title>Integrating or customizing SaaS within your own cloud environment</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/integrating-or-customizing-SaaS-within-your-own-cloud-environment/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Software as a Service (SaaS) solutions are often a quick way to get new
capabilities into an organization’s portfolio. Smaller SaaS solutions are
simple, web-based solutions which barely integrate with the organization’s
other solutions, besides the identity and access management (which is often
handled by federated authentication).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More complex or intermediate solutions require more integration focus, and
a whole new market of Integration Platform as a Service (iPaaS) solutions
came up to facilitate cross-cloud integrations. But even without the iPaaS
offerings, integrations are often a mandatory part to leverage the benefits
of the newly activated SaaS solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to bring some thoughts on the integrations that might be
needed to support customizing a SaaS solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 15:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-23:/2021/06/integrating-or-customizing-SaaS-within-your-own-cloud-environment/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>SaaS</category><category>integration</category><category>customization</category></item></channel></rss>