<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - documents</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/documents/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-12-10T16:03:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Majority of GDP documents moved to Gentoo wiki</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/majority-of-gdp-documents-moved-to-gentoo-wiki/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-10T16:03:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-10T16:03:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-10:/2013/12/majority-of-gdp-documents-moved-to-gentoo-wiki/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The majority of the English gentoo documents that resided in
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en"&gt;www.gentoo.org/doc/en&lt;/a&gt; have now been
moved to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. All those documents
have been made available in the main namespace, meaning that
non-developers can continue to contribute on those articles and guides,
fully in the spirit …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The majority of the English gentoo documents that resided in
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en"&gt;www.gentoo.org/doc/en&lt;/a&gt; have now been
moved to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. All those documents
have been made available in the main namespace, meaning that
non-developers can continue to contribute on those articles and guides,
fully in the spirit of a wiki and community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are now working on &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Documentation/Overview"&gt;a method for displaying an overview of
documents&lt;/a&gt;
that have been moved, or have seen enough development on the wiki that
they are deemed of proper quality and stable (not too many changes
left). Currently, such documents are (requested to be) marked for
translation, allowing me or other developers to review if the guides are
indeed ok to move forward. If so, they are marked as translatable
(allowing the various translation members on the wiki to move forward
with translating the guides) and will be made part of the overview as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the few documents that has not been moved yet is the Gentoo
Handbook as it is of a different format than the guides, and includes
dynamic documentation generation features which I have yet to fully
investigate (wiki-wise). I currently focused mainly on the non-handbook
guides, so the handbook itself will get more attention later (after the
documentation overview is completed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User:A3li"&gt;Alex Legler&lt;/a&gt; for
assisting me and providing the necessary features and functionality in
the Gentoo wiki to make this all possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit:&lt;/em&gt; added link to overview page.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="documents"></category><category term="gdp"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry></feed>