<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - kernel</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/kernel/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2015-05-10T14:18:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Audit buffering and rate limiting</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2015/05/audit-buffering-and-rate-limiting/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-05-10T14:18:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-05-10T14:18:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-05-10:/2015/05/audit-buffering-and-rate-limiting/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Be it because of SELinux experiments, or through general audit
experiments, sometimes you'll get in touch with a message similar to the
following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;audit: audit_backlog=321 &amp;gt; audit_backlog_limit=320
audit: audit_lost=44395 audit_rate_limit=0 audit_backlog_limit=320
audit: backlog limit exceeded
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- PELICAN_END_SUMMMARY --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message shows up when certain audit events could not be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Be it because of SELinux experiments, or through general audit
experiments, sometimes you'll get in touch with a message similar to the
following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;audit: audit_backlog=321 &amp;gt; audit_backlog_limit=320
audit: audit_lost=44395 audit_rate_limit=0 audit_backlog_limit=320
audit: backlog limit exceeded
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- PELICAN_END_SUMMMARY --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message shows up when certain audit events could not be logged
through the audit subsystem. Depending on the system configuration, they
might be either ignored, sent through the kernel logging infrastructure
or even have the system panic. And if the messages are sent to the
kernel log then they might show up, but even that log has its
limitations, which can lead to output similar to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;__ratelimit: 53 callbacks suppressed
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I want to give some pointers in configuring the audit
subsystem as well as understand these messages...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is auditd and kauditd&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take a look at the audit processes running on the system, you'll
notice that (assuming Linux auditing is used of course) two processes
are running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;# ps -ef | grep audit
root      1483     1  0 10:11 ?        00:00:00 /sbin/auditd
root      1486     2  0 10:11 ?        00:00:00 [kauditd]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;/sbin/auditd&lt;/code&gt; daemon is the user-space audit daemon. It &lt;a href="http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man3/audit_open.3.html"&gt;registers
itself&lt;/a&gt; with the
Linux kernel audit subsystem (through the audit netlink system), which
responds with spawning the &lt;code&gt;kauditd&lt;/code&gt; kernel thread/process. The fact
that the process is a kernel-level one is why the &lt;code&gt;kauditd&lt;/code&gt; is
surrounded by brackets in the &lt;code&gt;ps&lt;/code&gt; output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this is done, audit messages are communicated through the netlink
socket to the user-space audit daemon. For the detail-oriented people
amongst you, look for the &lt;em&gt;kauditd_send_skb()&lt;/em&gt; method in the
&lt;a href="http://lxr.free-electrons.com/source/kernel/audit.c"&gt;kernel/audit.c&lt;/a&gt;
file. Now, generated audit event messages are not directly relayed to
the audit daemon - they are first queued in a sort-of backlog, which is
where the backlog-related messages above come from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audit backlog queue&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the kernel-level audit subsystem, a socket buffer queue is used to
hold audit events. Whenever a new audit event is received, it is logged
and prepared to be added to this queue. Adding to this queue can be
controlled through a few parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first parameter is the backlog limit. Be it through a kernel boot
parameter (&lt;code&gt;audit_backlog_limit=N&lt;/code&gt;) or through a message relayed by the
user-space audit daemon (&lt;code&gt;auditctl -b N&lt;/code&gt;), this limit will ensure that a
queue cannot grow beyond a certain size (expressed in the amount of
messages). If an audit event is logged which would grow the queue beyond
this limit, then a failure occurs and is handled according to the system
configuration (more on that later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second parameter is the rate limit. When more audit events are
logged within a second than set through this parameter (which can be
controlled through a message relayed by the user-space audit system,
using &lt;code&gt;auditctl -r N&lt;/code&gt;) then those audit events are not added to the
queue. Instead, a failure occurs and is handled according to the system
configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only when the limits are not reached is the message added to the queue,
allowing the user-space audit daemon to consume those events and log
those according to the audit configuration. There are some good
resources on audit configuration available on the Internet. I find &lt;a href="http://webapp5.rrz.uni-hamburg.de/SuSe-Dokumentation/manual/sles-manuals_en/cha.audit.comp.html"&gt;this
SuSe
chapter&lt;/a&gt;
worth reading, but many others exist as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a useful command related to the subject of the audit backlog
queue. It queries the audit subsystem for its current status:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;# auditctl -s
AUDIT_STATUS: enabled=1 flag=1 pid=1483 rate_limit=0 backlog_limit=8192 lost=3 backlog=0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command displays not only the audit state (enabled or not) but also
the settings for rate limits (on the audit backlog) and backlog limit.
It also shows how many events are currently still waiting in the backlog
queue (which is zero in our case, so the audit user-space daemon has
properly consumed and logged the audit events).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Failure handling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an audit event cannot be logged, then this failure needs to be
resolved. The Linux audit subsystem can be configured do either silently
discard the message, switch to the kernel log subsystem, or panic. This
can be configured through the audit user-space (&lt;code&gt;auditctl -f [0..2]&lt;/code&gt;),
but is usually left at the default (which is 1, being to switch to the
kernel log subsystem).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before that is done, the message is displayed which reveals the cause of
the failure handling:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;audit: audit_backlog=321 &amp;gt; audit_backlog_limit=320
audit: audit_lost=44395 audit_rate_limit=0 audit_backlog_limit=320
audit: backlog limit exceeded
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the backlog queue was set to contain at most 320 entries
(which is low for a production system) and more messages were being
added (the Linux kernel in certain cases allows to have a few more
entries than configured for performance and consistency reasons). The
number of events already lost is displayed, as well as the current
limitation settings. The message "backlog limit exceeded" can be "rate
limit exceeded" if that was the limitation that was triggered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if the system is not configured to silently discard it, or to panic
the system, then the "dropped" messages are sent to the kernel log
subsystem. The calls however are also governed through a configurable
limitation: it uses a rate limit which can be set through &lt;code&gt;sysctl&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;# sysctl -a | grep kernel.printk_rate
kernel.printk_ratelimit = 5
kernel.printk_ratelimit_burst = 10
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the above example, this system allows one message every 5 seconds,
but does allow a burst of up to 10 messages at once. When the rate
limitation kicks in, then the kernel will log (at most one per second)
the number of suppressed events:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;[40676.545099] __ratelimit: 246 callbacks suppressed
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this limit is kernel-wide, not all kernel log events are
governed through it. It is the caller subsystem (in our case, the audit
subsystem) which is responsible for having its events governed through
this rate limitation or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finishing up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before waving goodbye, I would like to point out that the backlog queue
is a memory queue (and not &lt;a href="https://access.redhat.com/solutions/19327"&gt;on disk, Red
Hat&lt;/a&gt;), just in case it wasn't
obvious. Increasing the queue size can result in more kernel memory
consumption. Apparently, a &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/archives/linux-audit/2011-October/msg00007.html"&gt;practical size
estimate&lt;/a&gt;
is around 9000 bytes per message. On production systems, it is advised
not to make this setting too low. I personally set it to 8192.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lost audit events might result in difficulties for troubleshooting,
which is the case when dealing with new or experimental SELinux
policies. It would also result in missing security-important events. It
is the audit subsystem, after all. So tune it properly, and enjoy the
power of Linux' audit subsystem.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Free Software"></category><category term="audit"></category><category term="kernel"></category><category term="security"></category><category term="selinux"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened progress meeting of march 2013</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/03/gentoo-hardened-progress-meeting-of-march-2013/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-03-07T22:46:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-03-07T22:46:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-03-07:/2013/03/gentoo-hardened-progress-meeting-of-march-2013/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another month has passed, so time for a new progress meeting...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toolchain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC v4.7 has been unmasked, allowing a large set of users to test out
the new GCC. It is also expected that GCC 4.8-rc1 will hit the tree next
week. In the hardened-dev overlay, hardened support …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another month has passed, so time for a new progress meeting...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toolchain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC v4.7 has been unmasked, allowing a large set of users to test out
the new GCC. It is also expected that GCC 4.8-rc1 will hit the tree next
week. In the hardened-dev overlay, hardened support for x86, amd64 and
arm has been added (SPEC updates) and the remainder of architectures
will be added by the end of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kernel and grSecurity/PaX&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kernel 3.7.5 had a security issue (local root privilege escalation) so
3.7.5-r1 which held a fix for this was stabilized quickly. However,
other (non-security) problems have been reported, such as one with
dovecot, regarding the VSIZE memory size. This should be fixed in the
3.8 series, so these are candidate for a faster stabilization. This
faster stabilization is never fun, as it increases the likelihood that
we miss other things, but they are needed as the vulnerability in the
previous stable kernel was too severe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding XATTR_PAX, we are getting pretty close to the migration. The
eclass is ready and will be announced for review on the appropriate
mailinglists later this week. A small problem still remains on
Paludis-using systems (Paludis does not record NEEDED.ELF.2 information
- linkage information - so it is hard to get all the linkage information
on a system). A different revdep-pax and migrate-pax toolset will be
built that detects the necessary linkage information, but much slower
than on a Portage-running system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SELinux&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 11th revision of the policies are now stable, and work is on the way
for the 12th revision which will hit the tree soon. Some work is on the
way for setools and policycoreutils (one due to a new release - setools
- and the other one due to a build failure if PAM is not set). Both
packages will hit the hardened-dev overlay soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new "edition" of the selinuxnode virtual image has been pushed to the
mirror system, providing a SELinux-enabled (enforcing) Gentoo Hardened
system with grSecurity and PaX, as well as IMA and EVM enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Profiles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 13.0 profiles have been running fine for a while at a few of our
developer systems. No changes have been needed (yet) so things are
looking good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System Integrity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The necessary userland utilities have been moved to the main tree. The
documentation for IMA/EVM has been updated as well to reflec the current
state of IMA/EVM within Gentoo Hardened. IMA, even with the custom
policies, seems to be working well. EVM on the other hand has some
issues, so you might need to run with EVM=fix for now. Debugging on this
issue is on the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the user oriented documentation (integrity and SELinux) have
been moved to the Gentoo Wiki for easier user contributions and
simplified management. Other documents will follow soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="grsecurity"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="kernel"></category><category term="pax"></category><category term="profiles"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="toolchain"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened goes onward (aka project meeting)</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/02/gentoo-hardened-goes-onward-aka-project-meeting/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-02-07T23:40:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-02-07T23:40:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-02-07:/2013/02/gentoo-hardened-goes-onward-aka-project-meeting/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been a while again, so time for another Gentoo Hardened online
progress meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.8 is on development stage 4, so the hardened patches will be
worked on next week. Some help on it is needed to test the patches on
ARM, PPC and MIPS though. For …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been a while again, so time for another Gentoo Hardened online
progress meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.8 is on development stage 4, so the hardened patches will be
worked on next week. Some help on it is needed to test the patches on
ARM, PPC and MIPS though. For those interested, keep a close eye on the
hardened-dev overlay as those will contain the latest fixes. When GCC
4.9 starts development phase 1, Zorry will again try to upstream the
patches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the coming fixes, we might probably (need to) remove the various
hardenedno* GCC profiles from the hardened Gentoo profiles. This
shouldn't impact too many users as ebuilds add in the correct flags
anyhow (for instance when needing to turn off PIE/PIC).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel, grSecurity and PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kernel release 3.7.0 that we have stable in our tree has seen a few
setbacks, but no higher version is stable yet (mainly due to the
stabilization period needed). 3.7.4-r1 and 3.7.5 are prime candidates
with good track record,&lt;br&gt;
so we might be stabilizing 3.7.5 in the very near future (next week
probably).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the PaX flag migration (you know, from ELF-header based marking to
extended attributes marking), the documentation has seen its necessary
upgrades and the userland utilities have been updated to reflect the use
of xattr markings. The eclass we use for the markings will use the
correct utility based on the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One issue faced when trying to support both markings is that some
actions (like the "paxctl -Cc" which creates the PT_PAX header if it is
missing) make no sense with the other (as there is no header when using
XATTR_PAX). The eclass will be updated to ignore these flags when
XATTR_PAX is selected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revision 10 is stable in the tree, and revision 11 is waiting
stabilization period. A few more changes have been put in the policy
repository already (which are installed when using the live ebuilds) and
will of course be part of&lt;br&gt;
revision 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A change in the userland utilities was also pushed out to allow
permissive domains (so run a single domain in permissive mode instead of
the entire system).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the SELinux eclass has been updated to remove SELinux modules
from all defined SELinux module stores if the SELinux policy package is
removed from the system. Before that, the user had to remove the modules
from the store himself manually, but this is error-prone and easily
forgotten, especially for the non-default SELinux policy stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All hardened subprofiles are marked as deprecated now (you've seen the
discussions on this on the mailinglist probably on this) so we now have
a sane set of hardened profiles to manage. The subprofiles were used for
things like&lt;br&gt;
"desktop" or "server", whereas users can easily stack their profiles as
they see fit anyhow - so there was little reason for the project to
continue managing those subprofiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, now that Gentoo has released its 13.0 profile, we will need to
migrate our profiles to the 13.0 ones as well. So, the idea is to
temporarily support 13.0 in a subprofile, test it thoroughly, and then
remove the subprofile and switch the main one to 13.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;System Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation for IMA and EVM is available on the Gentoo Hardened
project site. They currently still refer to the IMA and EVM subsystems
as development-only, but they are available in the stable kernels now.
Especially the default policy that is available in the kernel is pretty
useful. When you want to consider custom policies (for instance with
SELinux integration) you'll need a kernel patch that is already
upstreamed but not applied to the stable kernels yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To support IMA/EVM, a package called ima-evm-utils is available in the
hardened-dev overlay, which will be moved to the main tree soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Documentation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, the PaX documentation has seen quite a lot of
updates. Other documents that have seen updates are the Hardened FAQ,
Integrity subproject and SELinux documentation although most of them
were small changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another suggestion given is to clean up the Hardened project page;
however, there has been some talk within Gentoo to move project pages to
the Gentoo wiki. Such a move might make the suggestion easier to handle.
And while on the subject of the wiki, we might want to move user guides
to the wiki already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bugs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bug &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/443630"&gt;443630&lt;/a&gt; refers to segmentation
faults with libvirt when starting Qemu domains on a SELinux-enabled
host. Sadly, I'm not able to test libvirt myself so either someone with
SELinux and libvirt&lt;br&gt;
expertise can chime in, or we will need to troubleshoot it by bug
(using gdb, strace'ing more, ...) which might take quite some time and
is not user friendly...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various talks where held at FOSDEM regarding Gentoo Hardened, and a lot
of people attended those talks. Also the round table was quite
effective, with many users interacting with developers all around. For
next year, chances are very high that we'll give a "What has changed
since last year" session and a round table again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With many thanks to the usual suspects: Zorry, blueness, prometheanfire,
lejonet, klondike and the several dozen contributors that are going to
kill me for not mentioning their (nick)names.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="grsecurity"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="kernel"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="minutes"></category><category term="online"></category><category term="pax"></category><category term="profiles"></category><category term="selinux"></category></entry></feed>