<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - Architecture</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/category/architecture/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2021-06-03T10:10:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Virtualization vs abstraction</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/virtualization-vs-abstraction/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-06-03T10:10:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-03T10:10:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-03:/2021/06/virtualization-vs-abstraction/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When an organization has an extensively large, and heterogeneous
infrastructure, infrastructure architects will attempt to make itless
complex and chaotic by introducing and maintaining a certain degree of
standardization. While many might consider standardization as a
rationalization (standardizing on a single database technology, single
vendor for hardware, etc.), rationalization is only one of the many ways
in which standards can simplify such a degree of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I'd like to point out two other, very common ways to
standardize the IT environment, without really considering a
rationalization: abstraction and virtualization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstraction: common and simplified interfaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term "abstraction" has slightly different connotations based on the
context in which the term is used. Generally speaking, an abstraction
provides a less detailed view on an object and shows the intrinsic qualities
upon which one looks at that object. Let's say we have a PostgreSQL database
and a MariaDB database. An abstract view on it could find that it has a lot
of commonalities, such as tabular representation of data, a network-facing
interface through which their database clients can interact with the
database, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then further generalize this abstraction to come to the generalized
"relational database management system" concept. Furthermore, rather than
focusing on the database-specific languages of the PostgreSQL database and
the MariaDB database (i.e. the commands that database clients send to the
database), we abstract the details that are not shared across the two, and
create a more common set of commands that both databases support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you standardize on this common set of commands, you get more freedom in
exchanging one database technology for the other. This is exactly what
happened several dozen years ago, and resulted in the SQL standard
(ISO/IEC 9075). This standard is a language that, if all your relational
database technologies support it, allows you - as an organization - to work
with a multitude of database technologies while still having a more efficient
and standardized way of dealing with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the SQL language standard is one example. IT is filled with many other
examples, some more formally defined as standards than others. Let's look at
a more recent example, within the area of application containerization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CRI and OCI are abstraction implementations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Docker project, now supported through the Docker company, started
with enabling application containerization in a more efficient way, it leaned
upon the capabilities that the Linux kernel offered on hiding information and
isolating resources (namespaces and control groups) and expanded on it to
make it user friendly. It was an immediate hit, and has since then resulted
in a very competitive market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Docker, applications could be put in more isolated environments and run
in parallel on the same system, without these applications seeing the other
ones. Each application has its own, private view on the system. With these
containers, the most important service that is still shared is the kernel,
with the kernel offering only those services to the containers that it can
keep isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Container runtime abstraction" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202106/container-runtimes.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://merlijn.sebrechts.be/blog/2020-01-docker-podman-kata-cri-o/"&gt;https://merlijn.sebrechts.be/blog/2020-01-docker-podman-kata-cri-o/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while Docker can be easily attributed to bringing this to the wider
public, other initiatives quickly followed suit. Multiple container
technologies were coming to life, and started to bid for a place in the
containerization market. To be able to compete here, many of these attempted
to use the same interfaces (be it system calls, commands or other) as Docker
used, so the users can more easily switch. But while trying to copy and
implement the same interfaces is a possible venue, it is still strongly
controlled by the evolution that Docker is taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, larger projects like Kubernetes have started introducing an
abstraction between the container runtime (which implements the actual
containerization) and the container definitions and management (which uses
the containerization). Within Kubernetes for instance, this is through the
Common Runtime Interface (CRI), and the Open Container Interface (OCI) is
used to link the container runtime management with the underlying container
technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introducing such an abstraction is a common way to establish a bit more
foothold in the market. Rather than trying to copy the market leader
verbatim, you create an intermediate layer, with immediate implementation
for the market leader as well, but with the promise that anyone that uses
the intermediate layer will be less tied to a single vendor or project: it
abstracts that vendor or project specifics away and shows mainly the
intrinsic qualities needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that abstraction is successful, other implementations for this abstraction
layer can easily come in and replace the previous technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstraction is not virtualization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of abstraction layers, abstract technologies or abstract
languages should not be misunderstood for virtualization. Abstraction does
not hide or differently represent the resources beneath. It does not represent
itself as something else, but merely leaves out details that might make
interactions with the different technologies more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtualization on the other hand takes a different view. Rather than removing
the specific details, it represents a resource as something that it isn't
(or isn't completely). Hypervisors like KVM create a virtual hardware view,
and translates whatever calls towards the virtual hardware into calls to the
actual hardware - sometimes to the same type of hardware, but often towards
the CPU or resources that simulate the virtualized hardware further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstraction is a bit like classification, and defining how to work with a
resource through the agreed upon interfaces for that class. If you plug in
a USB device like a USB stick or USB keyboard or mouse, operating systems
will be able to interact with it regardless of its vendor and product,
because it uses the abstraction offered by the device classes: the USB mass
storage device class for the USB stick, or the USB human interface device
class for the keyboard and mouse. It abstracts away the complexity of
dealing with multiple implementations, but the devices themselves still
need to be classified as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On hypervisors, you can create a virtual USB stick which in reality is just
a file on the hypervisor host or on a network file share. The hypervisor
virtualizes the view towards this file as if it is a USB stick, but in reality
there is no USB involved at all. Again, this doesn't have to be the case,
the hypervisor might as well enable virtualization of the USB device and
still eventually interact with an actual USB device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VLANs are virtualized networks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example of a virtualization is network virtualization through the
use of VLANs. In a virtual local area network (VLAN), all systems that
interact with this VLAN will see each other on the network as if they are
part of the same broadcast domain. Well, they are part of the same broadcast
domain. But if you look at the physical network implementation, this does not
imply that all these systems are attached to the same switch, and that no
routers are put in between to facilitate the communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In larger enterprises, the use of VLANs is ubiquitous. Network virtualization
enables the telco teams and departments to optimize the actual physical
network without continuously impacting the configurations and deployments of
the services that use the network. Teams can create hundreds or thousands of
such VLANs while keeping the actual hardware investments under control, and
even be able to change and manage the network without impacting services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This benefit is strongly tied to virtualization, as we see the same in
hardware virtualization for server and workstation resources. By offering
virtualized systems, the underlying hardware can be changed, replaced or
switched without impact on the actual software that is running within the
virtualized environment. Well, mostly without impact, because not all
virtualization technologies or implementations are creating a full
virtualized view - sometimes shortcuts are created to improve efficiency
and performance. But in general, it works Just Fine (tm).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resource optimization and consolidation is easily accomplished when using
virtualization. You need far fewer switches in a virtualized network, and
you need far fewer servers for a virtualized server farm. But, it does come
at a cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virtualization introduces different complexity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you introduce a virtualization layer, be it for network, storage,
hardware or application runtimes, you introduce a layer that needs to be
actively managed. Abstraction is often much less resource intensive, as it
is a way to simplify the view on the actual resources while still being 100%
aligned with those underlying resources. Virtualization means that you need
to manage the virtualized resources, and keep track of how these resources
map to the actual underlying resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="vSphere services" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202106/vsphere.png"/&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://virtualgyaan.com/vmkernel-components-and-functionality/"&gt;https://virtualgyaan.com/vmkernel-components-and-functionality/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at virtualized hardware for servers. On top of it, you have to
run and maintain the hypervisor, which represents the virtual hardware to
the operating systems. Within those (virtually running) operating systems,
you have a virtual view on resources: CPU, memory, etc. The sum of all
(virtual) CPUs is often not the same as the sum of all (actual) CPUs
(depending on configuration of course), and in larger environments the
virtual operating systems might not even be running on the same hardware
as they did a few hours ago, even though the system has not been restarted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing performance analysis implies looking at the resources within (virtual)
as well as mapped on the actual resources, which might not be of the same
type. A virtual GPU representation might be mapped to an actual GPU (and if
you want performance, I hope it is) but doesn't have to be. I've done
investigations on a virtual Trusted Platform Module (TPM) within a virtual
system running on a server that didn't have a TPM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessing which standardization to approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I'm confronted with an increase in IT complexity, I will often be
looking at a certain degree of standardization to facilitate this in the
organization. But what type of standardization to approach depends strongly
on the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standardization by rationalization is often triggered by cost optimization
or knowledge optimization. An organization that has ten different relational
database technologies in use could benefit of a rationalization in the number
of technologies to support. However, unless there is also sufficient
abstraction put in place, this rationalization can be intensive. Another
rationalization example could be on public cloud, where an organization
chooses to only focus on a single or two cloud providers but not more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While rationalization is easy to understand and explain, it does have adverse
consequences: you miss the benefits of whatever you're rationalized away,
and unless another type of standardization is put in place, it will be hard
to switch later on if the rationalization was ill-advised or picked the
wrong targets to rationalize towards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standardization by abstraction focuses more on simplification. You are
introducing technologies that might have better interoperability through
this abstraction, but this can only be successful if the abstraction is
comprehensive enough to still use the underlying resources in an optimal
manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own observation on abstraction is that it is not commonly accepted by
engineers and developers at face value. It requires much more communication
and explanation than rationalization, which is often easy to put under "cost
pressure". Abstraction focuses on efficiency in a different way, and thus
requires different communication. At the company I currently work for,
we've introduced the Open Service Broker (OSB) API as an abstraction for
service instantiation and service catalogs, and after even more than a
year, including management support, it is still a common endeavor to
explain and motivate why we chose this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtualization creates a highly efficient environment and supports resource
optimizations that aren't possible in other ways. Its benefits are much easier
to explain to the organization (and to management), but has a downside that
is often neglected: it introduces complexity. Hence, virtualization should
only be pursued if you can manage the complexity, and that it isn't much
worse than the complexity you want to remove. Virtualization requires
organizational support which is more platform-oriented (and thus might be
further away from the immediate 'business value' IT often has to explain),
in effect creating a new type of technology within the ever increasing
catalog of IT services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software-defined infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While virtualization has been going around in IT for quite some time (before
I was born), a new kid on the block is becoming very popular: software-defined
infrastructure. The likes of Software Defined Network (SDN), Compute (SDC) and
Storage (SDS) are already common or becoming common. Other implementations,
like the Software Defined Perimeter, are getting jabbed by vendors as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, SDI is not its own type of standardization. It is a way of managing
resources through code, and thus is a way of abstracting the infrastructure.
But unlike using a technology-agnostic abstraction, it pulls you into a
vendor-defined abstraction. That has its pros and cons, and as an architect
it is important to consider how to approach infrastructure-as-code, as SDI
implementations are not the only way to accomplish this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, SDI does not imply virtualization. Certainly, if a technology
is virtualized, then SDI will also easily interact with it, and help you
define and manage the virtualized infrastructure as well as its underlay
infrastructure. But virtualization isn't a prerequisite for SDI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you're confronted with chaos and complexity, don't immediately start
removing technologies under the purview of "rationalization". Consider your
options on abstraction and virtualization, but be aware of the pros and cons
of each.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When an organization has an extensively large, and heterogeneous
infrastructure, infrastructure architects will attempt to make itless
complex and chaotic by introducing and maintaining a certain degree of
standardization. While many might consider standardization as a
rationalization (standardizing on a single database technology, single
vendor for hardware, etc.), rationalization is only one of the many ways
in which standards can simplify such a degree of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I'd like to point out two other, very common ways to
standardize the IT environment, without really considering a
rationalization: abstraction and virtualization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstraction: common and simplified interfaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term "abstraction" has slightly different connotations based on the
context in which the term is used. Generally speaking, an abstraction
provides a less detailed view on an object and shows the intrinsic qualities
upon which one looks at that object. Let's say we have a PostgreSQL database
and a MariaDB database. An abstract view on it could find that it has a lot
of commonalities, such as tabular representation of data, a network-facing
interface through which their database clients can interact with the
database, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then further generalize this abstraction to come to the generalized
"relational database management system" concept. Furthermore, rather than
focusing on the database-specific languages of the PostgreSQL database and
the MariaDB database (i.e. the commands that database clients send to the
database), we abstract the details that are not shared across the two, and
create a more common set of commands that both databases support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you standardize on this common set of commands, you get more freedom in
exchanging one database technology for the other. This is exactly what
happened several dozen years ago, and resulted in the SQL standard
(ISO/IEC 9075). This standard is a language that, if all your relational
database technologies support it, allows you - as an organization - to work
with a multitude of database technologies while still having a more efficient
and standardized way of dealing with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the SQL language standard is one example. IT is filled with many other
examples, some more formally defined as standards than others. Let's look at
a more recent example, within the area of application containerization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CRI and OCI are abstraction implementations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Docker project, now supported through the Docker company, started
with enabling application containerization in a more efficient way, it leaned
upon the capabilities that the Linux kernel offered on hiding information and
isolating resources (namespaces and control groups) and expanded on it to
make it user friendly. It was an immediate hit, and has since then resulted
in a very competitive market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Docker, applications could be put in more isolated environments and run
in parallel on the same system, without these applications seeing the other
ones. Each application has its own, private view on the system. With these
containers, the most important service that is still shared is the kernel,
with the kernel offering only those services to the containers that it can
keep isolated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Container runtime abstraction" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202106/container-runtimes.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://merlijn.sebrechts.be/blog/2020-01-docker-podman-kata-cri-o/"&gt;https://merlijn.sebrechts.be/blog/2020-01-docker-podman-kata-cri-o/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while Docker can be easily attributed to bringing this to the wider
public, other initiatives quickly followed suit. Multiple container
technologies were coming to life, and started to bid for a place in the
containerization market. To be able to compete here, many of these attempted
to use the same interfaces (be it system calls, commands or other) as Docker
used, so the users can more easily switch. But while trying to copy and
implement the same interfaces is a possible venue, it is still strongly
controlled by the evolution that Docker is taking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, larger projects like Kubernetes have started introducing an
abstraction between the container runtime (which implements the actual
containerization) and the container definitions and management (which uses
the containerization). Within Kubernetes for instance, this is through the
Common Runtime Interface (CRI), and the Open Container Interface (OCI) is
used to link the container runtime management with the underlying container
technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introducing such an abstraction is a common way to establish a bit more
foothold in the market. Rather than trying to copy the market leader
verbatim, you create an intermediate layer, with immediate implementation
for the market leader as well, but with the promise that anyone that uses
the intermediate layer will be less tied to a single vendor or project: it
abstracts that vendor or project specifics away and shows mainly the
intrinsic qualities needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that abstraction is successful, other implementations for this abstraction
layer can easily come in and replace the previous technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstraction is not virtualization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of abstraction layers, abstract technologies or abstract
languages should not be misunderstood for virtualization. Abstraction does
not hide or differently represent the resources beneath. It does not represent
itself as something else, but merely leaves out details that might make
interactions with the different technologies more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtualization on the other hand takes a different view. Rather than removing
the specific details, it represents a resource as something that it isn't
(or isn't completely). Hypervisors like KVM create a virtual hardware view,
and translates whatever calls towards the virtual hardware into calls to the
actual hardware - sometimes to the same type of hardware, but often towards
the CPU or resources that simulate the virtualized hardware further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstraction is a bit like classification, and defining how to work with a
resource through the agreed upon interfaces for that class. If you plug in
a USB device like a USB stick or USB keyboard or mouse, operating systems
will be able to interact with it regardless of its vendor and product,
because it uses the abstraction offered by the device classes: the USB mass
storage device class for the USB stick, or the USB human interface device
class for the keyboard and mouse. It abstracts away the complexity of
dealing with multiple implementations, but the devices themselves still
need to be classified as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On hypervisors, you can create a virtual USB stick which in reality is just
a file on the hypervisor host or on a network file share. The hypervisor
virtualizes the view towards this file as if it is a USB stick, but in reality
there is no USB involved at all. Again, this doesn't have to be the case,
the hypervisor might as well enable virtualization of the USB device and
still eventually interact with an actual USB device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VLANs are virtualized networks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another example of a virtualization is network virtualization through the
use of VLANs. In a virtual local area network (VLAN), all systems that
interact with this VLAN will see each other on the network as if they are
part of the same broadcast domain. Well, they are part of the same broadcast
domain. But if you look at the physical network implementation, this does not
imply that all these systems are attached to the same switch, and that no
routers are put in between to facilitate the communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In larger enterprises, the use of VLANs is ubiquitous. Network virtualization
enables the telco teams and departments to optimize the actual physical
network without continuously impacting the configurations and deployments of
the services that use the network. Teams can create hundreds or thousands of
such VLANs while keeping the actual hardware investments under control, and
even be able to change and manage the network without impacting services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This benefit is strongly tied to virtualization, as we see the same in
hardware virtualization for server and workstation resources. By offering
virtualized systems, the underlying hardware can be changed, replaced or
switched without impact on the actual software that is running within the
virtualized environment. Well, mostly without impact, because not all
virtualization technologies or implementations are creating a full
virtualized view - sometimes shortcuts are created to improve efficiency
and performance. But in general, it works Just Fine (tm).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resource optimization and consolidation is easily accomplished when using
virtualization. You need far fewer switches in a virtualized network, and
you need far fewer servers for a virtualized server farm. But, it does come
at a cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virtualization introduces different complexity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you introduce a virtualization layer, be it for network, storage,
hardware or application runtimes, you introduce a layer that needs to be
actively managed. Abstraction is often much less resource intensive, as it
is a way to simplify the view on the actual resources while still being 100%
aligned with those underlying resources. Virtualization means that you need
to manage the virtualized resources, and keep track of how these resources
map to the actual underlying resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="vSphere services" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202106/vsphere.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Source: &lt;a href="https://virtualgyaan.com/vmkernel-components-and-functionality/"&gt;https://virtualgyaan.com/vmkernel-components-and-functionality/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at virtualized hardware for servers. On top of it, you have to
run and maintain the hypervisor, which represents the virtual hardware to
the operating systems. Within those (virtually running) operating systems,
you have a virtual view on resources: CPU, memory, etc. The sum of all
(virtual) CPUs is often not the same as the sum of all (actual) CPUs
(depending on configuration of course), and in larger environments the
virtual operating systems might not even be running on the same hardware
as they did a few hours ago, even though the system has not been restarted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing performance analysis implies looking at the resources within (virtual)
as well as mapped on the actual resources, which might not be of the same
type. A virtual GPU representation might be mapped to an actual GPU (and if
you want performance, I hope it is) but doesn't have to be. I've done
investigations on a virtual Trusted Platform Module (TPM) within a virtual
system running on a server that didn't have a TPM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessing which standardization to approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I'm confronted with an increase in IT complexity, I will often be
looking at a certain degree of standardization to facilitate this in the
organization. But what type of standardization to approach depends strongly
on the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standardization by rationalization is often triggered by cost optimization
or knowledge optimization. An organization that has ten different relational
database technologies in use could benefit of a rationalization in the number
of technologies to support. However, unless there is also sufficient
abstraction put in place, this rationalization can be intensive. Another
rationalization example could be on public cloud, where an organization
chooses to only focus on a single or two cloud providers but not more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While rationalization is easy to understand and explain, it does have adverse
consequences: you miss the benefits of whatever you're rationalized away,
and unless another type of standardization is put in place, it will be hard
to switch later on if the rationalization was ill-advised or picked the
wrong targets to rationalize towards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standardization by abstraction focuses more on simplification. You are
introducing technologies that might have better interoperability through
this abstraction, but this can only be successful if the abstraction is
comprehensive enough to still use the underlying resources in an optimal
manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My own observation on abstraction is that it is not commonly accepted by
engineers and developers at face value. It requires much more communication
and explanation than rationalization, which is often easy to put under "cost
pressure". Abstraction focuses on efficiency in a different way, and thus
requires different communication. At the company I currently work for,
we've introduced the Open Service Broker (OSB) API as an abstraction for
service instantiation and service catalogs, and after even more than a
year, including management support, it is still a common endeavor to
explain and motivate why we chose this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtualization creates a highly efficient environment and supports resource
optimizations that aren't possible in other ways. Its benefits are much easier
to explain to the organization (and to management), but has a downside that
is often neglected: it introduces complexity. Hence, virtualization should
only be pursued if you can manage the complexity, and that it isn't much
worse than the complexity you want to remove. Virtualization requires
organizational support which is more platform-oriented (and thus might be
further away from the immediate 'business value' IT often has to explain),
in effect creating a new type of technology within the ever increasing
catalog of IT services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software-defined infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While virtualization has been going around in IT for quite some time (before
I was born), a new kid on the block is becoming very popular: software-defined
infrastructure. The likes of Software Defined Network (SDN), Compute (SDC) and
Storage (SDS) are already common or becoming common. Other implementations,
like the Software Defined Perimeter, are getting jabbed by vendors as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, SDI is not its own type of standardization. It is a way of managing
resources through code, and thus is a way of abstracting the infrastructure.
But unlike using a technology-agnostic abstraction, it pulls you into a
vendor-defined abstraction. That has its pros and cons, and as an architect
it is important to consider how to approach infrastructure-as-code, as SDI
implementations are not the only way to accomplish this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, SDI does not imply virtualization. Certainly, if a technology
is virtualized, then SDI will also easily interact with it, and help you
define and manage the virtualized infrastructure as well as its underlay
infrastructure. But virtualization isn't a prerequisite for SDI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you're confronted with chaos and complexity, don't immediately start
removing technologies under the purview of "rationalization". Consider your
options on abstraction and virtualization, but be aware of the pros and cons
of each.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Architecture"></category><category term="architecture"></category><category term="virtualization"></category><category term="abstraction"></category></entry><entry><title>Abstracting infrastructure complexity</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-25T23:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-25T23:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2020-12-25:/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;IT is complex. Some even consider it to be more magic than reality. And with
the ongoing evolutions and inventions, the complexity is not really going
away. Sure, some IT areas are becoming easier to understand, but that is often
offset with new areas being explored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies and organizations that have a sizeable IT footprint generally see an
increase in their infrastructure, regardless of how many rationalization
initiatives that are started. Personally, I find it challenging, in a fun
way, to keep up with the onslaught of new technologies and services that are
onboarded in the infrastructure landscape that I'm responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just understanding a technology isn't enough to deal with its position in
the larger environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;IT is complex. Some even consider it to be more magic than reality. And with
the ongoing evolutions and inventions, the complexity is not really going
away. Sure, some IT areas are becoming easier to understand, but that is often
offset with new areas being explored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies and organizations that have a sizeable IT footprint generally see an
increase in their infrastructure, regardless of how many rationalization
initiatives that are started. Personally, I find it challenging, in a fun
way, to keep up with the onslaught of new technologies and services that are
onboarded in the infrastructure landscape that I'm responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just understanding a technology isn't enough to deal with its position in
the larger environment.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complexity is a challenging beast&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone were to attempt drawing out how the IT infrastructure of a larger
IT environment looks like in reality, it would soon become very, very large and
challenging to explain. Perhaps not chaotic, but definitely complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the challenges is the amount of "something" that is out there. That can
be the amount of devices you have, the amount of servers in the network, the
amount of flows going through firewalls or gateways, the amount of processes
running on a server, the amount of workstations and end user devices in use,
the amount of containers running in the container platform, the amount of cloud
platform instances that are active... &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "something" can even be less tangible than the previous examples such as
the amount of projects that are being worked on in parallel or the amount of
changes that are being prepared. However, that complexity is not one I'll deal
with in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another challenge is the virtualized nature of IT infrastructure, which has
a huge benefit for the organization and simplifies infrastructure services
for its own consumers, but does make it more, well, complicated to deal with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtual networks (vlans), virtual systems (hypervisors), virtual firewalls,
virtual applications (with support for streaming desktop applications to the
end user device without having the applications installed on that device),
virtual storage environments, etc. are all wonderful technologies which allow
for much more optimized resource usage, but does introduce a higher complexity
of the infastructure at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make sense of such larger structures, we start making abstractions of what
we see, structuring it in a way that we can more easily explain, assess or analyze
the environment and support changes properly. These abstract views do reflect
reality, but only to a certain extend. Not every question that can be asked can
be answered satisfactory with the same abstract view, but when it can, it is very
effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstracting service complexity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my day-to-day job, I'm responsible for the infrastructure of a reasonably
large environment. With "responsible" I don't want to imply that I'm the one
and only party involved of course - responsibilities are across a range of
people and roles. I am accountable for the long-term strategy on
infrastructure and the high-level infrastructure architecture and its offerings,
but how that plays out is a collaborative aspect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of this role, I do want to keep a close eye on all the services that
we offer from infrastructure side of things. And hence, I am often confronted
with the complexity mentioned earlier. To resolve this, I try to look at all
infastructure services in an abstract way, and document it in the same way so
that services are more easily explained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="An Archimate based view on the abstractions listed" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202012/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity-kvm.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Figure 1 - A possible visualization of the abstraction model, here in Archimate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstraction I apply is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We start with &lt;em&gt;components&lt;/em&gt;, building blocks that are used and which refer
  to a single product or technology out there. A specific Java product can
  be considered such a component, because by itself it hardly has any value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Components are put together to create a &lt;em&gt;solution&lt;/em&gt;. This is something that
  is intended to provide value to the organization at large, and is the level
  at which something is documented, has an organizational entity responsible
  for it, etc. Solutions are not yet instantiated though. An example of a
  solution could be a Kafka-based pub/sub solution, or an OpenLDAP-based
  directory solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solutions are used to create &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt;. A service is something that has
  an SLA attached to it. In most cases, the same solution is used to create
  multiple services. We can think of the Kafka-based pub/sub solution that
  has three services in the organization: a regular non-production one,
  a regular production one, and a highly available production service.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Services are supported through one or more &lt;em&gt;clusters&lt;/em&gt;. These are a
  way for teams to organize resources in support of a service. Some services
  might be supported by multiple clusters, for instance spread across
  different data centers. An OpenLDAP-based service might be supported by
  a single OpenLDAP cluster with native synchronization support spread across
  two data centers, or by two OpenLDAP clusters with a different
  synchronization mechanism between the two clusters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clusters exist out of one or more &lt;em&gt;instances&lt;/em&gt;. These are the actual deployed
  technology processes that enable the cluster. In an OpenLDAP cluster, you
  could have two master processes (&lt;code&gt;slapd&lt;/code&gt; processes) running, which are the
  instances within the cluster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On top of the clusters, we enable &lt;em&gt;containers&lt;/em&gt; (I call those containers, but
  they don't have anything to do with container technology like Docker containers).
  The containers are what the consumers are actually interested in. That could
  be an organization unit in an LDAP structure, a database within an RDBMS, 
  a set of topics within a Kafka cluster, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the basic abstractions I apply for most of the technologies, allowing
me to easily make a good view on the environment. Let's look at a few examples
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example: Virtualization of Wintel systems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a large, virtualized environment, you generally have a specific hypervisor
software being used: be it RHV (Red Hat Virtualization) based upon
KVM, Microsoft HyperV, VMWare vSphere or something else - the technology used
is generally well known. That's one of the components being used, but that is
far from the only component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better manage the virtualized environment the administration teams might
use an orchestration engine like Ansible, Puppet or Saltstack. They might also
have a component in use for automatically managing certificates and what not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these components are needed to build a full virtualization solution. For
me, as an architect, knowing which components are used is useful for things
like lifecycle management (which components are EOL, which components can be
easily replaced with a different one versus components that are more lock-in
oriented, etc.) or inventory management (which component is deployed where,
which version is used), which supports things like vulnerability management
(if we can map components to their Common Platform Enumeration (CPE) then
we can easily see which vulnerabilities are reported through the Common
Vulnerabilities and Exposure (CVE) reports).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interaction between all these components creates a sensible solution,
which is the virtualization solution. At this level, I'm mostly interested
in the solution roadmap, the responsibilities and documentation associated
with it, the costs, maturity of the offering within the organization, etc.
It is also on the solution level that most architectural designs are made,
and the best practices (and malpractices) are documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The virtualization solution itself is then instantiated within the
organization to create one or more services. These could be different
services based on the environment (a lab/sandbox virtualization service
with low to no SLA, a non-production one with standard SLA, a non-production
one with specific disaster recovery requirements, a production one with
standard SLA (and standard disaster recovery requirements), a high-performance
production one, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These services are mostly important for other architects, project leads
or other stakeholders that are going to make active use of the virtualization
services - the different services (which one could document as "service
plans") make it more obvious on what the offering is, and what differentiation
is supported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's consider a production, standard SLA virtualization service. The
system administrators of the virtualization environment might enable this
service across multiple clusters. This could be for several reasons: this
could be due to limits (maximum number of hosts per cluster), or because
of particular resource requirements (different CPU architecture requirements
- yes even with virtualization this is still a thing), or to make
things manageable for the administrators in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While knowing which cluster an application is on is, in general, not
that important, it can be very important when there are problems, or when
limits are being reached. As an architect, I'm definitely interested in
knowing why multiple clusters are made (what is the reasoning behind it) as
it gives a good view on what the administrators are generally dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a cluster (to support the virtualization) you'll find multiple hosts.
Often, a cluster is sized to be able to deal with one or two host fall-outs
so that the virtual machines (which are hosted on the cluster - these are
the "containers" that I spoke of) can be migrated to another host with only
a short downtime as a consequence (if their main host crashed) or no downtime
at all (if it is scheduled maintenance of the host). These hosts are the
instances of the cluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By using this abstraction, I can "map" the virtualization environment in
a way that I have a good enough view, without proclaiming to be anything
more than an informed architect, on this setup to support my own work,
and to be able to advice management on major investment requirements,
challenges, strategic evolutions and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More than just documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the above method is used for documenting the environment in which
I work (and which works well for the size of the environment I have to deal
with), it can be used for simplifying management of the technologies as
well. This level of abstraction can easily be used in environments that
push self-servicing forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's take the &lt;a href="https://www.openservicebrokerapi.org/"&gt;Open Service Broker API&lt;/a&gt;
as an example. This is an API that defines how to expose (infrastructure)
services to consumers that can easily create (provision) and destroy 
(deprovision) their own services. Brokers that support the API will
then automatically handle the service management. This model can easily
be put in to support the previous abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the virtualization environment again. If we want to enable self-servicing
on a virtualized environment, we can think of an offering where internal customers
can create new virtual machines (provision) either based on a company-vetted
template, or through an image (like with virtual appliances). The team that
manages the virtualization environment has a number of services, which they
describe in the service plans exposed by the API. An internal customer, when
privisioning a virtual machine, is thus creating a "container" for the right
service (based on their selected service plan) and on the right cluster
(based upon the parameters that the internal customer passes along with the
creation of its machine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can do the same with databases: a certain database solution (say PostgreSQL)
has its own offerings (exposed through service plans linked to the service), and
internal customers can create their own database ("container") on the right
cluster through this API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally have a few scripts that I use at home myself to quickly set
up a certain technology, using the above abstraction level as the foundation.
Rather than having to try and remember how to set up a multi-master OpenLDAP
service, or a replicated Kafka setup, I have scripts that create this based
upon this abstraction: the script parameters always use the service, cluster,
instance and container terminology and underlyingly map this to the
technology-specific approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is my intention to also promote this abstraction usage within my
work environment, as I believe it allows us to more easily explain what
all the infrastructure is used for, but also to more easily get new employees
known to our environment. But even if that isn't reached, the abstraction is
a huge help for me to assess and understand the multitude of technologies
that are out there, be it our mainframe setup, the SAN offerings, the
network switching setup, the databases, messaging services, cloud
landing zones, firewall setups, container platforms and more.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category><category term="infrastructure"></category><category term="archimate"></category></entry><entry><title>Working on infra strategy</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2020/10/working-on-infra-strategy/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-04T13:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-10-04T13:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2020-10-04:/2020/10/working-on-infra-strategy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a long hiatus, I'm ready to take up blogging again on my public blog.
With my day job becoming more intensive and my side-job taking the remainder
of the time, I've since quit my work on the Gentoo project. I am in process
of releasing a new edition of the SELinux System Administration book, so I'll
probably discuss that more later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to write about a task I had to do this year as brand new domain
architect for infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a long hiatus, I'm ready to take up blogging again on my public blog.
With my day job becoming more intensive and my side-job taking the remainder
of the time, I've since quit my work on the Gentoo project. I am in process
of releasing a new edition of the SELinux System Administration book, so I'll
probably discuss that more later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to write about a task I had to do this year as brand new domain
architect for infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transitioning to domain architect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I have been an infrastructure architect for quite some time already, my
focus then was always on specific areas within infrastructure (databases,
scheduling, big data), or on general infrastructure projects or challenges
(infrastructure zoning concept, region-wide disaster recovery analysis and
design). As one of my ex-colleagues and mentors put it, as infrastructure
architects you are allowed to piss on each other's area: you can (and perhaps
should) challenge the vision and projects of others, of course in a
professional way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heeded the advice of this person, and was able to get a much better grip on
all our infrastructure services, their designs and challenges. I mentioned
earlier on that my day job became more intensive: it was not just the direct
responsibilities that I had that became more challenging, my principle to learn
and keep track of all infrastructure evolutions were a large part of it as
well. This pays off, as feedback and advice within the architecture review
boards is more to the point, more tied to the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, as an architect, I still try to get my hands dirty on everything
bouncing around. When I was focusing on big data, I learned Spark and
pySpark, I revisited my Python knowledge, and used this for specific cases
(like using Python to create reports rather than Excel) to make sure I get a
general feel of what engineers and developers have to work with. When my focus
was on databases, I tried to get acquainted with DBA tasks. When we were
launching our container initiative, I set up and used Kubernetes myself (back
then this was also to see if SELinux is working properly with Kubernetes and
during the installation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this does not make me anything near what our engineers and experts are
doing, I feel it gives me enough knowledge to be able to talk and discuss
topics with these colleagues without being that "ivory tower" architect,
and better understand (to a certain level) what they are going through when
new initiatives or solutions are thrown at them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;End of 2019, the company decided that a reorganization was due, not only on
department and directorate level, but also on the IT and Enterprise
Architecture level. One of the areas that improved was to make sure the
infrastructure in general was also covered and supported by the EA team.
Part of that move, two of my infrastructure architect colleagues and
myself joined the EA team. One colleague is appointed to tackle a strategic
theme, another is now domain architect for workplace/workforce,
and I got the task of covering the infrastructure domain. Well, it is called
infrastructure, but focus on the infrastructure related to hosting of
applications and services: cloud hosting, data center, network, compute,
private cloud, container platform, mainframe, integration services,
middleware, etc. Another large part of what I consider "infrastructure" is
part of the workplace domain, which my colleague is pushing forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was still handing over my previous workload, coaching the new colleague
that got thrown in to make sure both him and the teams involved are not left
with a gap, the various domain enterprise architects got a first task: draft
up the strategy for the domain and don't wait too long ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tackling a domain strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I've drafted infrastructural strategies quite a few times already,
although those have most focus on the technology side. The domain view
goes beyond just the technological means: to be able to have a well-founded
strategy, I also have to tackle the resources and human side of things, the
ability of the organization to deal with (yet another?) transformation, the
processes involved, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the more specific area focus I had in the past, where the number of
direct stakeholders is limited, the infrastructure domain I now support has
many more direct stakeholders involved. If I count the product managers, system
architects, product owners (yes we are trying the Scaled Agile approach in our
organization) and the managerial roles within the domain, I have 148 people to
involve, spread across 7 Agile Release Trains with different directorate
steering. The consumers of the infrastructure services (which are more part of
business delivery services rather than on IT level) are even much larger than
that, and are the most important ones (but also more difficult) to get in touch
with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than just asking what the main evolutions are in the several areas of
the domains, I approached this more according to practices I read in books like
"Good Strategy, Bad Strategy" by Richard Rumelt. I started with interviews of
all the stakeholders to get to learn what their challenges and problems are.
I wanted our strategy to tackle the issues at hand, not focus on technological
choices. Based on these interviews, I grouped the issues and challenges to see
what are the primary causes of these issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I devised what action domains I need to focus on in the strategy. An
action domain was an area that more clearly describes the challenges ahead:
while I had close to 200 challenges observed from the interviews, I can assign
the huge majority of them to one of two action domains: if we tackle these
domains then we are helping the organization in most of their challenges.
After validating that these action domains are indeed covering the needs of
the organization, I started working on the principles how to tackle these
issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the principles I want to steer the evolution within the infrastructure
domain, without already focusing on the tangible projects to accomplish that.
The principles should map to both larger projects (which I wanted to describe
in the strategy as well) as well as smaller or more continuity-related
projects. I eventually settled with four principles:
  - one principle covering how to transform the environment,
  - one principle covering what we offer (and thus also what we won't be
    offering anymore),
  - one principle which extends our scope with a major area that our internal
    customers are demanding, and
  - one principle describing how we will design our services&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four principles are easy enough to remember for all involved, and if they are
described well, they are steering enough for the organization to take up in
their solutions. But with principles alone the strategy is not tangible enough
for everyone, and many choices to be made are not codified within those
principles. The next step was to draw out the vision for  infrastructure, based
upon current knowledge and the principles above, and show the major areas of
work that lays ahead, as well as give guidance on what these areas should
evolve to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I settled for eight vision statements, each worked out further with high level
guidance, as well as impact information: how will this impact the organization?
Do we need specific knowledge or other profiles that we miss? Is this a vision
that instills a cultural change (which often implies a slower adoption and the
need for more support)? What are the financial consequences? What will happen
if we do not pursue this vision?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within each vision, I collaborated with the various system architects and other
stakeholders to draft out epics, changes that support the vision and are ready
to be taken up in the Scaled Agile approach of the organization. The epics that
would be due soon were fully expanded, with a lean business case (attempt) and
phasing. Epics that are scheduled later (the strategy is a 5-year plan) are
mainly paraphrased as expanding those right now provides little value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the epics themselves are not fully described in the strategy (the visions
give the rough approach), drafting these out is a way to verify if the vision
statements are feasible and correct, and is a way to check if the organization
understands and supports the vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the moment I got the request to the final draft of the strategy note,
around 2 months have passed. The first draft was slideware and showed the
intentions towards management (who wanted feedback within a few weeks after
the request), after which the strategy was codified in a large document, and
brought for approval on the appropriate boards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was only the first hurdle though. Next was to communicate this strategy
further&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication and involvement are key&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strategic document was almost finalized when COVID-19 struck. The company
moved to working at home, and the way of working changed a lot. This also
impacted how to approach the communication of the strategy and trying to get
involvement of people. Rather than physically explaining the strategy, watching
the body language of the people to see if they understand and support it or
not, I was facing digital meetings where we did not yet have video.
Furthermore, the organization was moving towards a more distributed approach
with smaller teams (higher agility) with fewer means of bringing out
information to larger groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I selected a few larger meetings (such as those where all product managers and
system architects are present) to present and discuss the strategy, but also
started making webinars on this so that interested people could get informed
about it. I even decided to have two webinars: a very short one (3 minutes)
which focuses on the principles alone (and quickly summarizes the vision
statements), and an average one (20-ish minutes) which covers the principles
and vision statements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also made recordings of the full explanations (e.g. those to management
team), which take 1 hour, but did not move those towards a webinar (due to
time pressure). Of course, I also published the strategy document itself for
everyone, as well as the slides that accompany it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the next steps is to translate the strategy further towards the
specific agile release trains, drafting up specific roadmaps, etc. This will
also allow me to communicate and explain the strategy further. Right now, this
is where we are at - and while I am happy with the strategy content, I do feel
that the communication part received too little attention from myself, and is
something I need to continue to put focus on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a strategy is not absorbed by the organization, it fails as a strategy. And
if you do not have sufficient collaboration on the strategy after it was
'finalized' (not just communication but collaboration) then the organization
cannot absorb it. I also understand that the infrastructure strategy isn't
the only one guiding the organization: each domain has a strategy, and
while the domain architects do try to get the strategies aligned (or at least
not contradictory to each other), it is still not a single, company-wide
strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, colleagues are working on consolidating the various strategies on
architectural level, while the agile organization is using the strategies to
formulate their specific solution visions (and for a handful of solutions I'm
also directly involved).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll see how it pans out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, do you think this is a sensible approach I took? How did you tackle
communication and collaboration of such initiatives during COVID-19 measures? &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category></entry><entry><title>Project prioritization</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2017/07/project-prioritization/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-18T20:40:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-18T20:40:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-07-18:/2017/07/project-prioritization/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;This is a long read, skip to Prioritizing the projects and changes for the
approach details...&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations and companies generally have an IT workload (dare I say,
backlog?) which needs to be properly assessed, prioritized and taken up.
Sometimes, the IT team(s) get an amount of budget and HR resources to "do their
thing", while others need to continuously ask for approval to launch a new
project or instantiate a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sizeable organizations even require engineering and development effort on IT
projects which are not readily available: specialized teams exist, but they are
governance-wise assigned to projects. And as everyone thinks their project is
the top-most priority one, many will be disappointed when they hear there are
no resources available for their pet project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So... how should organizations prioritize such projects?&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;This is a long read, skip to Prioritizing the projects and changes for the
approach details...&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations and companies generally have an IT workload (dare I say,
backlog?) which needs to be properly assessed, prioritized and taken up.
Sometimes, the IT team(s) get an amount of budget and HR resources to "do their
thing", while others need to continuously ask for approval to launch a new
project or instantiate a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sizeable organizations even require engineering and development effort on IT
projects which are not readily available: specialized teams exist, but they are
governance-wise assigned to projects. And as everyone thinks their project is
the top-most priority one, many will be disappointed when they hear there are
no resources available for their pet project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So... how should organizations prioritize such projects?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structure your workload, the SAFe approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A first exercise you want to implement is to structure the workload, ideas or
projects. Some changes are small, others are large. Some are disruptive, others
are evolutionary. Trying to prioritize all different types of ideas and changes
in the same way is not feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structuring workload is a common approach. Changes are grouped in projects,
projects grouped in programs, programs grouped in strategic tracks. Lately,
with the rise in Agile projects, a similar layering approach is suggested in
the form of SAFe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="http://www.scaledagileframework.com/"&gt;Scaled Agile Framework&lt;/a&gt; a structure is suggested that uses, as a
top-level approach, value streams. These are strategically aligned steps that
an organization wants to use to build solutions that provide a continuous flow
of value to a customer (which can be internal or external). For instance, for a
financial service organization, a value stream could focus on 'Risk Management
and Analytics'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SAFe full framework" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/201707/safe-full.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;SAFe full framework overview, picture courtesy of www.scaledagileframework.com&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The value streams are supported through solution trains, which implement
particular solutions. This could be a final product for a customer (fitting in
a particular value stream) or a set of systems which enable capabilities for a
value stream. It is at this level, imo, that the benefits exercises from IT
portfolio management and benefits realization management research plays its
role (more about that later). For instance, a solution train could focus on an
'Advanced Analytics Platform'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a solution train, agile release trains provide continuous delivery for
the various components or services needed within one or more solutions. Here,
the necessary solutions are continuously delivered in support of the solution
trains. At this level, focus is given on the culture within the organization
(think DevOps), and the relatively short-lived delivery delivery periods. This
is the level where I see 'projects' come into play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you have the individual teams working on deliverables supporting a
particular project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAFe is just one of the many methods for organization and development/delivery
management. It is a good blueprint to look into, although I fear that larger
organizations will find it challenging to dedicate resources in a manageable
way. For instance, how to deal with specific expertise across solutions which
you can't dedicate to a single solution at a time? What if your organization
only has two telco experts to support dozens of projects? Keep that in mind,
I'll come back to that later...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get non-content information about the value streams and solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next to the structuring of the workload, you need to obtain information about
the solutions that you want to implement (keeping with the SAFe terminology).
And bear in mind that seemingly dull things such as ensuring your firewalls are
up to date are also deliverables within a larger ecosystem. Now, with
information about the solutions, I don't mean the content-wise information, but
instead focus on other areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Way back, in 1952, Harry Markowitz introduced &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modern_portfolio_theory"&gt;Modern portfolio theory&lt;/a&gt; as a
mathematical framework for assembling a portfolio of assets such that the
expected return is maximized for a given level of risk (quoted from Wikipedia).
This was later used in an IT portfolio approach by McFarlan in his &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/1981/09/portfolio-approach-to-information-systems"&gt;Portfolio
Approach to Information Systems&lt;/a&gt; article, published in September 1981.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There it was already introduced that risk and return shouldn't be looked at
from an individual project viewpoint, but how it contributes to the overall
risk and return. A balance, if you wish. His article attempts to categorize
projects based on risk profiles on various areas. Personally, I see the
suggested categorization more as a way of supporting workload assessments (how
many mandays of work will this be), but I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, other publications came up which tried to document frameworks and
methodologies that facilitate project portfolio prioritization and management.
The focus often boils down to value or benefits realization. In &lt;a href="https://books.google.be/books/about/The_Information_Paradox.html?id=mk60QgAACAAJ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&amp;amp;hl=en"&gt;The
Information Paradox&lt;/a&gt; John Thorp comes up with a benefits realization
approach, which enables organizations to better define and track benefits
realization - although it again boils down on larger transformation exercises
rather than the lower-level backlogs. The realm of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IT_portfolio_management"&gt;IT portfolio management&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benefits_realisation_management"&gt;Benefits realization management&lt;/a&gt; gives interesting pointers as to
the lecture part of prioritizing projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, although one can hardly state the resources are incorrect, a common
question is how to make this tangible. Personally, I tend to view the above on
the value stream level and solution train level.  Here, we have a strong
alignment with benefits and value for customers, and we can leverage the ideas
of past research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information needed at this level often boils down to strategic insights and
business benefits, coarse-grained resource assessments, with an important focus
on quality of the resources. For instance, a solution delivery might take up
500 days of work (rough estimation) but will also require significant back-end
development resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handling value streams and solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we implement this on the highest level in the structure, it should be
conceivable that the overview of the value streams (a dozen or so) and
solutions (a handful per value stream) is manageable, and something that at an
executive level is feasible to work with. These are the larger efforts for
structuring and making strategic alignment. Formal methods for prioritization
are generally not implemented or described.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my company, there are exercises that are aligning with SAFe, but it isn't
company-wide. Still, there is a structure in place that (within IT) one could
map to value streams (with some twisting ;-) and, within value streams, there
are structures in place that one could map to the solution train exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could assume that the enterprise knows about its resources (people, budget
...) and makes a high-level suggestion on how to distribute the resources in
the mid-term (such as the next 6 months to a year). This distribution is
challenged and worked out with the value stream owners. See also "lean
budgeting" in the SAFe approach for one way of dealing with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no prioritization of value streams. The enterprise has already made
its decision on what it finds to be the important values and benefits and
decided those in value streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within a value stream, the owner works together with the customers (internal or
external) to position and bring out solutions. My experience here is that
prioritization is generally based on timings and expectations from the
customer. In case of resource contention, the most challenging decision to make
here is to put a solution down (meaning, not to pursue the delivery of a
solution), and such decisions are hardly taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prioritizing the projects and changes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the lower echelons of the project portfolio structure, we have the projects
and changes. Let's say that the levels here are projects (agile release trains)
and changes (team-level). Here, I tend to look at prioritization on project
level, and this is the level that has a more formal approach for
prioritization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Because unlike the higher levels, where the prioritization is generally
quality-oriented on a manageable amount of streams and solutions, we have a
large quantity of projects and ideas. Hence, prioritization is more
quantity-oriented in which formal methods are more efficient to handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method that is used in my company uses scoring criteria on a per-project
level. This is not innovative per se, as past research has also revealed that
project categorization and mapping is a powerful approach for handling project
portfolio's. Just look for "categorizing priority projects it portfolio" in
Google and you'll find ample resources. Kendal's &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Advanced-Project-Portfolio-Management-PMO/dp/1932159029"&gt;Advanced Project Portfolio
Management and the PMO&lt;/a&gt; (book) has several example project scoring
criteria's. But allow me to explain our approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It basically is like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each project selects three value drivers (list decided up front)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the value drivers, the projects check if they contribute to it slightly (low), moderately (medium) or fully (high)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The value drivers have weights, as do the values. Sum the resulting products to get a priority score&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have the priority score validated by a scoring team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's get to the details of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the IT projects within the infrastructure area (which is what I'm active
in), we have around 5 scoring criteria (value drivers) that are value-stream
agnostic, and then 3 to 5 scoring criteria that are value-stream specific. Each
scoring criteria has three potential values: low (2), medium (4) and high (9).
The numbers are the weights that are given to the value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A scoring criteria also has a weight. For instance, we have a scoring criteria
on efficiency (read: business case) which has a weight of 15, so a score of
medium within that criteria gives a total value of 60 (4 times 15). The
potential values here are based on the "return on investment" value, with low
being a return less than 2 years, medium within a year, and high within a few
months (don't hold me on the actual values, but you get the idea).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sum of all values gives a priority score. Now, hold your horses, because
we're not done yet. There is a scoring rule that says a project can only be
scored by at most 3 scoring criteria. Hence, project owners need to see what
scoring areas their project is mostly visible in, and use those scoring
criteria. This rule supports the notion that people don't bring around ideas
that will fix world hunger and make a cure for cancer, but specific, well
scoped ideas (the former are generally huge projects, while the latter requires
much less resources).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so you have a score - is that your priority? No. As a project always falls
within a particular value stream, we have a "scoring team" for each value
stream which does a number of things. First, it checks if your project really
belongs in the right value stream (but that's generally implied) and has a
deliverable that fits the solution or target within that stream. Projects that
don't give any value or aren't asked by customers are eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, the team validates if the scoring that was used is correct: did you
select the right values (low, medium or high) matching the methodology for said
criteria? If not, then the score is adjusted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the team validates if the resulting score is perceived to be OK or
not. Sometimes, ideas just don't map correctly on scoring criteria, and even
though a project has a huge strategic importance or deliverable it might score
low. In those cases, the scoring team can adjust the score manually. However,
this is more of a fail-safe (due to the methodology) rather than the norm.
About one in 20 projects gets its score adjusted. If too many adjustments come
up, the scoring team will suggest a change in methodology to rectify the
situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the score obtained and validated by the scoring team, the project is given
a "go" to move to the project governance. It is the portfolio manager that then
uses the scores to see when a project can start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Providing levers to management&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, these scoring criteria are not established from a random number generator.
An initial suggestion was made on the scoring criteria, and their associated
weights, to the higher levels within the organization (read: the people in
charge of the prioritization and challenging of value streams and solutions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same people are those that approve the weights on the scoring criteria. If
management (as this is often the level at which this is decided) feels that
business case is, overall, more important than risk reduction, then they will
be able to put a higher value in the business case scoring than in the risk
reduction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only constraint is that the total value of all scoring criteria must be
fixed. So an increase on one scoring criteria implies a reduction on at least
one other scoring criteria. Also, changing the weights (or even the scoring
criteria themselves) cannot be done frequently. There is some inertia in
project prioritization: not the implementation (because that is a matter of
following through) but the support it will get in the organization itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Management can then use external benchmarks and other sources to gauge the
level that an organization is at, and then - if needed - adjust the scoring
weights to fit their needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource allocation in teams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Portfolio managers use the scores assigned to the projects to drive their
decisions as to when (and which) projects to launch. The trivial approach is to
always pick the projects with the highest scores. But that's not all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects can have dependencies on other projects. If these dependencies are
"hard" and non-negotiable, then the upstream project (the one being dependent
on) inherits the priority of the downstream project (the one depending on the
first) if the downstream project has a higher priority. Soft dependencies
however need to validate if they can (or have to) wait, or can implement
workarounds if needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects also have specific resource requirements. A project might have a high
priority, but if it requires expertise (say DBA knowledge) which is unavailable
(because those resources are already assigned to other ongoing projects) then
the project will need to wait (once resources are fully allocated and the
projects are started, then they need to finish - another reason why projects
have a narrow scope and an established timeframe).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For engineers, operators, developers and other roles, this approach allows them
to see which workload is more important versus others. When their scope is
always within a single value stream, then the mentioned method is sufficient.
But what if a resource has two projects, each of a different value stream? As
each value stream has its own scoring criteria it can use (and weight), one
value stream could systematically have higher scores than others...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mixing and matching multiple value streams&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To allow projects to be somewhat comparable in priority values, an additional
rule has been made in the scoring methodology: value streams must have a
comparable amount of scoring criteria (value drivers), and the total value of
all criteria must be fixed (as was already mentioned before). So if there are
four scoring criteria and the total value is fixed at 20, then one value stream
can have its criteria at (5,3,8,4) while another has it at (5,5,5,5).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is still not fully adequate, as one value stream could use a single
criteria with the maximum amount (20,0,0,0). However, we elected not to put in
an additional constraint, and have management work things out if the situation
ever comes out. Luckily, even managers are just human and they tend to follow
the notion of well-balanced value drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that two projects will have priority values that are currently
sufficiently comparable to allow cross-value-stream experts to be exchangeable
without monopolizing these important resources to a single value stream
portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current state&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scoring methodology has been around for a few years already. Initially, it
had fixed scoring criteria used by three value streams (out of seven, the other
ones did not use the same methodology), but this year we switched to support
both value stream agnostic criteria (like in the past) as well as value stream
specific ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methodology is furthest progressed in one value stream (with focus of around
1000 projects) and is being taken up by two others (they are still looking at
what their stream-specific criteria are before switching).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category><category term="pmo"></category><category term="strategy"></category><category term="SAFe"></category><category term="prioritization"></category><category term="project"></category></entry><entry><title>Structuring infrastructural deployments</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-07T20:40:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-07T20:40:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-06-07:/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many organizations struggle with the all-time increase in IP address
allocation and the accompanying need for segmentation. In the past, governing
the segments within the organization means keeping close control over the
service deployments, firewall rules, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the idea of micro-segmentation, supported through software-defined
networking solutions, seems to defy the need for a segmentation governance.
However, I think that that is a very short-sighted sales proposition. Even
with micro-segmentation, or even pure point-to-point / peer2peer communication
flow control, you'll still be needing a high level overview of the services
within your scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I'll give some insights in how we are approaching this in
the company I work for. In short, it starts with requirements gathering,
creating labels to assign to deployments, creating groups based on one or two
labels in a layered approach, and finally fixating the resulting schema and
start mapping guidance documents (policies) toward the presented architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many organizations struggle with the all-time increase in IP address
allocation and the accompanying need for segmentation. In the past, governing
the segments within the organization means keeping close control over the
service deployments, firewall rules, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the idea of micro-segmentation, supported through software-defined
networking solutions, seems to defy the need for a segmentation governance.
However, I think that that is a very short-sighted sales proposition. Even
with micro-segmentation, or even pure point-to-point / peer2peer communication
flow control, you'll still be needing a high level overview of the services
within your scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I'll give some insights in how we are approaching this in
the company I work for. In short, it starts with requirements gathering,
creating labels to assign to deployments, creating groups based on one or two
labels in a layered approach, and finally fixating the resulting schema and
start mapping guidance documents (policies) toward the presented architecture.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As always, start with the requirements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an infrastructure architect point of view, creating structure is one way
of dealing with the onslaught in complexity that is prevalent within the wider
organizational architecture. By creating a framework in which infrastructural
services can be positioned, architects and other stakeholders (such as
information security officers, process managers, service delivery owners, project
and team leaders ...) can support the wide organization in its endeavor of
becoming or remaining competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Structure can be provided through various viewpoints. As such, while creating
such framework, the initial intention is not to start drawing borders or
creating a complex graph. Instead, look at attributes that one would assign
to an infrastructural service, and treat those as labels. Create a nice
portfolio of attributes which will help guide the development of such framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following list gives some ideas in labels or attributes that one can use.
But be creative, and use experienced people in devising the "true" list of
attributes that fits the needs of your organization. Be sure to describe them
properly and unambiguously - the list here is just an example, as are the
descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tenant&lt;/strong&gt; identifies the organizational aggregation of business units which are
  sufficiently similar in areas such as policies (same policies in use),
  governance (decision bodies or approval structure), charging, etc. It
  could be a hierarchical aspect (such as organization) as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;location&lt;/strong&gt; provides insight in the physical (if applicable) location of the
  service. This could be an actual building name, but can also be structured
  depending on the size of the environment. If it is structured, make sure to
  devise a structure up front. Consider things such as regions, countries,
  cities, data centers, etc. A special case location value could be the
  jurisdiction, if that is something that concerns the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;service type&lt;/strong&gt; tells you what kind of service an asset is. It can be a
  workstation, a server/host, server/guest, network device, virtual or
  physical appliance, sensor, tablet, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;trust level&lt;/strong&gt; provides information on how controlled and trusted the service
  is. Consider the differences between unmanaged (no patching, no users doing
  any maintenance), open (one or more admins, but no active controlled
  maintenance), controlled (basic maintenance and monitoring, but with still
  administrative access by others), managed (actively maintained, no privileged
  access without strict control), hardened (actively maintained, additional
  security measures taken) and kiosk (actively maintained, additional security
  measures taken and limited, well-known interfacing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;compliance set&lt;/strong&gt; identifies specific compliance-related attributes, such as the
  PCI-DSS compliancy level that a system has to adhere to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;consumer group&lt;/strong&gt; informs about the main consumer group, active on the service.
  This could be an identification of the relationship that consumer group has
  with the organization (anonymous, customer, provider, partner, employee, ...)
  or the actual name of the consumer group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;architectural purpose&lt;/strong&gt; gives insight in the purpose of the service in
  infrastructural terms. Is it a client system, a gateway, a mid-tier system,
  a processing system, a data management system, a batch server, a reporting
  system, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;domain&lt;/strong&gt; could be interpreted as to the company purpose of the system. Is it for
  commercial purposes (such as customer-facing software), corporate functions
  (company management), development, infrastructure/operations ...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;production status&lt;/strong&gt; provides information about the production state of a
  service. Is it a production service, or a pre-production (final testing before
  going to production), staging (aggregation of multiple changes) or development
  environment?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the final set of labels, the next step is to aggregate results to create
a high-level view of the environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating a layered structure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are high that you'll end up with several attributes, and many of these
will have multiple possible values. What we don't want is to end in an
N-dimensional infrastructure architecture overview. Sure, it sounds sexy to do
so, but you want to show the infrastructure architecture to several stakeholders
in your organization. And projecting an N-dimensional structure on a
2-dimensional slide is not only challenging - you'll possibly create a projection
which leaves out important details or make it hard to interpret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, we looked at a &lt;em&gt;layered approach&lt;/em&gt;, with each layer handling one or two
requirements. The top layer represents the requirement which the organization
seems to see as the most defining attribute. It is the attribute where, if its
value changes, most of its architecture changes (and thus the impact of a service
relocation is the largest).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose for instance that the domain attribute is seen as the most defining one:
the organization has strict rules about placing corporate services and commercial
services in separate environments, or the security officers want to see the
commercial services, which are well exposed to many end users, be in a separate
environment from corporate services. Or perhaps the company offers commercial
services for multiple tenants, and as such wants several separate "commercial
services" environments while having a single corporate service domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, part of the infrastructure architecture overview on the top level
could look like so (hypothetical example):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Top level view" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/201706/07-1-toplevelview.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also shows that, next to the corporate and commercial interests of the
organization, a strong development support focus is prevalent as well. This
of course depends on the type of organization or company and how significant
in-house development is, but in this example it is seen as a major decisive
factor for service positioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These top-level blocks (depicted as locations, for those of you using Archimate)
are what we call "&lt;strong&gt;zones&lt;/strong&gt;". These are not networks, but clearly bounded areas in
which multiple services are positioned, and for which particular handling rules
exist. These rules are generally written down in policies and standards - more
about that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside each of these zones, a substructure is made available as well, based on
another attribute. For instance, let's assume that this is the architectural
purpose. This could be because the company has a requirement on segregating
workstations and other client-oriented zones from the application hosting related
ones. Security-wise, the company might have a principle where mid-tier services
(API and presentation layer exposures) are separate from processing services,
and where data is located in a separate zone to ensure specific data access or
more optimal infrastructure services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This zoning result could then be depicted as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Detailed top-level view" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/201706/07-1-detailedtoplevel.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this viewpoint, we can also deduce that this company provides separate
workstation services: corporate workstation services (most likely managed
workstations with focus on application disclosure, end user computing, etc.)
and development workstations (most likely controlled workstations but with more
open privileged access for the developer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By making this separation explicit, the organization makes it clear that the
development workstations will have a different position, and even a different
access profile toward other services within the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're not done yet. For instance, on the mid-tier level, we could look at the
consumer group of the services:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mid-tier explained" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/201706/07-1-midtier.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This separation can be established due to security reasons (isolating services
that are exposed to anonymous users from customer services or even partner
services), but one can also envision this to be from a management point of
view (availability requirements can differ, capacity management is more
uncertain for anonymous-facing services than authenticated, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going one layer down, we use a production status attribute as the defining
requirement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Anonymous user detail" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/201706/07-1-anonymousdetail.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, our company decided that the defined layers are sufficiently
established and make for a good overview. We used different defining properties
than the ones displayed above (again, find a good balance that fits the company
or organization that you're focusing on), but found that the ones we used were
mostly involved in existing policies and principles, while the other ones are
not that decisive for infrastructure architectural purposes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the tenant might not be selected as a deciding attribute, because
there will be larger tenants and smaller tenants (which could make the resulting
zone set very convoluted) or because some commercial services are offered toward
multiple tenants and the organizations' strategy would be to move toward
multi-tenant services rather than multiple deployments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, in the zoning structure there is still another layer, which from an
infrastructure architecture point is less about rules and guidelines and more
about manageability from an organizational point of view. For instance, in the
above example, a SAP deployment for HR purposes (which is obviously a corporate
service) might have its Enterprise Portal service in the &lt;code&gt;Corporate Services&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; 
&lt;code&gt;Mid-tier&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Group Employees&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Production&lt;/code&gt; zone. However, another service such as
an on-premise SharePoint deployment for group collaboration might be in &lt;code&gt;Corporate
Services&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Mid-tier&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Group Employees&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Production&lt;/code&gt; zone as well. Yet both
services are supported through different teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This "final" layer thus enables grouping of services based on the supporting
team (again, this is an example), which is organizationally aligned with the
business units of the company, and potentially further isolation of services
based on other attributes which are not defining for all services. For instance,
the company might have a policy that services with a certain business impact
assessment score must be in isolated segments with no other deployments within
the same segment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about management services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the above picture is missing some of the (in my opinion) most important
services: infrastructure support and management services. These services do not
shine in functional offerings (which many non-IT people generally look at) but
are needed for non-functional requirements: manageability, cost control,
security (if security can be defined as a non-functional - let's not discuss
that right now).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's first consider &lt;em&gt;interfaces&lt;/em&gt; - gateways and other services which are
positioned between zones or the "outside world". In the past, we would speak of
a demilitarized zone (DMZ). In more recent publications, one can find this as
an interface zone, or a set of Zone Interface Points (ZIPs) for accessing and
interacting with the services within a zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases, several of these interface points and gateways are used in the
organization to support a number of non-functional requirements. They can be
used for intelligent load balancing, providing virtual patching capabilities,
validating content against malware before passing it on to the actual services,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on the top level zone, different gateways might be needed (i.e.
different requirements). Interfaces for commercial services will have a strong
focus on security and manageability. Those for the corporate services might be
more integration-oriented, and have different data leakage requirements than
those for commercial services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, inside such an interface zone, one can imagine a substructure to take
place as well: egress interfaces (for communication that is exiting the zone),
ingress interfaces (for communication that is entering the zone) and internal
interfaces (used for routing between the subzones within the zone).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, there will also be requirements which are company-wide. Hence, one could
envision a structure where there is a company-wide interface zone (with
mandatory requirements regardless of the zone that they support) as well as a
zone-specific interface zone (with the mandatory requirements specific to that
zone).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I show a picture of this, let's consider &lt;em&gt;management services&lt;/em&gt;. Unlike
interfaces, these services are more oriented toward the operational management
of the infrastructure. Software deployment, configuration management, identity
&amp;amp; access management services, etc. Are services one can put under management
services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And like with interfaces, one can envision the need for both company-wide
management services, as well as zone-specific management services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This information brings us to a final picture, one that assists the
organization in providing a more manageable view on its deployment landscape.
It does not show the 3rd layer (i.e. production versus non-production
deployments) and only displays the second layer through specialization
information, which I've quickly made a few examples for (you don't want to make
such decisions in a few hours, like I did for this post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="General overview" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/201706/07-1-firstgeneral.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the organization took an alternative approach for structuring (different
requirements and grouping) the resulting diagram could look quite different:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alternative general overview" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/201706/07-1-secondgeneral.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flows, flows and more flows&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the high-level picture ready, it is not a bad idea to look at how flows
are handled in such an architecture. As the interface layer is available on
both company-wide level as well as the next, flows will cross multiple zones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the case of a corporate workstation connecting to a reporting server
(like a Cognos or PowerBI or whatever fancy tool is used), and this reporting
server is pulling data from a database system. Now, this database system is
positioned in the &lt;code&gt;Commercial&lt;/code&gt; zone, while the reporting server is in the
&lt;code&gt;Corporate&lt;/code&gt; zone. The flows could then look like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Flow example" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/201706/07-1-flow.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Note for the Archimate people: I'm sorry that I'm abusing the flow relation
here. I didn't want to create abstract services in the locations and then use
the "serves" or "used by" relation and then explaining readers that the arrows
are then inverse from what they imagine.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this picture, the corporate workstation does not connect to the reporting
server directly. It goes through the internal interface layer for the corporate
zone. This internal interface layer can offer services such as reverse proxies
or intelligent load balancers. The idea here is that, if the organization
wants, it can introduce additional controls or supporting services in this
internal interface layer without impacting the system deployments themselves
much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the true flow challenge is in the next one, where a processing system
connects to a data layer. Here, the processing server will first connect to the
egress interface for corporate, then through the company-wide internal
interface, toward the ingress interface of the commercial and then to the data
layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, why three different interfaces, and what would be inside it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the corporate level, the egress interface could be focusing on privacy
controls or data leakage controls. On the company-wide internal interface more
functional routing capabilities could be provided, while on the commercial
level the ingress could be a database activity monitoring (DAM) system such as
a database firewall to provide enhanced auditing and access controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does that mean that all flows need to have at least three gateways? No, this is
a functional picture. If the organization agrees, then one or more of these
interface levels can have a simple pass-through setup. It is well possible that
database connections only connect directly to a DAM service and that such flows
are allowed to immediately go through other interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance thus is not to make flows more difficult to provide, but to
provide several areas where the organization can introduce controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Making policies and standards more visible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the effects of having a better structure of the company-wide deployments
(i.e. a good zoning solution) is that one can start making policies more clear,
and potentially even simple to implement with supporting tools (such as
software defined network solutions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, a company might want to protect its production data and establish
that it cannot be used for non-production use, but that there are no
restrictions for the other data environments. Another rule could be that
web-based access toward the mid-tier is only allowed through an interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are simple statements which, if a company has a good IP plan, are easy to
implement - one doesn't need zoning, although it helps. But it goes further
than access controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the company might require corporate workstations to be under
heavy data leakage prevention and protection measures, while developer
workstations are more open (but don't have any production data access). This
not only reveals an access control, but also implies particular minimal
requirements (for the &lt;code&gt;Corporate&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Workstation&lt;/code&gt; zone) and services (for the
&lt;code&gt;Corporate&lt;/code&gt; interfaces).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This zoning structure does not necessarily make any statements about the
location (assuming it isn't picked as one of the requirements in the
beginning). One can easily extend this to include cloud-based services or
services offered by third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it also supports making policies and standards more realistic. I often
see policies that make bold statements such as "all software deployments must
be done through the company software distribution tool", but the policies don't
consider development environments (production status) or unmanaged, open or
controlled deployments (trust level). When challenged, the policy owner might
shrug away the comment with "it's obvious that this policy does not apply to
our sandbox environment" or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a proper zoning structure, policies can establish the rules for the right
set of zones, and actually pin-point which zones are affected by a statement.
This is also important if a company has many, many policies. With a good zoning
structure, the policies can be assigned with meta-data so that affected roles
(such as project leaders, architects, solution engineers, etc.) can easily get
an overview of the policies that influence a given zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, if I want to position a new management service, I am less
concerned about workstation-specific policies. And if the management service is
specific for the development environment (such as a new version control system)
many corporate or commercially oriented policies don't apply either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above approach for structuring an organization is documented here in a
high-level manner. It takes many assumptions or hypothetical decisions which
are to be tailored toward the company itself. In my company, a different zoning
structure is selected, taking into account that it is a financial service
provider with entities in multiple countries, handling several thousand of
systems and with an ongoing effort to include cloud providers within its
infrastructure architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the approach itself is followed in an equal fashion. We looked at
requirements, created a layered structure, and finished the zoning schema. Once
the schema was established, the requirements for all the zones were written out
further, and a mapping of existing deployments (as-is) toward the new zoning
picture is on-going. For those thinking that it is just slideware right now -
it isn't. Some of the structures that come out of the zoning exercise are
already prevalent in the organization, and new environments (due to mergers and
acquisitions) are directed to this new situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, we know we have a large exercise ahead before it is finished, but I
believe that it will benefit us greatly, not only from a security point of
view, but also clarity and manageability of the environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category><category term="segmentation"></category><category term="zoning"></category><category term="deployments"></category><category term="landscape"></category></entry><entry><title>Switching focus at work</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-20T13:29:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-20T13:29:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-09-20:/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, I was at work responsible for the infrastructure architecture of 
a couple of technological domains, namely databases and scheduling/workload 
automation. It brought me in contact with many vendors, many technologies
and most importantly, many teams within the organization. The focus domain
was challenging, as I had to deal with the strategy on how the organization,
which is a financial institution, will deal with databases and scheduling in
the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, I was at work responsible for the infrastructure architecture of 
a couple of technological domains, namely databases and scheduling/workload 
automation. It brought me in contact with many vendors, many technologies
and most importantly, many teams within the organization. The focus domain
was challenging, as I had to deal with the strategy on how the organization,
which is a financial institution, will deal with databases and scheduling in
the long term.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means looking at the investments related to those domains, implementation
details, standards of use, features that we will or will not use, positioning
of products and so forth. To do this from an architecture point of view means
that I not only had to focus on the details of the technology and understand 
all their use, but also become a sort-of subject matter expert on those topics.
Luckily, I had (well, still have) great teams of DBAs (for the databases) and
batch teams (for the scheduling/workload automation) to keep things in the right
direction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I helped them with a (hopefully sufficiently) clear roadmap, investment track,
procurement, contract/terms and conditions for use, architectural decisions and
positioning and what not. And they helped me with understanding the various
components, learn about the best use of these, and of course implement the 
improvements that we collaboratively put on the roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Times, they are changing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I flipped over a page at work. Although I remain an IT architect
within the same architecture team, my focus shifts entirely. Instead of a fixed
domain, my focus is now more volatile. I leave behind the stability of 
organizationally anchored technology domains and go forward in a more tense
environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of looking at just two technology domains, I need to look at all of them,
and find the right balance between high flexibility demands (which might not want
to use current "standard" offerings) which come up from a very agile context, and
the almost non-negotionable requirements that are typical for financial institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus is also not primarily technology oriented anymore. I'll be part of an 
enterprise architecture team with direct business involvement and although my
main focus will be on the technology side, it'll also involve information
management, business processes and applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end goal is to set up a future-proof architecture in an agile, fast-moving
environment (contradictio in terminis ?) which has a main focus in data analytics
and information gathering/management. Yes, "big data", but more applied than what
some of the vendors try to sell us ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm currently finishing off the high-level design and use of a Hadoop platform,
and the next focus will be on a possible micro-service architecture using Docker.
I've been working on this Hadoop design for a while now (but then it was together
with my previous function at work) and given the evolving nature of Hadoop (and
the various services that surround it) I'm confident that it will not be the last
time I'm looking at it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let me hope I can keep things manageable ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category><category term="work"></category><category term="hadoop"></category><category term="docker"></category></entry><entry><title>Making the case for multi-instance support</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2015/08/making-the-case-for-multi-instance-support/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-22T12:45:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-08-22T12:45:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-08-22:/2015/08/making-the-case-for-multi-instance-support/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the high attention that technologies such as &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://coreos.com/blog/rocket/"&gt;Rocket&lt;/a&gt; and the like get (I recommend to look at 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/p8952/bocker"&gt;Bocker&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Wilmott as well ;-), I
still find it important that technologies are well capable of supporting a
multi-instance environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to run multiple instances makes for great consolidation. The system
can be optimized for the technology, access to the system limited to the admins
of said technology while still providing isolation between instances. For some
technologies, running on commodity hardware just doesn't cut it (not all 
software is written for such hardware platforms) and consolidation allows for
reducing (hardware/licensing) costs.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With the high attention that technologies such as &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://coreos.com/blog/rocket/"&gt;Rocket&lt;/a&gt; and the like get (I recommend to look at 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/p8952/bocker"&gt;Bocker&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Wilmott as well ;-), I
still find it important that technologies are well capable of supporting a
multi-instance environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to run multiple instances makes for great consolidation. The system
can be optimized for the technology, access to the system limited to the admins
of said technology while still providing isolation between instances. For some
technologies, running on commodity hardware just doesn't cut it (not all 
software is written for such hardware platforms) and consolidation allows for
reducing (hardware/licensing) costs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Examples of multi-instance technologies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A first example that I'm pretty familiar with is multi-instance database
deployments: Oracle DBs, SQL Servers, PostgreSQLs, etc. The consolidation
of databases while still keeping multiple instances around (instead of
consolidating into a single instance itself) is mainly for operational 
reasons (changes should not influence other database/schema's) or
technical reasons (different requirements in parameters, locales, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other examples are web servers (for web hosting companies), which next to
virtual host support (which is still part of a single instance) could
benefit from multi-instance deployments for security reasons (vulnerabilities
might be better contained then) as well as performance tuning. Same goes
for web application servers (such as TomCat deployments).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even other technologies like mail servers can benefit from multiple
instance deployments. Postfix has a &lt;a href="http://www.postfix.org/MULTI_INSTANCE_README.html"&gt;nice guide&lt;/a&gt;
on multi-instance deployments and also covers some of the use cases for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advantages of multi-instance setups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary objective that most organizations have when dealing with multiple
instances is the consolidation to reduce cost. Especially expensive, 
propriatary software which is CPU licensed gains a lot from consolidation 
(and don't think a CPU is a CPU, each company
&lt;a href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/passportadvantage/pvu_licensing_for_customers.html"&gt;has&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.oracle.com/us/corporate/contracts/processor-core-factor-table-070634.pdf"&gt;its&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)
&lt;a href="go.microsoft.com/fwlink/?LinkID=229882"&gt;own&lt;/a&gt; (PDF) core weight table to
get the most money out of their customers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But beyond cost savings, using multi-instance deployments also provides for
resource sharing. A high-end server can be used to host the multiple instances,
with for instance SSD disks (or even flash cards), more memory, high-end CPUs,
high-speed network connnectivity and more. This improves performance considerably,
because most multi-instance technologies don't need all resources continuously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage, if properly designed, is that multi-instance capable software
can often leverage the multi-instance deployments for fast changes. A database
might be easily patched (remove vulnerabilities) by creating a second codebase
deployment, patching that codebase, and then migrating the database from one
instance to another. Although it often still requires downtime, it can be made
considerably less, and roll-back of such changes is very easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A last advantage that I see is security. Instances can be running as different
runtime accounts, through different SELinux contexts, bound on different
interfaces or chrooted into different locations. This is not an advantage
compared to dedicated systems of course, but more an advantage compared
to full consolidation (everything in a single instance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't always focus on multi-instance setups though&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple instances isn't a silver bullet. Some technologies are generally much
better when there is a single instance on a single operating system. Personally,
I find that such technologies should know better. If they are really designed to
be suboptimal in case of multi-instance deployments, then there is a design error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when the advantages of multiple instances do not exist (no license cost,
hardware cost is low, etc.) then organizations might focus on single-instance
deployments, because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;multi-instance deployments might require more users to access the system
  (especially when it is multi-tenant)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;operational activities might impact other instances (for instance updating 
  kernel parameters for one instance requires a reboot which affects other
  instances)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the software might not be properly "multi-instance aware" and as such
  starts fighting for resources with its own sigbling instances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that properly designed architectures are well capable of using
virtualization (and in the future containerization) moving towards
single-instance deployments becomes more and more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What should multi-instance software consider?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software should, imo, always consider multi-instance deployments. Even
when the administrator decides to stick with a single instance, all that
that takes is that the software ends up with a "single instance" setup
(it is &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; easier to support multiple instances and deploy a single one,
than to support single instances and deploy multiple ones).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing software should take into account is that it might (and
will) run with different runtime accounts - service accounts if you whish.
That means that the software should be well aware that file locations are
separate, and that these locations will have different access control settings
on them (if not just a different owner).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead of using &lt;code&gt;/etc/foo&lt;/code&gt; as the mandatory location, consider supporting
&lt;code&gt;/etc/foo/instance1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;/etc/foo/instance2&lt;/code&gt; if full directories are needed, or
just have &lt;code&gt;/etc/foo1.conf&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;/etc/foo2.conf&lt;/code&gt;. I prefer the directory approach,
because it makes management much easier. It then also makes sense that the log
location is &lt;code&gt;/var/log/foo/instance1&lt;/code&gt;, the data files are at &lt;code&gt;/var/lib/foo/instance1&lt;/code&gt;,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second is that, if a service is network-facing (which most of them
are), it must be able to either use multihomed systems easily (bind to
different interfaces) or use different ports. The latter is a challenge
I often come across with software - the way to configure the software to
deal with multiple deployments and multiple ports is often a lengthy
trial-and-error setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's so difficult with using a &lt;em&gt;base port&lt;/em&gt; setting, and document how the
other ports are derived from this base port. &lt;a href="http://neo4j.com/docs/stable/ha-setup-tutorial.html"&gt;Neo4J&lt;/a&gt;
needs 3 ports for its enterprise services (transactions, cluster management
and online backup), but they all need to be explicitly configured if you
want a multi-instance deployment. What if one could just set &lt;code&gt;baseport = 5001&lt;/code&gt;
with the software automatically selecting 5002 and 5003 as other ports (or 6001
and 7001). If the software in the future needs another port, there is no need
to update the configuration (assuming the administrator leaves sufficient room).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also consider the service scripts (&lt;code&gt;/etc/init.d&lt;/code&gt;) or similar (depending on the
init system used). Don't provide a single one which only deals with one instance.
Instead, consider supporting symlinked service scripts which automatically obtain
the right configuration from its name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, a service script called &lt;code&gt;pgsql-inst1&lt;/code&gt; which is a symlink to
&lt;code&gt;/etc/init.d/postgresql&lt;/code&gt; could then look for its configuration in &lt;code&gt;/var/lib/postgresql/pgsql-inst1&lt;/code&gt;
(or &lt;code&gt;/etc/postgresql/pgsql-inst1&lt;/code&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like supporting &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2013/05/the-linux-d-approach/"&gt;.d directories&lt;/a&gt;,
I consider multi-instance support an important non-functional requirement for software.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category></entry></feed>