<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - Architecture</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 09:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>Ownership and responsibilities for infrastructure services</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2022/01/ownership-and-responsibilities-for-infrastructure-services/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In a perfect world, using infrastructure or technology services would be
seamless, without impact, without risks. It would auto-update, tailor to
the user needs, detect when new features are necessary, adapt, etc. But
while this is undoubtedly what vendors are saying their product delivers,
the truth is way, waaaay different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing infrastructure services implies that the company or organization
needs to organize itself to deal with all aspects of supporting a service.
What are these aspects? Well, let's go through those that are top-of-mind
for me...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operational support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have a service running, then you need to ensure operational
support is in place in case there are issues. Be it to resolve a
malfunction, a security issue, or a performance degradation - you need
(human) resources to ensure that the service remains running adequately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many organizations, this is handled in a three- or sometimes 
even four-level support structure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;First line&lt;/em&gt; is generally a call center that procedurally validates if
  an issue is service-bound, or if they can assist the user to correctly
  or better use the service. &lt;em&gt;First line&lt;/em&gt; often does not require any
  knowledge of the customer base nor target infrastructure, and is strongly
  procedure-oriented. They do not have operational duties on the services
  themselves, and are an important part to weed out unstructured or invalid
  service requests. They then escalate the issues to &lt;em&gt;second line&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Second line&lt;/em&gt; is an organization that has knowledge on the customer
  base and the services themselves. They are also often the last line
  that has a wide view of all services within the company, as subsequent
  support levels are more specialized. &lt;em&gt;Second line&lt;/em&gt; has the ability to
  take actions on the services themselves (like restarting services)
  if this is agreed upon in the past with the main stakeholders, and when
  this is executed in a controlled manner. If &lt;em&gt;second line&lt;/em&gt; isn't able to
  resolve an issue, it moves to &lt;em&gt;third line&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Third line&lt;/em&gt; support is generally the team that is operationally involved
  in the service itself. If the problem lays with a customer portal for
  instance, then &lt;em&gt;third line support&lt;/em&gt; is often the team that maintains the
  customer portal. They know the service and its usage in detail, and are
  in many organizations the last line of support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some organizations even continue this layering, with a fourth line of
support being a technical expert in a particular component used by the
service. If the customer portal has problems, and it is within the database,
and the DBAs of the customer portal team do not have the knowledge to
resolve it, they might escalate further to a dedicated DBA team (which
is not assigned to any particular business service but specifically
organized to be experts in database and database administration).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all companies have a technology-oriented support team though, and
many companies will consider this as part of 3rd line support as well,
if not just to be more aligned with market terminology on support structures.
Still, organizing and optimizing this third line of support is often
something that infrastructure service support is heavily involved in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the structure approached by the organization, these teams
will need the knowledge and supporting tools and procedures to do their job.
You need people that can develop support procedures, create simplified
automation (for second line to execute), and continuously update that
information. And if a vendor is involved, then the support line will need to
have knowledge on how to approach the vendor: what are the procedures and
processes for raising incidents, what is the priority queue like? Does
the vendor have certain SLAs that the team should know about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The several layers of support will need continuous training, even if it
is just refreshing past information. It is also wise to involve these
support lines in information sharing, like when you know there is a growth
in database reliance in the business services, or when you know many
databases are being migrated from one technology to another. Second line
for instance might be able to use that information, together with their
cross-organizational knowledge, to better triage issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, this support structure is often tied to service level agreements that
the company makes either internally, or with its customers. Hence, the support
must be guaranteed within those SLAs. That implies that the support must be
driven through multiple people, as the organization has to provide support
during off-hours, during holidays, during absence... heck, even during global
pandemics. I use the "3 FTE per technology" principle: you need three people
with enough knowledge to support the technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintenance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the support part, teams exist that are responsible for
the service itself, including patching and updates. This is part of the
maintenance requirement on services, and infrastructure services are not
different. Perhaps even more so than business services, infrastructure
services have a wider impact if they are hit with a bug or with
performance degradation, as many business services rely on the infrastructure
to be up and running, highly available, well-performing, and secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maintenance tasks for services include, alongside the participation in the
operational support:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executing security- and stability patch validation and roll-out (updates)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proactively assessing the state of the service to see if improvements
  or mitigations are needed, before these result in actual issues&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensuring sufficient capacity is available for now and in the immediate
  future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resolving performance issues, be it by increasing resources, moving
  services to different locations or hosts, fine-tuning configuration
  parameters, offloading workload to different services, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executing planned maintenance activities, which can include upgrades
  to higher versions. When the service cannot be transparently upgraded,
  this will involve a thorough alignment with all stakeholders as part of
  the change management processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In case of larger, wide-spanning incidents (or even disasters), the teams
  play an active role in the orchestrated recovery together with all other
  teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designing and architecting the integrations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure that the services are well supported and can be maintained in
an efficient manner, there is often a strong focus on the proper design of
the infrastructure services and their role in the architecture. This
design does not just include pointing out which components exist where,
but also how the service integrates within the larger landscape:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are administration tasks executed? How do administrators authenticate
  themselves?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where are the monitoring metrics found and stored? Do you use trend analysis,
  and in which system?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are the assets related to the service tracked? What is the lifecycle for
  the individual assets, and how does that impact the maintainability of the
  service?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the best way to use the service, and what will not be allowed?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How are backups taken, and what does a restore procedure look like? Do you
  support both in-place restores, side restores, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What underlying resource requirements exist? Do you require certain
  tiered storage, or network performance requirements? If you allow your
  service to be instantiated by others (rather than maintain a platform
  yourself), what are the target resources that you allow? Are there
  minimal resource requirements?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do users interact with the service? Do they access it directly,
  or do you require intermediate gateways (like reverse proxies)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, design and architecture go beyond integrations. I focus strongly on
integrations here as it is a part of design and architecture that has strong
dependencies and relations with other teams and technologies. To work out
the integration side of a service, you can't do this autonomously without
assistance from the other service teams. Of course, if those teams have
everything well documented and architected, and easy to consume, then the
team responsible for the design and architecture can do a large part of the
work independently, but having a final validation or confirmation is always
beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the values of a proper integration design is a higher quality of the
service delivery. If integrations are missed, you'll find that a service 
might not be ready to be activated in production, and then suddenly there
is a stronger focus on timely delivery than on quality. Situations where
firewall rules need to be quickly pushed and opened up because a project
failed to assess their integrations, resulting in security risks, is
sadly enough all too common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Larger organizations will often have architects and designers within the teams
or directorates to support this endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secure setup and deployment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that some integrations might result in heightened risks, and
infrastructure services are often widely used or consumed, the organization
will need to make sure that the services are designed to be secure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security of a service is more than just ensuring it is up-to-date. You
will also need to make sure it is configured correctly (as misconfigurations
are a frequent occurrence of security incidents), that the authentication
and authorizations are properly designed (and where needed or possible,
using multi-factor authentication), that the deployment considers the
placement and interactions (firewalls, zoning, etc.), that the service
provides functional (or perhaps even physical) segregation, that the
data governance is appropriate and aligned with regulatory and company
requirements, that the service is continuously validated by the security
tooling available (patch indications, vulnerability management, ...), etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As services also evolve when they are alive, secure setup and deployment
is not a one-off (but the initial thoughts and designs are not to be
underestimated): the teams will need to assess the impact of new
insights (like security notifications, vulnerabilities, global changes
by the organization, new threats in the wider IT world) which implies
that the team has a continuous security and risk focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases, there is even a coding and development component with
a service. Not many services can be installed and deployed without requiring
any integration scripting or even in-depth coding (such as custom plugins).
And when there is coding, there is the need for secure coding: following
a Secure Development LifeCycle (SDLC) approach to get assurance about
the secure state of the developed code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the deployment uses infrastructure-as-code methods, follows a
GitOps approach, or similar, then there should also be sufficient attention
to the secure setup of these pipelines and the platforms on which they
run. The code (or configurations) hosted should also follow appropriate
security guidelines&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robust and reliable services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing for a trustworthy, secure environment is one thing. The other
major focus area for infrastructure services is the availability,
robustness, and resilience of the service. While not all services
require to be up and running 24/7, nowadays it is hard to imagine
many services to still have significant downtimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, you often need to architecture and design for a resilient service,
which can take a beating if it has to. Organize load- and stress testing.
Organize disruptive testing if needed, and learn from the results to build
a better service. Design for a service that you can do technical maintenance
on without disrupting the customers themselves as much as possible - but
don't overshoot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the service is set up in multiple locations, make sure that there is
independence between these locations (often across different regions) so
that failures in one region do not affect the other regions. Consider a setup
as used in many public cloud environments: high availability across availability
zones in the same region, and regional independence while allowing for
cross-region usage scenarios for the customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assess what can go wrong, and either try to update the architectures and
designs to be more resilient against these failures, or establish procedures
and processes to quickly recover. A common focus area here is to recover
from disasters (using so-called Disaster Recovery Procedures), and there 
are plenty of disasters to assess: data center failures, large Internet
outages, ransomware or other cyberattacks, worldwide epidemic outbreaks,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality assurance at all stages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organization has to be able to provide fixes for defects and problems that
were raised, or to preemptively fix issues before they reach the customers. That
doesn't mean that the organization needs to be able to develop the fixes itself:
especially with off-the-shelf products the development is done by the
independent software vendor (ISV). However, the organization does have the
responsibility to track and put their weight on this so that the issues are
indeed properly resolved (and in case of a third-party product, preferably
through a fix that is applied to the main product, and not a one-off for that
particular company). Of course, if the service is developed in-house, then the
development of the fixes has to be guaranteed by the organization as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be able to provide secure and reliable services, it is vital to have
good change management processes and tools in place so that you can
approach the various stages of quality assurance before reaching production.
In &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/12/the-pleasures-of-having-DTAP/"&gt;The pleasures of having
DTAP&lt;/a&gt; I mention
the benefits of having four environments for the various stages of a development
lifecycle (development, testing, acceptance, and production) and that is
perfectly applicable to infrastructure services as well, even when the
environments for infrastructure services might be isolated from those of the
more business-oriented development stages: you want to make sure that the
business-oriented development has production-grade services for its processes,
and not the intermediate and possibly less reliable in-development infrastructure
services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout these environments, testing can (should) be introduced to provide
guidance to the engineers and developers to improve on the service. Testing can
take several forms: unit testing within the frameworks, integration testing of
code in larger environments, integration testing of new products in those
environments, sanity testing with simple use cases to ensure nothing blows
up (figuratively... hopefully), regression tests to ensure no fixed defects
creep back in, acceptance tests for specific features or use cases, load
testing to ensure the product stays up under the expected loads (and the
individual components or services have the right performance profile), stress testing
to ensure the product is resilient against higher loads or bursts, destructive
tests to see the product behaves as expected when unauthorized usage is
performed, security testing and penetration testing to provide assurance
on the secure state of the product deployment, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases, the QA part is driven by organizational requirements, and not all
products require the same intensity on the tests and assurance levels. But, by
introducing the right automation, it is far easier to include multiple test
scenarios and test types in your pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Products then pass through the various stages according to the change
management principles and processes that are in effect in the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy and roadmap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team responsible for an infrastructure service will also need to consider
the service in the long term: is the current technology (or set of products)
still state-of-the-art, mature, and following market practices? Or does the team
consider the technology to be relatively outdated and in need of an update? When
would the right time be to address this update?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the currently used technology is nearing its end-of-sale, end-of-support
(EOS), or even end-of-life (EOL). In that case, the team has to be ready to
address these lifecycle stages accordingly, be it through migrations, or
refactoring of current usages. Perhaps the teams find that it is more sensible
to get an extended support contract in place, or that they have the ability to
take the support (including code development) completely internally. Whatever
the choice is, it has to be made clear for the wider organization, and the
support team has to be ready to take on its commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a distinction between the service (or better yet, "capability") that is
offered, versus the products and technologies that support and realize it.
Capabilities will be needed by the organization for a long, long time, whereas
the products that realize these capabilities can have much shorter timeframes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team will need to consider alternatives for the products, and see when those
alternatives make sense to address and implement. Perhaps the organization might
benefit from multiple implementations using different technologies because they
serve different usage scenarios, and the costs of keeping multiple technologies
in the air is less than the value it provides. Or perhaps an alternative needs
to be quickly realizable in case of a sudden exit scenario of the current
technology (or vendor). In that case, while the alternative doesn't need to be
up and running, the team must be able to address the change in due time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The need to have a proper roadmap on the capability and products that are being
used also reflects in the relationship that that team has with the vendor. For
strategically important products, an organization might even want to participate
in that vendor's Customer Advisory Board (CAB) or equivalent programs. The
team should have the time and resources to collaborate with that vendor to build
a partnership, participate in the conferences and other events, as that provides
input to the team on the progress and future of that product. Those insights are
primordial to properly design and organize an internal roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the internal roadmap has taken shape, then the responsible teams are
involved in supporting the organization through updates and upgrades, by
communicating the need for these upfront (so that the internal customers can
plan around it), and to track the progress so there are no lingering risks for
the wide organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More elaborate (internal) customer support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The support for the infrastructure service often has to extend beyond the
operational support that I started with in this article. Teams that provide
certain capabilities within the organization don't do this as a vendor, but as
part of that organization. So when an internal customer needs help in migrating
away from a service, the team is still involved in this process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, more elaborate support such as migrations (both towards a new technology,
service or capability, as well as migration away from it), finding
suitable alternatives that are not properly handled by the capability (and thus
might be best provided by a different team), ... helps in building out the trust
that the wider organization has in IT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost, licenses, and contractual obligations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many services have certain contractual obligations associated with them, often
known as the Terms and Conditions of the contract and product usage.
Infrastructure teams will need to make sure that these T&amp;amp;Cs are known and that
the organization adheres to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of an infrastructure service usage also needs to be correctly devised
and accounted for. Teams have to make sure the product usage remains within the
allocated licenses (or, if there is no capping in place, that the usage is
sufficiently constrained that the organization does not get any surprises), and
is often involved in defining a chargeback towards the rest of the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tend to make a distinction between showback (show the organization how much a
service costs to the company or usage group) and chargeback (a governance-driven
or tax-driven requirement for charging usage to the organization), as the latter
is more a company decision on how to approach this, whereas the showback is the
actual, factual cost. Showback is needed to support conscious decisions on next
steps or consumption patterns, whereas chargeback might be necessary for
tax reasons in larger corporations where IT is considered as part of a different
legal entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Addressing cost, licenses, and T&amp;amp;Cs is not to be underestimated. Many vendors
make this very difficult, as that allows for many interpretations during license
audits that can give a nice bonus to the vendor if he can show that his
interpretation is more appropriate than how you thought that the contract or
license was structured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of a product or technology is not just the cost of the purchase, and
even that cost is still somewhat variable: many things are open for negotiation,
and you also don't need to tackle this directly with the vendor, as there is a
large market of middle parties that facilitate purchasing technologies. These
can often provide better rates as they can bundle purchases of multiple
customers and thus negotiate better deals with the main vendor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost also depends on the support contract associated with it, as well as
the costs of other depending technologies (such as capacity requirements) that come
from its implementation. This is often neglected in SaaS purchases: even though
you have correctly negotiated a good price for the SaaS service, you might be
jeopardizing your internet connectivity and need to upgrade the bandwidth, the
anti-DDoS service, your firewall capabilities, etc. because the consumption of
that SaaS service is significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The responsibilities for managing and tracking infrastructure services are large
and not to be underestimated. It is not a matter of deploying a new service and
assuming everybody can deal with it, nor are all responsibilities equally
visible to the end-user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback? Comments? Don't hesitate to &lt;a href="mailto:sven.vermeulen@siphos.be"&gt;drop me an
email&lt;/a&gt;, or join the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/infrainsight/status/TODO"&gt;discussion on
Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Jan 2022 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2022-01-13:/2022/01/ownership-and-responsibilities-for-infrastructure-services/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>RACI</category><category>responsibilities</category></item><item><title>The pleasures of having DTAP</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/12/the-pleasures-of-having-DTAP/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;No, not Diphtheria, Tetanus, and Pertussis (vaccine), but &lt;em&gt;Development,
Test, Acceptance, and Production (DTAP)&lt;/em&gt;: different environments that,
together with a well-working release management process, provide a way to
get higher quality and reduced risks in production. DTAP is an important
cornerstone for a larger infrastructure architecture as it provides
environments that are tailored to the needs of many stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 30 Dec 2021 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-12-30:/2021/12/the-pleasures-of-having-DTAP/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>DTAP</category><category>environments</category><category>zoning</category><category>development</category><category>test</category><category>acceptance</category><category>production</category></item><item><title>Creating an enterprise open source policy</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/11/creating-an-enterprise-open-source-policy/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Nowadays it is impossible to ignore, or even prevent open source from being
active within the enterprise world. Even if a company only wants to use
commercially backed solutions, many - if not most - of these are built with, and
are using open source software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, open source is more than just a code sourcing possibility. By having a
good statement within the company on how it wants to deal with open source, what
it wants to support, etc. engineers and developers can have a better
understanding of what they can do to support their business further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cases, companies will draft up an &lt;em&gt;open source policy&lt;/em&gt;, and in this post
I want to share some practices I've learned on how to draft such a policy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-11-20:/2021/11/creating-an-enterprise-open-source-policy/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>opensource</category><category>enterprise</category><category>legal</category><category>compliance</category></item><item><title>Hybrid cloud can be very complex</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/11/hybrid-cloud-can-be-very-complex/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I am not an advocate for hybrid cloud architectures. Or at least, not the
definition for hybrid cloud that assumes one (cloud or on premise) environment
is just an extension of another (cloud or on premise) environment. While such
architectures seem to be simple and fruitful - you can easily add some capacity
in the other environment to handle burst load - they are a complex beast to
tame.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 20:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-11-08:/2021/11/hybrid-cloud-can-be-very-complex/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>hybrid</category><category>cloud</category></item><item><title>Transparent encryption is not a silver bullet</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/10/transparent-encryption-is-not-a-silver-bullet/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Transparent encryption is relatively easy to implement, but without
understanding what it actually means or why you are implementing it, you will
probably make the assumption that this will prevent the data from being
accessed by unauthorized users. Nothing can be further from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 08:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-10-19:/2021/10/transparent-encryption-is-not-a-silver-bullet/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>encryption</category><category>transparent</category><category>luks</category><category>dm-crypt</category></item><item><title>Evaluating the zero trust hype</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/10/evaluating-the-zero-trust-hype/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Security vendors are touting the benefits of "zero trust" as the new way to
approach security and security-conscious architecturing. But while there are
principles within the zero trust mindset that came up in the last dozen years,
most of the content in zero trust discussions is tied to age-old security
propositions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-10-05:/2021/10/evaluating-the-zero-trust-hype/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>zero trust</category><category>security</category><category>enterprise</category><category>network security</category></item><item><title>Scale is a cloud threat</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/scale-is-a-cloud-threat/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Not that long ago, a vulnerability was found in &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/"&gt;Microsoft Azure Cosmos
DB&lt;/a&gt;, a NoSQL SaaS database
within the Microsoft Azure cloud. The vulnerability, which is dubbed
&lt;a href="https://chaosdb.wiz.io/"&gt;ChaosDB&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/wiz_io"&gt;Wiz Research
Team&lt;/a&gt;, uses a vulnerability or misconfiguration in
the &lt;a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/cosmos-db/cosmosdb-jupyter-notebooks"&gt;Jupyter Notebook
feature&lt;/a&gt;
within Cosmos DB. This vulnerability allowed an attacker to gain access to
other's Cosmos DB credentials. Not long thereafter, a second vulnerability
dubbed
&lt;a href="https://www.wiz.io/blog/omigod-critical-vulnerabilities-in-omi-azure"&gt;OMIGOD&lt;/a&gt;
showed that cloud security is not as simple as some vendors like you to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These vulnerabilities are a good example of how scale is a cloud threat. Companies
that do not have enough experience with public cloud might not assume this in
their threat models.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Sep 2021 17:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-09-28:/2021/09/scale-is-a-cloud-threat/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>vulnerability</category></item><item><title>Naming conventions</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/naming-conventions/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Naming conventions. Picking the right naming convention is easy if you are all
by yourself, but hard when you need to agree upon the conventions in a larger
group. Everybody has an opinion on naming conventions, and once you decide
on it, you do expect everybody to follow through on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's consider why naming conventions are (not) important and consider a few
examples to help in creating a good naming convention yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 19:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-09-15:/2021/09/naming-conventions/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>naming</category></item><item><title>Location view of infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/location-view-of-infrastructure/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In this last post on the infrastructure domain, I cover the fifth and final
viewpoint that is important for an infrastructure domain representation, and
that is the &lt;em&gt;location view&lt;/em&gt;. As mentioned in previous posts, the viewpoints I
think are most representative of the infrastructure domain are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/process-view-of-infrastructure/"&gt;process view&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;service view&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/"&gt;component view&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/"&gt;zoning view&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like with the component view, the location view is a layered approach. While I
initially wanted to call it the network view, "location" might be a broader
term that matches the content better. Still, it's not a perfect name, but the
name is less important than the content, not?&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-09-07:/2021/09/location-view-of-infrastructure/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>location</category><category>network</category><category>virtualization</category><category>protocol</category></item><item><title>Process view of infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/process-view-of-infrastructure/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;,
I started with the five different views that would support a good view of
what infrastructure would be. I believe these views (component, location,
process, service, and zoning) cover the breadth of the domain. The post also
described the component view a bit more and linked to previous posts I made (one
for &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;services&lt;/a&gt;, another for
&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/"&gt;zoning&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one I want to tackle here is the most elaborate one, also the most
enterprise-ish, and one that always is a balance on how much time and
effort to put into it (as an architect), as well as hoping that the processes
are sufficiently standardized in a flexible manner so that you don't need
to cover everything again and again in each project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let's talk about processes...&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 11:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-09-01:/2021/09/process-view-of-infrastructure/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>process</category></item><item><title>Component view of infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;IT architects try to use views and viewpoints to convey the target architecture
to the various stakeholders. Each stakeholder has their own interests in the
architecture and wants to see their requirements fulfilled. A core
role of the architect is to understand these requirements and make sure the
requirements are met, and to balance all the different requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architecture languages or meta-models often put significant focus on these
views. Archimate has a large annex on &lt;a href="https://pubs.opengroup.org/architecture/archimate3-doc/apdxc.html#_Toc10045495"&gt;Example
Viewpoints&lt;/a&gt;
just for this purpose. However, unless the organization is widely accustomed to
enterprise architecture views, it is unlikely that the views themselves are the
final product: being able to translate those views into pretty slides and
presentations is still an important task for architects when they need to
present their findings to non-architecture roles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 21:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-08-27:/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>component</category><category>viewpoint</category></item><item><title>Disaster recovery in the public cloud</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/07/disaster-recovery-in-the-public-cloud/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The public cloud is a different beast than an on-premise environment, and that
also reflects itself on how we (should) look at the processes that are
actively steering infrastructure designs and architecture. One of these
is the business continuity, severe incident handling, and the
hopefully-never-to-occur disaster recovery. When building up procedures
for handling disasters (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disaster_recovery"&gt;DRP = Disaster Recovery Procedure or Disaster 
Recover Planning&lt;/a&gt;),
it is important to keep in mind what these are about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-07-30:/2021/07/disaster-recovery-in-the-public-cloud/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>DRP</category></item><item><title>What is the infrastructure domain?</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/07/what-is-the-infrastructure-domain/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In my job as domain architect for "infrastructure", I often come across
stakeholders that have no common understanding of what infrastructure means in
an enterprise architecture. Since then, I am trying to figure out a way to
easily explain it - to find a common, generic view on what infrastructure
entails. If successful, I could use this common view to provide context on the
many, many IT projects that are going around.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 15:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-07-19:/2021/07/what-is-the-infrastructure-domain/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>pattern</category></item><item><title>Organizing service documentation</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/07/organizing-service-documentation/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;An IT services overview&lt;/a&gt;
I try to keep track of the architecture and designs of the IT services and
solutions in a way that I feel helps me keep in touch with all the various
services and solutions out there. Similar to how system administrators try to
find a balance while working on documentation (which is often considered a
chore) and using a structure that is sufficiently simple and standard for the
organization to benefit from, architects should try to keep track of
architecturally relevant information as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this post, I'm going to explain a bit more on how I approach documenting
service and solution insights for architectural relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 09:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-07-08:/2021/07/organizing-service-documentation/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>documentation</category><category>structure</category><category>wiki</category></item><item><title>Not sure if TOSCA will grow further</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/not-sure-if-TOSCA-will-grow-further/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;TOSCA is an OASIS open standard, and is an abbreviation for &lt;em&gt;Topology and
Orchestration Specification for Cloud Applications&lt;/em&gt;. It provides a
domain-specific language to describe how an application should be deployed
in the cloud (the topology), which and how many resources it needs, as well
as tasks to run when certain events occur (the orchestration). When I
initially came across this standard, I was (and still am) interested
in how far this goes. The promise of declaring an application (and even
bundling the necessary application artefacts) within a single asset and
then using this asset to deploy on whatever cloud is very appealing to
an architect. Especially in organizations that have a multi-cloud
strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 14:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-30:/2021/06/not-sure-if-TOSCA-will-grow-further/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>TOSCA</category><category>OASIS</category><category>topology</category><category>orchestration</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>IaC</category><category>NFV</category></item><item><title>Integrating or customizing SaaS within your own cloud environment</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/integrating-or-customizing-SaaS-within-your-own-cloud-environment/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Software as a Service (SaaS) solutions are often a quick way to get new
capabilities into an organization’s portfolio. Smaller SaaS solutions are
simple, web-based solutions which barely integrate with the organization’s
other solutions, besides the identity and access management (which is often
handled by federated authentication).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More complex or intermediate solutions require more integration focus, and
a whole new market of Integration Platform as a Service (iPaaS) solutions
came up to facilitate cross-cloud integrations. But even without the iPaaS
offerings, integrations are often a mandatory part to leverage the benefits
of the newly activated SaaS solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to bring some thoughts on the integrations that might be
needed to support customizing a SaaS solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 15:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-23:/2021/06/integrating-or-customizing-SaaS-within-your-own-cloud-environment/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>SaaS</category><category>integration</category><category>customization</category></item><item><title>An IT services overview</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My current role within the company I work for is “domain architect”, part
of the enterprise architects teams. The domain I am accountable for is 
“infrastructure”, which can be seen as a very broad one. Now, I’ve been
maintaining an overview of our IT services before I reached that role, 
mainly from an elaborate interest in the subject, as well as to optimize
my efficiency further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming a domain architect allows me to use the insights I’ve since
gathered to try and give appropriate advice, but also now requires me to
maintain a domain architecture. This structure is going to be the starting
point of it, although it is not the true all and end all of what I would
consider a domain architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 17:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-14:/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>overview</category><category>service</category><category>landscape</category><category>catalog</category><category>capability</category></item><item><title>Virtualization vs abstraction</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/virtualization-vs-abstraction/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When an organization has an extensively large, and heterogeneous
infrastructure, infrastructure architects will attempt to make itless
complex and chaotic by introducing and maintaining a certain degree of
standardization. While many might consider standardization as a
rationalization (standardizing on a single database technology, single
vendor for hardware, etc.), rationalization is only one of the many ways
in which standards can simplify such a degree of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I'd like to point out two other, very common ways to
standardize the IT environment, without really considering a
rationalization: abstraction and virtualization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 10:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-03:/2021/06/virtualization-vs-abstraction/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>virtualization</category><category>abstraction</category></item><item><title>Abstracting infrastructure complexity</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;IT is complex. Some even consider it to be more magic than reality. And with
the ongoing evolutions and inventions, the complexity is not really going
away. Sure, some IT areas are becoming easier to understand, but that is often
offset with new areas being explored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies and organizations that have a sizeable IT footprint generally see an
increase in their infrastructure, regardless of how many rationalization
initiatives that are started. Personally, I find it challenging, in a fun
way, to keep up with the onslaught of new technologies and services that are
onboarded in the infrastructure landscape that I'm responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just understanding a technology isn't enough to deal with its position in
the larger environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2020 23:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2020-12-25:/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>archimate</category></item><item><title>Working on infra strategy</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2020/10/working-on-infra-strategy/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;After a long hiatus, I'm ready to take up blogging again on my public blog.
With my day job becoming more intensive and my side-job taking the remainder
of the time, I've since quit my work on the Gentoo project. I am in process
of releasing a new edition of the SELinux System Administration book, so I'll
probably discuss that more later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to write about a task I had to do this year as brand new domain
architect for infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 13:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2020-10-04:/2020/10/working-on-infra-strategy/</guid><category>Architecture</category></item><item><title>Project prioritization</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2017/07/project-prioritization/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;This is a long read, skip to “Prioritizing the projects and changes” for the
approach details...&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations and companies generally have an IT workload (dare I say,
backlog?) which needs to be properly assessed, prioritized and taken up.
Sometimes, the IT team(s) get an amount of budget and HR resources to "do their
thing", while others need to continuously ask for approval to launch a new
project or instantiate a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sizeable organizations even require engineering and development effort on IT
projects which are not readily available: specialized teams exist, but they are
governance-wise assigned to projects. And as everyone thinks their project is
the top-most priority one, many will be disappointed when they hear there are
no resources available for their pet project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So... how should organizations prioritize such projects?&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 20:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-07-18:/2017/07/project-prioritization/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>pmo</category><category>strategy</category><category>SAFe</category><category>prioritization</category><category>project</category></item><item><title>Structuring infrastructural deployments</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Many organizations struggle with the all-time increase in IP address
allocation and the accompanying need for segmentation. In the past, governing
the segments within the organization means keeping close control over the
service deployments, firewall rules, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the idea of micro-segmentation, supported through software-defined
networking solutions, seems to defy the need for a segmentation governance.
However, I think that that is a very short-sighted sales proposition. Even
with micro-segmentation, or even pure point-to-point / peer2peer communication
flow control, you'll still be needing a high level overview of the services
within your scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I'll give some insights in how we are approaching this in
the company I work for. In short, it starts with requirements gathering,
creating labels to assign to deployments, creating groups based on one or two
labels in a layered approach, and finally fixating the resulting schema and
start mapping guidance documents (policies) toward the presented architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 20:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-06-07:/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>segmentation</category><category>zoning</category><category>deployments</category><category>landscape</category></item><item><title>Switching focus at work</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, I was at work responsible for the infrastructure architecture of 
a couple of technological domains, namely databases and scheduling/workload 
automation. It brought me in contact with many vendors, many technologies
and most importantly, many teams within the organization. The focus domain
was challenging, as I had to deal with the strategy on how the organization,
which is a financial institution, will deal with databases and scheduling in
the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 13:29:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-09-20:/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>work</category><category>hadoop</category><category>docker</category></item><item><title>Making the case for multi-instance support</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2015/08/making-the-case-for-multi-instance-support/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;With the high attention that technologies such as &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://coreos.com/blog/rocket/"&gt;Rocket&lt;/a&gt; and the like get (I recommend to look at 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/p8952/bocker"&gt;Bocker&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Wilmott as well ;-), I
still find it important that technologies are well capable of supporting a
multi-instance environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to run multiple instances makes for great consolidation. The system
can be optimized for the technology, access to the system limited to the admins
of said technology while still providing isolation between instances. For some
technologies, running on commodity hardware just doesn't cut it (not all 
software is written for such hardware platforms) and consolidation allows for
reducing (hardware/licensing) costs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 12:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-08-22:/2015/08/making-the-case-for-multi-instance-support/</guid><category>Architecture</category></item></channel></rss>