<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - Architecture</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 10:10:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Virtualization vs abstraction</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/virtualization-vs-abstraction/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When an organization has an extensively large, and heterogeneous
infrastructure, infrastructure architects will attempt to make itless
complex and chaotic by introducing and maintaining a certain degree of
standardization. While many might consider standardization as a
rationalization (standardizing on a single database technology, single
vendor for hardware, etc.), rationalization is only one of the many ways
in which standards can simplify such a degree of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I'd like to point out two other, very common ways to
standardize the IT environment, without really considering a
rationalization: abstraction and virtualization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 10:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-03:/2021/06/virtualization-vs-abstraction/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>virtualization</category><category>abstraction</category></item><item><title>Abstracting infrastructure complexity</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;IT is complex. Some even consider it to be more magic than reality. And with
the ongoing evolutions and inventions, the complexity is not really going
away. Sure, some IT areas are becoming easier to understand, but that is often
offset with new areas being explored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies and organizations that have a sizeable IT footprint generally see an
increase in their infrastructure, regardless of how many rationalization
initiatives that are started. Personally, I find it challenging, in a fun
way, to keep up with the onslaught of new technologies and services that are
onboarded in the infrastructure landscape that I'm responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just understanding a technology isn't enough to deal with its position in
the larger environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2020 23:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2020-12-25:/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>archimate</category></item><item><title>Working on infra strategy</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2020/10/working-on-infra-strategy/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;After a long hiatus, I'm ready to take up blogging again on my public blog.
With my day job becoming more intensive and my side-job taking the remainder
of the time, I've since quit my work on the Gentoo project. I am in process
of releasing a new edition of the SELinux System Administration book, so I'll
probably discuss that more later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to write about a task I had to do this year as brand new domain
architect for infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 13:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2020-10-04:/2020/10/working-on-infra-strategy/</guid><category>Architecture</category></item><item><title>Project prioritization</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2017/07/project-prioritization/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;This is a long read, skip to “Prioritizing the projects and changes” for the
approach details...&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations and companies generally have an IT workload (dare I say,
backlog?) which needs to be properly assessed, prioritized and taken up.
Sometimes, the IT team(s) get an amount of budget and HR resources to "do their
thing", while others need to continuously ask for approval to launch a new
project or instantiate a change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sizeable organizations even require engineering and development effort on IT
projects which are not readily available: specialized teams exist, but they are
governance-wise assigned to projects. And as everyone thinks their project is
the top-most priority one, many will be disappointed when they hear there are
no resources available for their pet project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So... how should organizations prioritize such projects?&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2017 20:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-07-18:/2017/07/project-prioritization/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>pmo</category><category>strategy</category><category>SAFe</category><category>prioritization</category><category>project</category></item><item><title>Structuring infrastructural deployments</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Many organizations struggle with the all-time increase in IP address
allocation and the accompanying need for segmentation. In the past, governing
the segments within the organization means keeping close control over the
service deployments, firewall rules, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the idea of micro-segmentation, supported through software-defined
networking solutions, seems to defy the need for a segmentation governance.
However, I think that that is a very short-sighted sales proposition. Even
with micro-segmentation, or even pure point-to-point / peer2peer communication
flow control, you'll still be needing a high level overview of the services
within your scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I'll give some insights in how we are approaching this in
the company I work for. In short, it starts with requirements gathering,
creating labels to assign to deployments, creating groups based on one or two
labels in a layered approach, and finally fixating the resulting schema and
start mapping guidance documents (policies) toward the presented architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 20:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-06-07:/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>segmentation</category><category>zoning</category><category>deployments</category><category>landscape</category></item><item><title>Switching focus at work</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, I was at work responsible for the infrastructure architecture of 
a couple of technological domains, namely databases and scheduling/workload 
automation. It brought me in contact with many vendors, many technologies
and most importantly, many teams within the organization. The focus domain
was challenging, as I had to deal with the strategy on how the organization,
which is a financial institution, will deal with databases and scheduling in
the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 13:29:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-09-20:/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>work</category><category>hadoop</category><category>docker</category></item><item><title>Making the case for multi-instance support</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2015/08/making-the-case-for-multi-instance-support/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;With the high attention that technologies such as &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://coreos.com/blog/rocket/"&gt;Rocket&lt;/a&gt; and the like get (I recommend to look at 
&lt;a href="https://github.com/p8952/bocker"&gt;Bocker&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Wilmott as well ;-), I
still find it important that technologies are well capable of supporting a
multi-instance environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to run multiple instances makes for great consolidation. The system
can be optimized for the technology, access to the system limited to the admins
of said technology while still providing isolation between instances. For some
technologies, running on commodity hardware just doesn't cut it (not all 
software is written for such hardware platforms) and consolidation allows for
reducing (hardware/licensing) costs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2015 12:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-08-22:/2015/08/making-the-case-for-multi-instance-support/</guid><category>Architecture</category></item></channel></rss>