<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - architecture</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 22:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Diagrams are no communication channel</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2024/09/diagrams-are-no-communication-channel/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;IT architects generally use architecture-specific languages or modeling
techniques to document their thoughts and designs. &lt;a href="https://www.opengroup.org/archimate-forum/archimate-overview"&gt;ArchiMate&lt;/a&gt;,
the framework I have the most experience with, is a specialized enterprise
architecture modeling language. It is maintained by The Open Group, an organization
known for its broad architecture framework titled TOGAF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My stance, however, is that architects should not use the diagrams from their
architecture modeling framework to convey their message to every stakeholder
out there...&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 22:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2024-09-05:/2024/09/diagrams-are-no-communication-channel/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category></item><item><title>Location view of infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/location-view-of-infrastructure/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In this last post on the infrastructure domain, I cover the fifth and final
viewpoint that is important for an infrastructure domain representation, and
that is the &lt;em&gt;location view&lt;/em&gt;. As mentioned in previous posts, the viewpoints I
think are most representative of the infrastructure domain are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/process-view-of-infrastructure/"&gt;process view&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;service view&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/"&gt;component view&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/"&gt;zoning view&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;location view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like with the component view, the location view is a layered approach. While I
initially wanted to call it the network view, "location" might be a broader
term that matches the content better. Still, it's not a perfect name, but the
name is less important than the content, not?&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 18:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-09-07:/2021/09/location-view-of-infrastructure/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>location</category><category>network</category><category>virtualization</category><category>protocol</category></item><item><title>Process view of infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/09/process-view-of-infrastructure/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;,
I started with the five different views that would support a good view of
what infrastructure would be. I believe these views (component, location,
process, service, and zoning) cover the breadth of the domain. The post also
described the component view a bit more and linked to previous posts I made (one
for &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;services&lt;/a&gt;, another for
&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/"&gt;zoning&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one I want to tackle here is the most elaborate one, also the most
enterprise-ish, and one that always is a balance on how much time and
effort to put into it (as an architect), as well as hoping that the processes
are sufficiently standardized in a flexible manner so that you don't need
to cover everything again and again in each project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let's talk about processes...&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 11:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-09-01:/2021/09/process-view-of-infrastructure/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>process</category></item><item><title>Component view of infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;IT architects try to use views and viewpoints to convey the target architecture
to the various stakeholders. Each stakeholder has their own interests in the
architecture and wants to see their requirements fulfilled. A core
role of the architect is to understand these requirements and make sure the
requirements are met, and to balance all the different requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architecture languages or meta-models often put significant focus on these
views. Archimate has a large annex on &lt;a href="https://pubs.opengroup.org/architecture/archimate3-doc/apdxc.html#_Toc10045495"&gt;Example
Viewpoints&lt;/a&gt;
just for this purpose. However, unless the organization is widely accustomed to
enterprise architecture views, it is unlikely that the views themselves are the
final product: being able to translate those views into pretty slides and
presentations is still an important task for architects when they need to
present their findings to non-architecture roles.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 21:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-08-27:/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>component</category><category>viewpoint</category></item><item><title>Disaster recovery in the public cloud</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/07/disaster-recovery-in-the-public-cloud/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The public cloud is a different beast than an on-premise environment, and that
also reflects itself on how we (should) look at the processes that are
actively steering infrastructure designs and architecture. One of these
is the business continuity, severe incident handling, and the
hopefully-never-to-occur disaster recovery. When building up procedures
for handling disasters (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Disaster_recovery"&gt;DRP = Disaster Recovery Procedure or Disaster 
Recover Planning&lt;/a&gt;),
it is important to keep in mind what these are about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-07-30:/2021/07/disaster-recovery-in-the-public-cloud/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>DRP</category></item><item><title>What is the infrastructure domain?</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/07/what-is-the-infrastructure-domain/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In my job as domain architect for "infrastructure", I often come across
stakeholders that have no common understanding of what infrastructure means in
an enterprise architecture. Since then, I am trying to figure out a way to
easily explain it - to find a common, generic view on what infrastructure
entails. If successful, I could use this common view to provide context on the
many, many IT projects that are going around.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jul 2021 15:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-07-19:/2021/07/what-is-the-infrastructure-domain/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>pattern</category></item><item><title>Organizing service documentation</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/07/organizing-service-documentation/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;An IT services overview&lt;/a&gt;
I try to keep track of the architecture and designs of the IT services and
solutions in a way that I feel helps me keep in touch with all the various
services and solutions out there. Similar to how system administrators try to
find a balance while working on documentation (which is often considered a
chore) and using a structure that is sufficiently simple and standard for the
organization to benefit from, architects should try to keep track of
architecturally relevant information as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in this post, I'm going to explain a bit more on how I approach documenting
service and solution insights for architectural relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2021 09:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-07-08:/2021/07/organizing-service-documentation/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>documentation</category><category>structure</category><category>wiki</category></item><item><title>Not sure if TOSCA will grow further</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/not-sure-if-TOSCA-will-grow-further/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;TOSCA is an OASIS open standard, and is an abbreviation for &lt;em&gt;Topology and
Orchestration Specification for Cloud Applications&lt;/em&gt;. It provides a
domain-specific language to describe how an application should be deployed
in the cloud (the topology), which and how many resources it needs, as well
as tasks to run when certain events occur (the orchestration). When I
initially came across this standard, I was (and still am) interested
in how far this goes. The promise of declaring an application (and even
bundling the necessary application artefacts) within a single asset and
then using this asset to deploy on whatever cloud is very appealing to
an architect. Especially in organizations that have a multi-cloud
strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 14:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-30:/2021/06/not-sure-if-TOSCA-will-grow-further/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>TOSCA</category><category>OASIS</category><category>topology</category><category>orchestration</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>IaC</category><category>NFV</category></item><item><title>Integrating or customizing SaaS within your own cloud environment</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/integrating-or-customizing-SaaS-within-your-own-cloud-environment/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Software as a Service (SaaS) solutions are often a quick way to get new
capabilities into an organization’s portfolio. Smaller SaaS solutions are
simple, web-based solutions which barely integrate with the organization’s
other solutions, besides the identity and access management (which is often
handled by federated authentication).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More complex or intermediate solutions require more integration focus, and
a whole new market of Integration Platform as a Service (iPaaS) solutions
came up to facilitate cross-cloud integrations. But even without the iPaaS
offerings, integrations are often a mandatory part to leverage the benefits
of the newly activated SaaS solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I want to bring some thoughts on the integrations that might be
needed to support customizing a SaaS solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 15:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-23:/2021/06/integrating-or-customizing-SaaS-within-your-own-cloud-environment/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>SaaS</category><category>integration</category><category>customization</category></item><item><title>An IT services overview</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My current role within the company I work for is “domain architect”, part
of the enterprise architects teams. The domain I am accountable for is 
“infrastructure”, which can be seen as a very broad one. Now, I’ve been
maintaining an overview of our IT services before I reached that role, 
mainly from an elaborate interest in the subject, as well as to optimize
my efficiency further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming a domain architect allows me to use the insights I’ve since
gathered to try and give appropriate advice, but also now requires me to
maintain a domain architecture. This structure is going to be the starting
point of it, although it is not the true all and end all of what I would
consider a domain architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 17:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-14:/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>overview</category><category>service</category><category>landscape</category><category>catalog</category><category>capability</category></item><item><title>Virtualization vs abstraction</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/virtualization-vs-abstraction/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;When an organization has an extensively large, and heterogeneous
infrastructure, infrastructure architects will attempt to make itless
complex and chaotic by introducing and maintaining a certain degree of
standardization. While many might consider standardization as a
rationalization (standardizing on a single database technology, single
vendor for hardware, etc.), rationalization is only one of the many ways
in which standards can simplify such a degree of complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I'd like to point out two other, very common ways to
standardize the IT environment, without really considering a
rationalization: abstraction and virtualization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 10:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-03:/2021/06/virtualization-vs-abstraction/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>virtualization</category><category>abstraction</category></item></channel></rss>