<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - infrastructure</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 13:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Containers are the new IaaS</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2022/05/containers-are-the-new-iaas/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;At work, as with many other companies, we're actively investing in new
platforms, including container platforms and public cloud. We use Kubernetes
based container platforms both on-premise and in the cloud, but are also very
adamant that the container platforms should only be used for application
workload that is correctly designed for cloud-native deployments: we do not
want to see vendors packaging full operating systems in a container and
then shouting they are now container-ready.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 13:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2022-05-21:/2022/05/containers-are-the-new-iaas/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>kubernetes</category><category>container</category><category>iaas</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>virtual-machine</category></item><item><title>Not sure if TOSCA will grow further</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/not-sure-if-TOSCA-will-grow-further/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;TOSCA is an OASIS open standard, and is an abbreviation for &lt;em&gt;Topology and
Orchestration Specification for Cloud Applications&lt;/em&gt;. It provides a
domain-specific language to describe how an application should be deployed
in the cloud (the topology), which and how many resources it needs, as well
as tasks to run when certain events occur (the orchestration). When I
initially came across this standard, I was (and still am) interested
in how far this goes. The promise of declaring an application (and even
bundling the necessary application artefacts) within a single asset and
then using this asset to deploy on whatever cloud is very appealing to
an architect. Especially in organizations that have a multi-cloud
strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 14:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-30:/2021/06/not-sure-if-TOSCA-will-grow-further/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>cloud</category><category>TOSCA</category><category>OASIS</category><category>topology</category><category>orchestration</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>IaC</category><category>NFV</category></item><item><title>Abstracting infrastructure complexity</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;IT is complex. Some even consider it to be more magic than reality. And with
the ongoing evolutions and inventions, the complexity is not really going
away. Sure, some IT areas are becoming easier to understand, but that is often
offset with new areas being explored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Companies and organizations that have a sizeable IT footprint generally see an
increase in their infrastructure, regardless of how many rationalization
initiatives that are started. Personally, I find it challenging, in a fun
way, to keep up with the onslaught of new technologies and services that are
onboarded in the infrastructure landscape that I'm responsible for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just understanding a technology isn't enough to deal with its position in
the larger environment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2020 23:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2020-12-25:/2020/12/abstracting-infrastructure-complexity/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>infrastructure</category><category>archimate</category></item></channel></rss>