<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - ima</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/ima/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-05-14T03:50:00+02:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Highlevel assessment of Cdorked and Gentoo Hardened/SELinux</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/05/highlevel-assessment-of-cdorked-and-gentoo-hardenedselinux/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-14T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-05-14T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-05-14:/2013/05/highlevel-assessment-of-cdorked-and-gentoo-hardenedselinux/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With all the
&lt;a href="http://www.welivesecurity.com/2013/05/07/linuxcdorked-malware-lighttpd-and-nginx-web-servers-also-affected/"&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt;
surrounding
&lt;a href="https://threatpost.com/attack-using-backdoored-apache-binaries-to-lead-to-blackhole-kit/"&gt;Cdorked&lt;/a&gt;,
I took a look at if SELinux and/or other Gentoo Hardened technologies
could reduce the likelihood that this infection occurs on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, we don't know yet how the malware gets installed on the
server. We do know that the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With all the
&lt;a href="http://www.welivesecurity.com/2013/05/07/linuxcdorked-malware-lighttpd-and-nginx-web-servers-also-affected/"&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt;
surrounding
&lt;a href="https://threatpost.com/attack-using-backdoored-apache-binaries-to-lead-to-blackhole-kit/"&gt;Cdorked&lt;/a&gt;,
I took a look at if SELinux and/or other Gentoo Hardened technologies
could reduce the likelihood that this infection occurs on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, we don't know yet how the malware gets installed on the
server. We do know that the Apache binaries themselves are modified, so
the first thing to look at is to see if this risk can be reduced. Of
course, using an intrusion detection system like
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/AIDE"&gt;AIDE&lt;/a&gt; helps, but even with Gentoo's
&lt;strong&gt;qcheck&lt;/strong&gt; command you can test the integrity of the files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;# qcheck www-servers/apache
Checking www-servers/apache-2.2.24 ...
  * 424 out of 424 files are good
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the binary is modified, this would result in something equivalent to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;Checking www-servers/apache-2.2.24 ...
 MD5-DIGEST: /usr/sbin/apache2
  * 423 out of 424 files are good
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don't know if the modified binary would otherwise work just fine, I
have not been able to find exact details on the infected binary to (in a
sandbox environment of course) analyze this further. Also, because we
don't know how they are installed, it is not easy to know if binaries
that you built yourself are equally likely to be modified/substituted or
if the attack checks checksums of the binaries against a known list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that it would run, then the infecting malware would need to set
the proper SELinux context on the file (if it overwrites the existing
binary, then the context is retained, otherwise it gets the default
context of &lt;code&gt;bin_t&lt;/code&gt;). If the context is wrong, then starting Apache
results in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;apache2: Syntax error on line 61 of /etc/apache2/httpd.conf: Cannot load /usr/lib64/apache2/modules/mod_actions.so into server: /usr/lib64/apache2/modules/mod_actions.so: cannot open shared object file: Permission denied
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because the modified binary stays in the calling domain context
(&lt;code&gt;initrc_t&lt;/code&gt;). If you use a targeted policy, then this will not present
itself as &lt;code&gt;initrc_t&lt;/code&gt; is an unconfined domain. But with strict policies,
&lt;code&gt;initrc_t&lt;/code&gt; is not allowed to read &lt;code&gt;httpd_modules_t&lt;/code&gt;. Even worse, the
remainder of SELinux protections don't apply anymore, since with
unconfined domains, all bets are off. That is why Gentoo focuses this
hard on using a strict policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what if the binary runs in the proper domain? Well then, from the
articles I read, the malware can do a reverse connect. That means that
the domain will attempt to connect to an IP address provided by the
attacker (in a specifically crafted URL). For SELinux, this means that
the &lt;em&gt;name_connect&lt;/em&gt; permission is checked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;# sesearch -s httpd_t -c tcp_socket -p name_connect -ACTS
Found 20 semantic av rules:
   allow nsswitch_domain dns_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; 
DT allow httpd_t port_type : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_connect ]
DT allow httpd_t ftp_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_relay ]
DT allow httpd_t smtp_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_sendmail ]
DT allow httpd_t postgresql_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_connect_db ]
DT allow httpd_t oracledb_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_connect_db ]
DT allow httpd_t squid_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_relay ]
DT allow httpd_t mssql_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_connect_db ]
DT allow httpd_t kerberos_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ allow_kerberos ]
DT allow nsswitch_domain ldap_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ authlogin_nsswitch_use_ldap ]
DT allow httpd_t http_cache_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_relay ]
DT allow httpd_t http_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_relay ]
DT allow httpd_t http_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_graceful_shutdown ]
DT allow httpd_t mysqld_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_connect_db ]
DT allow httpd_t ocsp_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ allow_kerberos ]
DT allow nsswitch_domain kerberos_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ allow_kerberos ]
DT allow httpd_t pop_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_sendmail ]
DT allow nsswitch_domain ocsp_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ allow_kerberos ]
DT allow httpd_t gds_db_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_connect_db ]
DT allow httpd_t gopher_port_t : tcp_socket { name_connect } ; [ httpd_can_network_relay ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So by default, the Apache (&lt;code&gt;httpd_t&lt;/code&gt;) domain is allowed to connect to
DNS port (to resolve hostnames). All other &lt;em&gt;name_connect&lt;/em&gt; calls depend
on SELinux booleans (mentioned after it) that are by default disabled
(at least on Gentoo). Disabling hostname resolving is not really
feasible, so if the attacker uses a DNS port as port that the malware
needs to connect to, SELinux will not deny it (unless you use additional
networking constraints).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the reverse connect is an interesting feature of the malware, but
not the main one. The main focus of the malware is to redirect customers
to particular sites that can trick the user in downloading additional
(client) malware. Because this is done internally within Apache, SELinux
cannot deal with this. As a user, make sure you configure your browser
not to trust non-local iframes and such (always do this, not just
because there is a possible threat right now). The configuration of
Cdorked is a shared memory segment of Apache itself. Of course, since
Apache uses shared memory, the malware embedded within will also have
access to the shared memory. However, if this shared memory would need
to be accessed by third party applications (the malware seems to grant
read/write rights on everybody to this segment) SELinux will prevent
this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;# sesearch -t httpd_t -c shm -ACTS
Found 2 semantic av rules:
   allow unconfined_domain_type domain : shm { create destroy getattr setattr read write associate unix_read unix_write lock } ; 
   allow httpd_t httpd_t : shm { create destroy getattr setattr read write associate unix_read unix_write lock } ;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only unconfined domains and the &lt;code&gt;httpd_t&lt;/code&gt; domain itself have access to
&lt;code&gt;httpd_t&lt;/code&gt; labeled shared memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what about IMA/EVM? Well, those will not help here since IMA checks
for integrity of files that were modified &lt;em&gt;offline&lt;/em&gt;. As the modification
of the Apache binaries is most likely done online, IMA would just accept
this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, it seems that a good system integrity approach is the most
effective until we know more about how the malware-infected binary is
written to the system in the first place (as this is better protected by
MAC controls like SELinux).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Security"></category><category term="apache"></category><category term="cdorked"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="ima"></category><category term="selinux"></category></entry><entry><title>Uploading selinuxnode test VM</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/02/uploading-selinuxnode-test-vm/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-02-25T03:05:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-02-25T03:05:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-02-25:/2013/02/uploading-selinuxnode-test-vm/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing (but I'll delay the publication of this post a
few hours), I'm uploading a new SELinux-enabled KVM guest image. This is
not an update on the previous image though (it's a reinstalled system -
after all, I use VMs for testing, so it makes sense to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing (but I'll delay the publication of this post a
few hours), I'm uploading a new SELinux-enabled KVM guest image. This is
not an update on the previous image though (it's a reinstalled system -
after all, I use VMs for testing, so it makes sense to reinstall from
time to time to check if the installation instructions are still
accurate). However, the focus remains the same:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A minimal Gentoo Linux installation for amd64 (x86_64) as guest
    within a KVM hypervisor. The image is about 190 Mb in size
    compressed, and 1.6 Gb in size uncompressed. The file format is
    Qemu's QCOW2 so expect the image to grow as you work with it. The
    file systems are, in total, sized to about 50 Gb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The installation has SELinux enabled (strict policy, enforcing
    mode), various grSecurity settings enabled (including PaX and TPE),
    but now also includes IMA (Integrity Measurement Architecture) and
    EVM (Extended Verification Module) although EVM is by default
    started in fix mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The image will not start any network-facing daemons by default
    (unlike the previous image) for security reasons (if I let this
    image stay around this long as I did with the previous, it's prone
    to have some vulnerabilities in the future, although I'm hoping I
    can update the image more frequently). This includes SSH, so you'll
    need access to the image console first after which you can configure
    the network and start SSH (&lt;strong&gt;run_init rc-service sshd start&lt;/strong&gt; does
    the trick).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A couple of default accounts are created, and the image will display
    those accounts and their passwords on the screen (it is a test/play
    VM, not a production VM).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still a few minor issues with it, that I hope to fix by the
next upload:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=457812"&gt;Bug 457812&lt;/a&gt; is
    still applicable to the image, so you'll notice lots of SELinux
    denials on the mknod capability. They seem to be cosmetic though.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At shutdown, udev somewhere fails with a SELinux initial
    context problem. I thought I had it covered, but I noticed after
    compressing the image that it is still there. I'll fix it - I
    promise ;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EVM is enabled in fix mode, because otherwise EVM is &lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_name=1361476641.29360.114.camel%40falcor1&amp;amp;forum_name=linux-ima-user"&gt;prohibiting
    mode
    changes&lt;/a&gt;
    on files in /run. I still have to investigate this further though -
    I had to use the EVM=fix workaround due to time pressure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When uploaded, I'll ask the Gentoo infrastructure team to synchronise
the image with our mirrors so you can enjoy it. It'll be on the
distfiles, under experimental/amd64/qemu-selinux (it has the 20130224
date in the name, so you can see for yourself if the sync has already
occurred or not).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="evm"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="grsecurity"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="ima"></category><category term="kvm"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="virtual"></category></entry><entry><title>Working on a new selinuxnode VM</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/02/working-on-a-new-selinuxnode-vm/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-02-23T14:04:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-02-23T14:04:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-02-23:/2013/02/working-on-a-new-selinuxnode-vm/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, I made a &lt;a href="http://distfiles.gentoo.org/experimental/amd64/qemu-selinux/"&gt;SELinux enabled
VM&lt;/a&gt; for
people to play with, displaying a minimal Gentoo installation, including
the hardening features it supports (PIE/PIC toolchain, grSecurity, PaX
and SELinux). I'm currently trying to create a new one, which also
includes IMA/EVM, but it looks like …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, I made a &lt;a href="http://distfiles.gentoo.org/experimental/amd64/qemu-selinux/"&gt;SELinux enabled
VM&lt;/a&gt; for
people to play with, displaying a minimal Gentoo installation, including
the hardening features it supports (PIE/PIC toolchain, grSecurity, PaX
and SELinux). I'm currently trying to create a new one, which also
includes IMA/EVM, but it looks like I still have many things to
investigate further...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I notice that many SELinux domains want to use the mknod
capability, even for domains of which I have no idea whatsoever why they
need it. I don't notice any downsides though, and running in permissive
mode doesn't change the domain behavior. But still, I'm reluctant to
mark them dontaudit as long as I'm not 100% sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the gettys (I think it is the getty) result in a "Cannot change
SELinux context: permission denied" error, even though everything is
running in the right SELinux context. I still have to confirm if it
really is the getty process or something else (the last run I had the
impression it was a udev-related process). But there are no denials and
no SELinux errors in the logs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, during shutdown, many domains have problems accessing their PID
files in /var/run (which is a link to /run). I most likely need to allow
read privileges on all domains that have access to var_run_t towards
the var_t symlinks. It isn't a problem per se (the processes still run
correctly) but ugly as hell, and if you introduce monitoring it'll go
haywire (as no PID files were either found, or were stale).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, EVM is giving me a hard time, not allowing me to change mode and
ownership in files on /var/run. I have received some feedback from the
IMA user list on this so it is still very much a work-in-progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the first attempt to generate a new VM resulted in a download
of 817 MB (instead of the 158 MB of the previous release), so I still
have to correct my USE flags and doublecheck the installed applications.
Anyway, definitely to be continued. Too bad time is a scarce resource
:-(&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="evm"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="ima"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="selinuxnode"></category><category term="vm"></category></entry></feed>