<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - asset-management</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 10:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><item><title>An IT conceptual data model</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2022/01/an-it-conceptual-data-model/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This time a much shorter post, as I've been asked to share this information
recently and found that it, by itself, is already useful enough to publish. It
is a conceptual data model for IT services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The IT model, and why it is useful&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A conceptual data model for IT services supports several IT processes, with a
strong focus on &lt;em&gt;asset management&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;configuration management&lt;/em&gt;. Many IT
vendors that have solutions active within those processes will have their own
data model in place, but I often feel that their models have room for
improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these models are too fine-grained, others are limited to server
infrastructure. And while most applications allow for further customization, I
feel that an IT architect should have a conceptual model in mind for their
actions and projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conceptual data model that I'm currently working on looks as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="An IT CDM, first version" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202201/it-cdm-v1.png"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My intention is to update this CDM with new insights when I capture those. It is
not my intention to further develop the data model into a physical data model,
but perhaps in the long term I could make it a conceptual one (explaining what
the attributes are of each concept).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback? Comments? Don't hesitate to &lt;a href="mailto:sven.vermeulen@siphos.be"&gt;drop me an
email&lt;/a&gt;, or join the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/infrainsight/status/1483002656478093315"&gt;discussion on
Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2022-01-17:/2022/01/an-it-conceptual-data-model/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>cdm</category><category>asset-management</category><category>configuration-management</category></item></channel></rss>