<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - work</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/work/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2015-09-20T13:29:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Switching focus at work</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-09-20T13:29:00+02:00</published><updated>2015-09-20T13:29:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-09-20:/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, I was at work responsible for the infrastructure architecture of 
a couple of technological domains, namely databases and scheduling/workload 
automation. It brought me in contact with many vendors, many technologies
and most importantly, many teams within the organization. The focus domain
was challenging, as I had to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, I was at work responsible for the infrastructure architecture of 
a couple of technological domains, namely databases and scheduling/workload 
automation. It brought me in contact with many vendors, many technologies
and most importantly, many teams within the organization. The focus domain
was challenging, as I had to deal with the strategy on how the organization,
which is a financial institution, will deal with databases and scheduling in
the long term.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This means looking at the investments related to those domains, implementation
details, standards of use, features that we will or will not use, positioning
of products and so forth. To do this from an architecture point of view means
that I not only had to focus on the details of the technology and understand 
all their use, but also become a sort-of subject matter expert on those topics.
Luckily, I had (well, still have) great teams of DBAs (for the databases) and
batch teams (for the scheduling/workload automation) to keep things in the right
direction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I helped them with a (hopefully sufficiently) clear roadmap, investment track,
procurement, contract/terms and conditions for use, architectural decisions and
positioning and what not. And they helped me with understanding the various
components, learn about the best use of these, and of course implement the 
improvements that we collaboratively put on the roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Times, they are changing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I flipped over a page at work. Although I remain an IT architect
within the same architecture team, my focus shifts entirely. Instead of a fixed
domain, my focus is now more volatile. I leave behind the stability of 
organizationally anchored technology domains and go forward in a more tense
environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of looking at just two technology domains, I need to look at all of them,
and find the right balance between high flexibility demands (which might not want
to use current "standard" offerings) which come up from a very agile context, and
the almost non-negotionable requirements that are typical for financial institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus is also not primarily technology oriented anymore. I'll be part of an 
enterprise architecture team with direct business involvement and although my
main focus will be on the technology side, it'll also involve information
management, business processes and applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end goal is to set up a future-proof architecture in an agile, fast-moving
environment (contradictio in terminis ?) which has a main focus in data analytics
and information gathering/management. Yes, "big data", but more applied than what
some of the vendors try to sell us ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm currently finishing off the high-level design and use of a Hadoop platform,
and the next focus will be on a possible micro-service architecture using Docker.
I've been working on this Hadoop design for a while now (but then it was together
with my previous function at work) and given the evolving nature of Hadoop (and
the various services that surround it) I'm confident that it will not be the last
time I'm looking at it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let me hope I can keep things manageable ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category><category term="work"></category><category term="hadoop"></category><category term="docker"></category></entry></feed>