<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - Documentation</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/feeds/documentation.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2015-01-03T10:09:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Gentoo Wiki is growing</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2015/01/gentoo-wiki-is-growing/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-01-03T10:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2015-01-03T10:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-01-03:/2015/01/gentoo-wiki-is-growing/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is because of the winter holidays, but the last weeks I've
noticed a lot of updates and edits on the Gentoo wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Website/Tyrian"&gt;Tyrian&lt;/a&gt; layout,
whose purpose is to eventually become the unified layout for all Gentoo
resources, happened first. Then, three common templates (&lt;code&gt;Code …&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it is because of the winter holidays, but the last weeks I've
noticed a lot of updates and edits on the Gentoo wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Website/Tyrian"&gt;Tyrian&lt;/a&gt; layout,
whose purpose is to eventually become the unified layout for all Gentoo
resources, happened first. Then, three common templates (&lt;code&gt;Code&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;File&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;Kernel&lt;/code&gt;) where deprecated in favor of their "*Box" counterparts
(&lt;code&gt;CodeBox&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;FileBox&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;KernelBox&lt;/code&gt;). These provide better parameter
support (which should make future updates on the templates easier to
implement) as well as syntax highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the wiki also saw a number of contributions being added. I added a
short article on &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Efibootmgr"&gt;Efibootmgr&lt;/a&gt;
as the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Handbook:Main_Page"&gt;Gentoo
handbook&lt;/a&gt; now also uses
it for its EFI related instructions, but other users added quite a few
additional articles as well. As they come along, articles are being
marked by editors for translation. For me, that's a trigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever a wiki article is marked for translations, it shows up on the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Special:PageTranslation"&gt;PageTranslation&lt;/a&gt;
list. When I have time, I pick one of these articles and try to update
it to move to a common style (the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Gentoo_Wiki:Guidelines"&gt;Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; page
is the "official" one, and I have a
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User:SwifT/Styleguide"&gt;Styleguide&lt;/a&gt; in
which I elaborate a bit more on the use). Having a common style gives a
better look and feel to the articles (as they are then more alike),
gives a common documentation development approach (so everyone can join
in and update documentation in a similar layout/structure) and - most
importantly - reduces the number of edits that do little more than
switch from one formatting to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an article has been edited, I mark it for translation, and then the
real workhorse on the wiki starts. We have several active translators on
the Gentoo wiki, who we cannot thank hard enough for their work (I used
to start at Gentoo as a translator, I have some feeling about their
work). They make the Gentoo documentation reachable for a broader
audience. Thanks to the use of the translation extension (kindly offered
by the Gentoo wiki admins, who have been working quite hard the last few
weeks on improving the wiki infrastructure) translations are easier to
handle and follow through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of a translation-marked article is that any change on the
article also shows up on the list again, allowing me to look at the
change and perform edits when necessary. For the end user, this is
behind the scenes - an update on an article shows up immediately, which
is fine. But for me (and perhaps other editors as well) this gives a
nice overview of changes to articles (watchlists can only go so far) and
also shows the changes in a simple yet efficient manner. Thanks to this
approach, we can more actively follow up on edits and improve where
necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, editing is not always just a few minutes of work. Consider the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/GRUB2"&gt;GRUB2&lt;/a&gt; article on the wiki. It was
marked for translation, but had some issues with its style. It was very
verbose (which is not a bad thing, but suggests to split information
towards multiple articles) and quite a few open discussions on its
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Talk:GRUB2"&gt;Discussions&lt;/a&gt; page. I started
editing the article around 13.12h local time, and ended at 19.40h.
Unlike with offline documentation, the entire process of the editing can
be followed through the page'
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/index.php?title=GRUB2&amp;amp;offset=&amp;amp;limit=100&amp;amp;action=history"&gt;history&lt;/a&gt;).
And although I'm still not 100% satisfied with the result, it is imo
easier to follow through and read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, don't get me wrong - I do not feel that the article was wrong
in any way. Although I would appreciate articles that immediately follow
a style, I rather see more contributions (which we can then edit towards
the new style) than that we would start penalizing contributors that
don't use the style. That would work contra-productive, because it is
far easier to update the style of an article than to write articles. We
should try and get more contributors to document aspects of their Gentoo
journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, please keep them coming. If you find a lack of (good) information
for something, start jotting down what you know in an article. We'll
gladly help you out with editing and improving the article then, but the
content is something you are probably best to write down.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>Added UEFI instructions to AMD64/x86 handbooks</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/12/added-uefi-instructions-to-amd64x86-handbooks/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-23T18:08:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-12-23T18:08:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-12-23:/2014/12/added-uefi-instructions-to-amd64x86-handbooks/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just finished up adding some UEFI instructions to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Handbook:Main_Page"&gt;Gentoo
handbooks&lt;/a&gt; for AMD64
and x86 (I don't know how many systems are still using x86 instead of
the AMD64 one, and if those support UEFI, but the instructions are
shared and they don't collide). The entire EFI stuff can …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just finished up adding some UEFI instructions to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Handbook:Main_Page"&gt;Gentoo
handbooks&lt;/a&gt; for AMD64
and x86 (I don't know how many systems are still using x86 instead of
the AMD64 one, and if those support UEFI, but the instructions are
shared and they don't collide). The entire EFI stuff can probably be
improved a lot, but basically the things that were added are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boot the system using UEFI already if possible (which is needed for
    efibootmgr to access the EFI variables). This is not entirely
    mandatory (as efibootmgr is not mandatory to boot a system)
    but recommended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use vfat for the &lt;code&gt;/boot/&lt;/code&gt; location, as this now becomes the EFI
    System Partition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;configure the Linux kernel to support EFI stub and EFI variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;install the Linux kernel as the &lt;code&gt;bootx64.efi&lt;/code&gt; file to boot the
    system with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use efibootmgr to add boot options (if required) and create an EFI
    boot entry called "Gentoo"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find grave errors, please do mention them (either on a talk page
on the wiki, as a &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org"&gt;bug&lt;/a&gt; or through IRC) so it
is picked up. All developers and trusted contributors on the wiki have
access to the files so can edit where needed (but do take care that, if
something is edited, that it is either architecture-specific or shared
across all architectures - check the page when editing; if it is
&lt;em&gt;Handbook:Parts&lt;/em&gt; then it is shared, and &lt;em&gt;Handbook:AMD64&lt;/em&gt; is specific for
the architecture). And if I'm online I'll of course act on it quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and no - it is not a bug that there is a (now not used) &lt;code&gt;/dev/sda1&lt;/code&gt;
"bios" partition. Due to the differences with the possible installation
alternatives, it is easier for us (me) to just document a common
partition layout than to try and write everything out (making it just
harder for new users to follow the instructions).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="efi"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="handbook"></category><category term="uefi"></category></entry><entry><title>Handbooks moved</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/12/handbooks-moved/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-14T14:42:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-12-14T14:42:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-12-14:/2014/12/handbooks-moved/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday the move of the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Handbook:Main_Page"&gt;Gentoo
Wiki&lt;/a&gt; for the Gentoo
handbooks (whose most important part are the installation instructions
for the various supported architectures) has been concluded, with a
last-minute addition being the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Handbook:Main_Page#Viewing_the_handbook"&gt;one-page
views&lt;/a&gt;
so that users who want to can view the installation instructions
completely within one view …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday the move of the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Handbook:Main_Page"&gt;Gentoo
Wiki&lt;/a&gt; for the Gentoo
handbooks (whose most important part are the installation instructions
for the various supported architectures) has been concluded, with a
last-minute addition being the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Handbook:Main_Page#Viewing_the_handbook"&gt;one-page
views&lt;/a&gt;
so that users who want to can view the installation instructions
completely within one view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we use lots of
&lt;a href="http://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Transclusion"&gt;transclusions&lt;/a&gt; (i.e.
including different wiki articles inside another article) to support a
common documentation base for the various architectures, I did hit a
limit that prevented me from creating a single-page for the entire
handbook (i.e. "Installing Gentoo Linux", "Working with Gentoo",
"Working with portage" and "Network configuration" together), but I
could settle with one page per part. I think that matches most of the
use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the move now done, it is time to start tackling the various bugs
that were reported against the handbook, as well as initiate
improvements where needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did make a (probably more - but this one is fresh in my memory)
mistake in the move though. I had to do a lot of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;``` {lang="xml"}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...
```&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without this, transcluded parts would suddenly show the translation tags
as regular text. Only afterwards (I'm talking about more than &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Documentation/HandbookDevelopment"&gt;400
different
pages&lt;/a&gt;)
did I read that I should transclude the &lt;code&gt;/en&lt;/code&gt; pages (like
&lt;code&gt;Handbook:Parts/Installation/About/en&lt;/code&gt; instead of
&lt;code&gt;Handbook:Parts/Installation/About&lt;/code&gt;) as those do not have the
translation specifics in them. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="handbook"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>Updated Linux Sea, now with viewport thingie</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/updated-linux-sea-now-with-viewport-thingie/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-16T23:37:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-16T23:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-16:/2013/12/updated-linux-sea-now-with-viewport-thingie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just pushed out an update to &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; (an online resource to introduce
you to Linux, using Gentoo Linux as an example), including its PDF and
ePub versions. The changes are pretty small (see its
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sjvermeu/Linux-Sea/blob/master/ChangeLog"&gt;ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with the update, it now also includes a
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;meta name="viewport"...&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; so …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just pushed out an update to &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; (an online resource to introduce
you to Linux, using Gentoo Linux as an example), including its PDF and
ePub versions. The changes are pretty small (see its
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sjvermeu/Linux-Sea/blob/master/ChangeLog"&gt;ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with the update, it now also includes a
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;meta name="viewport"...&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; so that the document renders better on a
mobile device. Not perfect, but at least it's not small text anymore
where you need to pinch-zoom and then scroll left/right all over the
place. Same with my blog btw.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="css"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="linux sea"></category><category term="mobile"></category></entry><entry><title>Majority of GDP documents moved to Gentoo wiki</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/majority-of-gdp-documents-moved-to-gentoo-wiki/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-10T16:03:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-10T16:03:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-10:/2013/12/majority-of-gdp-documents-moved-to-gentoo-wiki/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The majority of the English gentoo documents that resided in
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en"&gt;www.gentoo.org/doc/en&lt;/a&gt; have now been
moved to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. All those documents
have been made available in the main namespace, meaning that
non-developers can continue to contribute on those articles and guides,
fully in the spirit …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The majority of the English gentoo documents that resided in
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en"&gt;www.gentoo.org/doc/en&lt;/a&gt; have now been
moved to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. All those documents
have been made available in the main namespace, meaning that
non-developers can continue to contribute on those articles and guides,
fully in the spirit of a wiki and community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are now working on &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Documentation/Overview"&gt;a method for displaying an overview of
documents&lt;/a&gt;
that have been moved, or have seen enough development on the wiki that
they are deemed of proper quality and stable (not too many changes
left). Currently, such documents are (requested to be) marked for
translation, allowing me or other developers to review if the guides are
indeed ok to move forward. If so, they are marked as translatable
(allowing the various translation members on the wiki to move forward
with translating the guides) and will be made part of the overview as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the few documents that has not been moved yet is the Gentoo
Handbook as it is of a different format than the guides, and includes
dynamic documentation generation features which I have yet to fully
investigate (wiki-wise). I currently focused mainly on the non-handbook
guides, so the handbook itself will get more attention later (after the
documentation overview is completed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big thanks to &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User:A3li"&gt;Alex Legler&lt;/a&gt; for
assisting me and providing the necessary features and functionality in
the Gentoo wiki to make this all possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit:&lt;/em&gt; added link to overview page.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="documents"></category><category term="gdp"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>Moving Gentoo docs to the wiki</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/07/moving-gentoo-docs-to-the-wiki/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-07-28T11:22:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-07-28T11:22:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-07-28:/2013/07/moving-gentoo-docs-to-the-wiki/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slowly but surely Gentoo documentation guides are being moved to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to the translation
support provided by the infrastructure, all "reasons" not to go forward
with this have been resolved. At first, I'm focusing on documentation
with open bugs that have not been picked up (usually due …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slowly but surely Gentoo documentation guides are being moved to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to the translation
support provided by the infrastructure, all "reasons" not to go forward
with this have been resolved. At first, I'm focusing on documentation
with open bugs that have not been picked up (usually due to (human)
resource limits), but other documents will follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of already moved documents are the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Xorg/Configuration"&gt;Xorg configuration
guide&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/GCC_optimization"&gt;GCC
optimization guide&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/UTF-8"&gt;UTF-8&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/User-mode_Linux/System_testing_with_UML"&gt;System testing with
UML&lt;/a&gt;.
Many more have been moved as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The migrations are assisted by a conversion script that translates
GuideXML into wiki style content, although manual corrections remain
needed. For instance, all &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;pre caption="..."&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; stuff is changed into
&lt;code&gt;{{Code|...}}&lt;/code&gt; even though the Wiki has several templates for code, such
as &lt;code&gt;{{Kernel|...}}&lt;/code&gt; for kernel configurations, &lt;code&gt;{{RootCmd|...}}&lt;/code&gt; for
commands ran as a privileged user and &lt;code&gt;{{Cmd|...}}&lt;/code&gt; for unprivileged
user commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I updated the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/list.xml"&gt;documentation
list&lt;/a&gt; on the main Gentoo site to
reflect the movement of documents as well, as this list will be slowly
shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="docs"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="gdp"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="wiki"></category></entry><entry><title>My application base: draw.io</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/06/my-application-base-draw-io/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-03T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-06-03T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-06-03:/2013/06/my-application-base-draw-io/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The next few weeks (months even) will be challenging my free time as I'm
working on (too many) projects simultaneously (sadly, only a few of
those are free software related, most are house renovations). But that
shouldn't stop me from starting a new set of posts, being &lt;em&gt;my
application base …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The next few weeks (months even) will be challenging my free time as I'm
working on (too many) projects simultaneously (sadly, only a few of
those are free software related, most are house renovations). But that
shouldn't stop me from starting a new set of posts, being &lt;em&gt;my
application base&lt;/em&gt;. In this series, I'll cover a few applications (or
websites) that I either use often or that I should use more. In either
case, the application does its job very well so why not give some input
on it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first on the agenda is the &lt;a href="http://www.draw.io"&gt;Draw.io&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Draw.io, you get a web-browser based drawing application for
diagrams, flowcharts, UML, BPMN etc. I came across this application
while looking for an alternative to &lt;a href="https://live.gnome.org/Dia"&gt;Dia&lt;/a&gt;,
which by itself was supposed to be an alternative to &lt;a href="https://office.microsoft.com/en-us/visio/"&gt;Microsoft
Visio&lt;/a&gt; (err, no). Don't get
me wrong, Dia is nice, but it lacks evolution and just doesn't feel
easy. Draw.io on the other hand is evolving constantly, and it is also
active on &lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/100634082864796769666/"&gt;Google Plus&lt;/a&gt;
where you can follow up on all recent developments and thoughts (I hope
I get the G+ link correctly, it's not that I don't like numbers, just
not in URLs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started using Draw.io while documenting free software IT architectures
(such as implementations of BIND, PostgreSQL, etc.) for which I needed
some diagrams. Although Draw.io is an online application (and its
underlying engine is not completely free software) you can easily work
with it from different locations. It integrates with &lt;a href="https://drive.google.com"&gt;Google
Drive&lt;/a&gt; to store the diagrams on if you want -
and if you don't, you can always save the diagrams in their native XML
format on your system and open them later again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interface is very easy to use, and I recently found out that it now
also supports mobile devices, which is perfect for tablets (the mobile
device support is recent afaik and still undergoing updates). The site
also works well in various browsers (tried IExplorer 10 at work, Firefox
and Google Chrome and they all seem to work nicely) - eat that stupid
commercial vendors that force me into using IExplorer 8 or Firefox 10 -
you know who you are!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A site/service to keep a close eye on. The service itself is free (and
doesn't seem too limited due to it), but Draw.io also has commercial
support if you want through Google Apps and Confluence integration. I
don't have much experience with those yet but that might change in the
near future (projects, projects).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="appbase"></category><category term="architecturing"></category><category term="dia"></category><category term="draw"></category><category term="draw.io"></category><category term="mab"></category><category term="visio"></category></entry><entry><title>A simple IPv6 setup</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/05/a-simple-ipv6-setup/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-20T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-05-20T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-05-20:/2013/05/a-simple-ipv6-setup/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;For internal communication between guests on my workstation, I use IPv6
which is set up using the &lt;em&gt;Router Advertisement&lt;/em&gt; "feature" of IPv6. The
tools I use are &lt;a href="http://www.thekelleys.org.uk/dnsmasq/doc.html"&gt;dnsmasq&lt;/a&gt;
for DNS/DHCP and router advertisement support, and
&lt;a href="http://roy.marples.name/projects/dhcpcd"&gt;dhcpcd&lt;/a&gt; as client. It might be
a total mess (grew almost organically until it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For internal communication between guests on my workstation, I use IPv6
which is set up using the &lt;em&gt;Router Advertisement&lt;/em&gt; "feature" of IPv6. The
tools I use are &lt;a href="http://www.thekelleys.org.uk/dnsmasq/doc.html"&gt;dnsmasq&lt;/a&gt;
for DNS/DHCP and router advertisement support, and
&lt;a href="http://roy.marples.name/projects/dhcpcd"&gt;dhcpcd&lt;/a&gt; as client. It might be
a total mess (grew almost organically until it worked), but as far as
I'm concerned, it is working... and that is all that matters (for now).
I'll have to look deeper into the IPv6 stuff to understand it all better
though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the client side, &lt;strong&gt;dhcpcd&lt;/strong&gt; is ran with the following options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;dhcpcd_eth0=&amp;quot;-t 5 -L --ipv6ra_own&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had to enable &lt;code&gt;--ipv6ra_own&lt;/code&gt; to get it to obtain its global address,
otherwise it only got its link local one (&lt;code&gt;fe80::&lt;/code&gt; something). I also
added a hook into &lt;code&gt;/lib/dhcpcd/dhcpcd-hooks&lt;/code&gt; to get it to trigger a
hostname update for IPv6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cat 28-set-ip6-address 
if $ifup; then export new_ip_address=${ra1_prefix%%/64}; fi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;SELinux-policy wise, I had to enable &lt;code&gt;dhcpc_t&lt;/code&gt; to write to the hostname
proc file and set the system hostname. The first one (21) is needed
because of the &lt;code&gt;--ipv6ra_own&lt;/code&gt; parameter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;# selocal -l | grep dhcpc_t
21: allow dhcpc_t self:rawip_socket create_socket_perms; # dhcpclient
22: kernel_rw_kernel_sysctl(dhcpc_t) # set hostname
23: allow dhcpc_t self:capability sys_admin; # set hostname
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, in &lt;code&gt;/etc/dhcpcd.conf&lt;/code&gt;, I removed the &lt;em&gt;nohook lookup-hostname&lt;/em&gt;
and set the &lt;em&gt;force_hostname&lt;/em&gt; one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;#nohook lookup-hostname
env force_hostname=YES
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On the server side, I use the following configuration of dnsmasq
(snippet):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;dhcp-range=2001:db8:81:e2::,ra-only
enable-ra
dhcp-option=option6:dns-server,[2001:db8:81:e2::26b5:365b:5072]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I use the documentation prefix for now (since it is
meant for internal communication only, and makes it easier to copy/paste
into documentation ;-) but when I am going to use full IPv6 access to
the Internet, this prefix will of course change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I enabled IPv6 forwarding on the &lt;code&gt;tap0&lt;/code&gt; interface because
otherwise I continuously got the following messages on the clients:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;May 12 18:43:07 test dhcpcd[3869]: eth0: adding default route via fe80::d848:19ff:fe0d:55c2
May 12 18:43:07 test dhcpcd[3869]: eth0: fe80::d848:19ff:fe0d:55c2 is no longer a router
May 12 18:43:07 test dhcpcd[3869]: eth0: deleting default route via fe80::d848:19ff:fe0d:55c2
May 12 18:43:13 test dhcpcd[3869]: eth0: fe80::d848:19ff:fe0d:55c2 is unreachable, expiring it
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To enable IPv6 forwarding, you can use sysctl but I added it in the
script that sets up the tap0 interface:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;tunctl -b -u swift -t tap0
ifconfig tap0 add 2001:db8:81:e2::26b5:365b:5072/64
vde_switch --numports 16 --mod 777 --group users --tap tap0 -d
echo 1 &amp;gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv6/conf/tap0/forwarding
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="dhcpcd"></category><category term="dnsmasq"></category><category term="ip6"></category><category term="ipv6"></category><category term="ra"></category></entry><entry><title>Added "predictable network interface" info into the handbook</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/05/added-predictable-network-interface-info-into-the-handbook/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-07T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-05-07T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-05-07:/2013/05/added-predictable-network-interface-info-into-the-handbook/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being long overdue - like many of our documentation-reported bugs :-( I
worked on &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=466262"&gt;bug 466262&lt;/a&gt;
to update the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/"&gt;Gentoo Handbook&lt;/a&gt;
with information about &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=4&amp;amp;chap=2#doc_chap4"&gt;Network Interface
Naming&lt;/a&gt;.
Of course, the installation instructions have also seen the necessary
updates to refer to this change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some luck (read: time) I might be able …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Being long overdue - like many of our documentation-reported bugs :-( I
worked on &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=466262"&gt;bug 466262&lt;/a&gt;
to update the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/"&gt;Gentoo Handbook&lt;/a&gt;
with information about &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=4&amp;amp;chap=2#doc_chap4"&gt;Network Interface
Naming&lt;/a&gt;.
Of course, the installation instructions have also seen the necessary
updates to refer to this change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With some luck (read: time) I might be able to fix various other
documentation-related ones soon. I had some problems with the new
SELinux userspace that I wanted to get fixed before, and then I worked
on the new SELinux policies as well as trying to figure out how SELinux
deals with network related aspects. Hence I saw time fly by at the speed
of a neutrino...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTW, the 20130424 policies are in the tree.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="documentation"></category><category term="gdp"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="udev"></category></entry><entry><title>Simple drawing for I/O positioning</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/04/simple-drawing-for-io-positionin/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-18T01:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-04-18T01:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-04-18:/2013/04/simple-drawing-for-io-positionin/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Instead of repeatedly trying to create an overview of the various layers
involved with I/O operations within Linux on whatever white-board is in
the vicinity, I decided to draw one up in &lt;a href="http://www.draw.io"&gt;Draw.io&lt;/a&gt;
that I can then update as I learn more from this fascinating world. The
drawing's …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Instead of repeatedly trying to create an overview of the various layers
involved with I/O operations within Linux on whatever white-board is in
the vicinity, I decided to draw one up in &lt;a href="http://www.draw.io"&gt;Draw.io&lt;/a&gt;
that I can then update as I learn more from this fascinating world. The
drawing's smaller blocks within the layers are meant to give some
guidance to what is handled where, so they are definitely not complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for those interested (or those that know more of it than I ever will
and prepared to help me out):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/io-layers.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="io-layers" src="http://blog.siphos.be/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/io-layers-231x300.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope it isn't too far from the truth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="io"></category><category term="linux"></category></entry><entry><title>Integrity checking with AIDE</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/04/integrity-checking-with-aide/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-11T17:02:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-04-11T17:02:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-04-11:/2013/04/integrity-checking-with-aide/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As to at least do some progress in the integrity part of Gentoo Hardened
(a subproject I'd like to extend towards greater heights), I dediced to
write up a &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/AIDE"&gt;small guide&lt;/a&gt; on how to
work with &lt;a href="http://aide.sourceforge.net"&gt;AIDE&lt;/a&gt;. The tool is simple enough
(and it allowed me to test its SELinux …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As to at least do some progress in the integrity part of Gentoo Hardened
(a subproject I'd like to extend towards greater heights), I dediced to
write up a &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/AIDE"&gt;small guide&lt;/a&gt; on how to
work with &lt;a href="http://aide.sourceforge.net"&gt;AIDE&lt;/a&gt;. The tool is simple enough
(and it allowed me to test its SELinux policy module a bit) so you'll
get by fairly quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, what I'd like to know a bit more about is on how to use AIDE on
a hypervisor level, scanning through the file systems of the guests,
without needing in-guest daemons. I wrote a small part in the guide, but
I need to test it more thoroughly. In the end, I'd like to have a
configuration that AIDE is running on the host, mounting the guest file
systems, scanning the necessary files and sending out reports, all one
at a time (snapshot, mount, scan+report, unmount, destroy snapshot,
next).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone has pointers towards such a setup, it'd be greatly
appreciated. It provides, in my opinion, a secure way of scanning
systems even if they are completely compromised (in other words you
couldn't trust anything running inside the guest or running with the
libraries or software within the guest).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="aide"></category><category term="integrity"></category></entry><entry><title>Linux Sea and ePub update</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/04/linux-sea-and-epub-update/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-02T20:16:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-04-02T20:16:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-04-02:/2013/04/linux-sea-and-epub-update/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just "published" a small update on the &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; online book. Nothing major, some
path updates (like the move to /etc/portage for the make.conf file). But
I wouldn't put a blog post online if there wasn't anything else to say
;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I was made aware that the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just "published" a small update on the &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; online book. Nothing major, some
path updates (like the move to /etc/portage for the make.conf file). But
I wouldn't put a blog post online if there wasn't anything else to say
;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I was made aware that the ePub versions I publish were broken.
I don't use ePub readers myself, so all I do is read the ePubs through a
Firefox plug-in and it's been a while that I did that on my own ePubs.
Apparently, the stylesheets I used to convert the Docbook to ePub
changes behavior (or my scripts abused an error in the previous
stylesheets that are fixed now). So right now the
&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/linux_sea.epub"&gt;ePub&lt;/a&gt; version should
work again, and the code snippet below is what I use now to build it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;xsltproc --stringparam base.dir linuxsea-epub/OEBPS/ /usr/share/sgml/docbook/xsl-stylesheets/epub3/chunk.xsl LINUXSEA.xml;
cp -r /path/to/src/linux_sea/images linuxsea-epub/OEBPS;
cd linuxsea-epub;
zip -X0 linux_sea.epub mimetype;
zip -r -X9 linux_sea.epub META-INF OEBPS;
mv linux_sea.epub ../;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="epub"></category><category term="linux sea"></category><category term="linux_sea"></category></entry><entry><title>git patch apply</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2012/09/git-patch-apply/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-09-27T20:45:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-09-27T20:45:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2012-09-27:/2012/09/git-patch-apply/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had to merge the changes made to an upstream project with a
local repository. I took out the changes as patches through
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git format-patch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (as the local repository isn't a clone of the
remote one so I couldn't just create a branch and merge) and hoped to
apply …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently had to merge the changes made to an upstream project with a
local repository. I took out the changes as patches through
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git format-patch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (as the local repository isn't a clone of the
remote one so I couldn't just create a branch and merge) and hoped to
apply them with &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git am&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Sadly, trying this resulted in an error
equivalent with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;error: test.txt: does not match index&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Git suggested to fix the index, and then continue with
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git am --resolved&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. But what the ... does it mean with fixing the
index? Basically, it means that the change needs to be recorded by git
in order to be applied, but why does the patch fail to recognize this?
The &lt;code&gt;test.txt&lt;/code&gt; file exists and is known by git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some searching, I found a way to handle this - it might not be
pretty, but it did the trick, and I succesfully merged about 200 commits
in an hour or so. You can see this post as a "backup" for my memory ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I tried to apply the patch using
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git am 0001-some-stuff.patch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. If it succeeds, continue. If it
doesn't, apply the patch manually using
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;patch &amp;lt; 0001-some-stuff.patch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Then make sure that the changed
files (see &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;) are taking part of the commit (use
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git add&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;). When the changes are made and recorded, run
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git am --resolved&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Or if you want to discard it, make sure no
changes are made/recorded and run &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git am --skip&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it. Some scripting made this a whole lot easier. Check the return
code of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git am&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. If it is zero, continue with the next patch. If it
isn't, run patch and again check for the return code. If it is zero,
remove all &lt;code&gt;*.orig&lt;/code&gt; files (or change the patch command so it doesn't
write orig files), add all (changed) files to the git index and run
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;git am --resolved&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. And if the patch fails, have the user fix
things manually and continue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Linux Sea now in ePub</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2012/04/linux-sea-now-in-epub/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-04-20T17:31:00+02:00</published><updated>2012-04-20T17:31:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2012-04-20:/2012/04/linux-sea-now-in-epub/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On request of Matthew Marchese, I now automatically build an &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/linux_sea.epub"&gt;ePub
version&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; for those that like to read such
resources on a digital reader. Thanks to the use of DocBook, this was
simply a matter of using its xsl-stylesheets/epub/docbook.xsl stylesheet
against the DocBook sources …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On request of Matthew Marchese, I now automatically build an &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/linux_sea.epub"&gt;ePub
version&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; for those that like to read such
resources on a digital reader. Thanks to the use of DocBook, this was
simply a matter of using its xsl-stylesheets/epub/docbook.xsl stylesheet
against the DocBook sources and zip the created directory structures
(OEBPS and META-INF) to get to the ePub file.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>File System Labels in Linux Sea</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2011/02/file-system-labels-in-linux-sea/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-02-12T20:42:00+01:00</published><updated>2011-02-12T20:42:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2011-02-12:/2011/02/file-system-labels-in-linux-sea/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have added some information on file system labels in &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/linux_sea.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;). If you don't
know what labels are (or UUIDs), here is a quick summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most, if not all file systems, assign a universally unique identifier
(UUID) which looks like a random hexadecimal string to each file system …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have added some information on file system labels in &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt;
(&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/linux_sea.pdf"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;). If you don't
know what labels are (or UUIDs), here is a quick summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most, if not all file systems, assign a universally unique identifier
(UUID) which looks like a random hexadecimal string to each file system.
On a Gentoo system, you can get an overview of all UUIDs detected using
a simple &lt;strong&gt;ls -l /dev/disk/by-uuid&lt;/strong&gt;, courtesy of the gentoo udev rules.
Users can also assign a specific label to a file system, either when
they create it (like &lt;strong&gt;mkfs.ext4 -L ROOT /dev/sda2&lt;/strong&gt;) or afterwards
(&lt;strong&gt;e2label /dev/sda2 ROOT&lt;/strong&gt;). This is also not limited to the content
file systems - you can also assign a label to a swap file system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This information can then be used to uniquely identify the file system,
even if you don't know what the device file (/dev/sda2) is called. A
huge advantage is for those devices that often change device file
(removable media, but also SATA or SCSI disks on systems where the admin
loves adding and removing disks ;-) as you can keep your fstab
configuration static: the fstab file doesn't need to be changed, even
when the device files themselves change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple fstab line (&lt;code&gt;/dev/sda2  /  ext4  defaults,noatime  0 0&lt;/code&gt;) can
then easily be transformed to use the LABEL="..." syntax (like
&lt;code&gt;LABEL=ROOT /  ext4  defaults,noatime  0 0&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people might also think they can use this mechanism for their
kernel boot parameter (like using &lt;code&gt;root=LABEL=ROOT&lt;/code&gt; instead of
&lt;code&gt;root=/dev/sda2&lt;/code&gt;). Sadly, the Linux kernel doesn't offer this
functionality. It is possible, but only when you use an initramfs (which
I don't).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Linux Sea last content chapter</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2010/09/linux-sea-last-content-chapter/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-04T22:42:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-09-04T22:42:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2010-09-04:/2010/09/linux-sea-last-content-chapter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last chapter in &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux Sea&lt;/a&gt;
focuses on &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/ch19.html"&gt;Using A Shell&lt;/a&gt;.
This seems to me like a nice last chapter, as it confronts the user with
the exciting world of shell scripts. I hope that the chapters in the
book are sufficiently stuffed so that beginners (who are not afraid …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The last chapter in &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux Sea&lt;/a&gt;
focuses on &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/ch19.html"&gt;Using A Shell&lt;/a&gt;.
This seems to me like a nice last chapter, as it confronts the user with
the exciting world of shell scripts. I hope that the chapters in the
book are sufficiently stuffed so that beginners (who are not afraid to
learn) can more easily start off with (Gentoo) Linux. Of course, this is
just the beginning. The existing content needs to be sharpened, extended
where needed, updated, etc. so expect a few updates coming along!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Linux Sea: log file management and backups</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2010/09/linux-sea-log-file-management-and-backups/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-02T14:31:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-09-02T14:31:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2010-09-02:/2010/09/linux-sea-log-file-management-and-backups/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've added two more chapters to the &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; book. The first one is about &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/ch17.html"&gt;Log
file management&lt;/a&gt;, the second
one about &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/ch18.html"&gt;Taking Backups&lt;/a&gt;.
They're far from finished, but I thought that those two topics are
important for day-to-day Gentoo usage and shouldn't be left out of the
Linux Sea …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've added two more chapters to the &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; book. The first one is about &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/ch17.html"&gt;Log
file management&lt;/a&gt;, the second
one about &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/ch18.html"&gt;Taking Backups&lt;/a&gt;.
They're far from finished, but I thought that those two topics are
important for day-to-day Gentoo usage and shouldn't be left out of the
Linux Sea saga.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Added "iw" support to Linux Sea</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2010/08/added-iw-support-to-linux-sea/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-26T01:42:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-08-26T01:42:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2010-08-26:/2010/08/added-iw-support-to-linux-sea/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The wireless driver developers are actively working on a &lt;a href="http://wireless.kernel.org/en/users/Documentation/iw"&gt;new wireless
toolset called
"iw"&lt;/a&gt;, slowly
deprecating the older wireless-tools toolset (which contains the
"iwconfig" command). Kasumi_Ninja reported to me in the &lt;a href="https://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-p-6310061.html#6310061"&gt;Gentoo
Forums&lt;/a&gt; that
it would be nice to add information on iw to &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt;, so I did. I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The wireless driver developers are actively working on a &lt;a href="http://wireless.kernel.org/en/users/Documentation/iw"&gt;new wireless
toolset called
"iw"&lt;/a&gt;, slowly
deprecating the older wireless-tools toolset (which contains the
"iwconfig" command). Kasumi_Ninja reported to me in the &lt;a href="https://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-p-6310061.html#6310061"&gt;Gentoo
Forums&lt;/a&gt; that
it would be nice to add information on iw to &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt;, so I did. I must admit though
that my systems don't (or hardly) support iw, so I had to be lead by
examples throughout the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from the iw addition, I've reorganized the sections on &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/ch09.html"&gt;Software
Management&lt;/a&gt; as it was
becoming too crowded. I've also started a
&lt;a href="http://github.com/sjvermeu/Linux-Sea/raw/master/ChangeLog"&gt;ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt;
for those who want to track the changes to the document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if anyone can recommend me a good spell- and grammar checker...&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>I remain impressed by the free software community</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2010/08/i-remain-impressed-by-the-free-software-community/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-25T00:42:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-08-25T00:42:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2010-08-25:/2010/08/i-remain-impressed-by-the-free-software-community/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My current personal projects, &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://cvechecker.sourceforge.net"&gt;cvechecker&lt;/a&gt;, are actively being
watched by the free software community. For the Linux Sea book, I get
nice feedback and ideas on the &lt;a href="https://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-812252.html"&gt;Gentoo
Forums&lt;/a&gt; and on the
cvechecker application, people such as Nigel Horne are helping out in
various ways - including &lt;a href="http://cvechecker.sourceforge.net/docs/featurerequests.html"&gt;feature …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My current personal projects, &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://cvechecker.sourceforge.net"&gt;cvechecker&lt;/a&gt;, are actively being
watched by the free software community. For the Linux Sea book, I get
nice feedback and ideas on the &lt;a href="https://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-812252.html"&gt;Gentoo
Forums&lt;/a&gt; and on the
cvechecker application, people such as Nigel Horne are helping out in
various ways - including &lt;a href="http://cvechecker.sourceforge.net/docs/featurerequests.html"&gt;feature
requests&lt;/a&gt;
of all sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must admit, I remain impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Small changes have already been squeezed in in the Linux Sea document. A
larger change (the use of the &lt;a href="http://wireless.kernel.org/en/users/Documentation/iw"&gt;iw
tools&lt;/a&gt; for
wireless connectivity) is being investigated (sadly, &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2010/08/new-laptop-time-to-play/"&gt;my broadcom-sta
device&lt;/a&gt; doesn't
support the new nl80211 API so the documentation change is slower to
integrate than expected). I'm also planning to make some updates on the
software management chapter as it is currently becoming quite crowded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the cvetool, most
&lt;a href="http://cvechecker.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/cvechecker/ChangeLog?view=markup"&gt;changes&lt;/a&gt;
are bugfixes and output enhancements as expected. I'm not going to add
more functionality now - I first want to get a stable 1.0 release out
there. But first continue to squash bugs and add rules to the
versions.dat file so that it is usable on various systems (release 0.4
is around the corner).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Question yourself v3</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2010/05/question-yourself-v3/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-05-19T22:11:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-05-19T22:11:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2010-05-19:/2010/05/question-yourself-v3/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another update to &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/tools-quizzer.html"&gt;Quizzer&lt;/a&gt;,
now at version 3. But more importantly, updates to the &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; related chapters are made
available online - get a taste for it at the &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/tools/quizzer/quizzer.html?category=linuxsea"&gt;online quizzer
set&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback is, as always, very much appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Question yourself v2</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2010/05/question-yourself-v2/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-05-11T20:59:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-05-11T20:59:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2010-05-11:/2010/05/question-yourself-v2/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of the
&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/tools-quizzer.html"&gt;Quizzer&lt;/a&gt; webscript is
available. The &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/tools/quizzer/quizzer.html"&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt;
has also been updated with quick tests on the first few chapters of
Linux Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More exercises on the following chapters will follow soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updates to the script include visual accept/reject of single-choice and
multiple choice answers and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A new version of the
&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/tools-quizzer.html"&gt;Quizzer&lt;/a&gt; webscript is
available. The &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/tools/quizzer/quizzer.html"&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt;
has also been updated with quick tests on the first few chapters of
Linux Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More exercises on the following chapters will follow soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updates to the script include visual accept/reject of single-choice and
multiple choice answers and improved support for Internet Explorer
(which I don't have at home to validate).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Question yourself</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2010/05/question-yourself/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-05-02T23:58:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-05-02T23:58:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2010-05-02:/2010/05/question-yourself/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you ever write down things in the hope you never forget them, but
still think it would be better if you could somehow take a test of that
subject from time to time to make sure you don't forget?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do, and I found it quite difficult to keep …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Do you ever write down things in the hope you never forget them, but
still think it would be better if you could somehow take a test of that
subject from time to time to make sure you don't forget?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do, and I found it quite difficult to keep the knowledge live without
having to reread the things every now and then. For that purpose, I
started writing a simple JavaScript/XML/XSL fileset that allowed me to
present questions (randomly if necessary) from a structured set of
questions. In the beginning, it was too simple to share (string
matching) but quickly grew to something more elaborate: regular
expression support, multiple string-answer support, in-paragraph answer
boxes and single/multiple choice answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this fileset in place, I can keep track of things I would most
likely otherwise forget: just select the category which I want to take a
test from, and start with a (lot of) random question(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've decided to put this fileset
&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/tools-quizzer.html"&gt;online&lt;/a&gt; (including
&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/tools/quizzer/quizzer.html"&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt; files) and
will extend the demo file with questions regarding my book, &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt;, allowing readers of the book to
take online tests after they've finished a chapter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>A dozen pages added</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2010/04/a-dozen-pages-added/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-04-22T00:53:00+02:00</published><updated>2010-04-22T00:53:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2010-04-22:/2010/04/a-dozen-pages-added/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just a quick heads-up that a dozen pages in the &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; book have been added. Nothing
spectacular, just a few more paragraphs on services/runlevels, a few
updates on software management and on boot failure resolutions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Translations to "Linux Sea"</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2009/12/translations-to-linux-sea/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-12-02T17:38:00+01:00</published><updated>2009-12-02T17:38:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2009-12-02:/2009/12/translations-to-linux-sea/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few people have contacted me if they were allowed to translate the
online book I'm writing (&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux Sea&lt;/a&gt;).
Of course they are, the license allows it. However, I recommend to wait
a bit. At this moment, I'm not going to release the docbook sources (I'm
not writing it in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few people have contacted me if they were allowed to translate the
online book I'm writing (&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux Sea&lt;/a&gt;).
Of course they are, the license allows it. However, I recommend to wait
a bit. At this moment, I'm not going to release the docbook sources (I'm
not writing it in DocBook, but I'm generating from another XML into
DocBook) until I'm happy with the final result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm glad to see that the document is well received. There is still lots
of work on it (more excercises, a thorough spelling / grammar check,
elaborate on certain topics, ...) so stay tuned for further updates. Why
are those updates "slow"? Well, let's say that I use a "fair share
scheduling" principle on all my hobbies ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Small updates on Linux Sea</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2009/10/small-updates-on-linux-sea/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-10-19T21:36:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-10-19T21:36:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2009-10-19:/2009/10/small-updates-on-linux-sea/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few updates have made it to the &lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea" title="Linux Sea (HTML)"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt; book:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information regarding ndiswrapper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some information about udev and the symlinks that it creates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The
&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea/linux_sea.pdf" title="Linux Sea (PDF)"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;
version has been updated as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry><entry><title>Darwin Information Typing Architecture</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2009/04/darwin-information-typing-architecture/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-04-18T09:59:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-04-18T09:59:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2009-04-18:/2009/04/darwin-information-typing-architecture/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having documented a lot in LaTeX (back in the old days at the
university), &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml"&gt;GuideXML&lt;/a&gt;
(Gentoo's document markup language) and DocBook (&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt;) I'm now pointing my arrows at
DITA, the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin_Information_Typing_Architecture"&gt;Darwin Information Typing
Architecture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DITA "forces" the technical writer in separating the content of his
document in specialized subjects …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having documented a lot in LaTeX (back in the old days at the
university), &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml"&gt;GuideXML&lt;/a&gt;
(Gentoo's document markup language) and DocBook (&lt;a href="http://swift.siphos.be/linux_sea"&gt;Linux
Sea&lt;/a&gt;) I'm now pointing my arrows at
DITA, the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin_Information_Typing_Architecture"&gt;Darwin Information Typing
Architecture&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DITA "forces" the technical writer in separating the content of his
document in specialized subjects: reference, task or concept, or a
specialized version of any of those which you can create/define
yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By separating content in those three subjects, you can more easily
manage your technical documentation (write concepts as individual
topics, tasks as end-user procedures and references for affiliated
topics or command information).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all these documents are written, you bind them together using a
DITA map (a metadocument which holds references to all related
concepts/tasks/references) et voila: your documentation is ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, not really, you need to build it to something end users can read -
you can use &lt;a href="http://dita-ot.sourceforge.net/"&gt;dita-ot&lt;/a&gt; for that. It
supports building for Eclipse Infocenter, RTF, XHTML and PDF out of the
box.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category></entry></feed>