<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - landscape</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 17:30:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>An IT services overview</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My current role within the company I work for is “domain architect”, part
of the enterprise architects teams. The domain I am accountable for is 
“infrastructure”, which can be seen as a very broad one. Now, I’ve been
maintaining an overview of our IT services before I reached that role, 
mainly from an elaborate interest in the subject, as well as to optimize
my efficiency further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becoming a domain architect allows me to use the insights I’ve since
gathered to try and give appropriate advice, but also now requires me to
maintain a domain architecture. This structure is going to be the starting
point of it, although it is not the true all and end all of what I would
consider a domain architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 17:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-06-14:/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>architecture</category><category>overview</category><category>service</category><category>landscape</category><category>catalog</category><category>capability</category></item><item><title>Structuring infrastructural deployments</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Many organizations struggle with the all-time increase in IP address
allocation and the accompanying need for segmentation. In the past, governing
the segments within the organization means keeping close control over the
service deployments, firewall rules, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the idea of micro-segmentation, supported through software-defined
networking solutions, seems to defy the need for a segmentation governance.
However, I think that that is a very short-sighted sales proposition. Even
with micro-segmentation, or even pure point-to-point / peer2peer communication
flow control, you'll still be needing a high level overview of the services
within your scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I'll give some insights in how we are approaching this in
the company I work for. In short, it starts with requirements gathering,
creating labels to assign to deployments, creating groups based on one or two
labels in a layered approach, and finally fixating the resulting schema and
start mapping guidance documents (policies) toward the presented architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jun 2017 20:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2017-06-07:/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>segmentation</category><category>zoning</category><category>deployments</category><category>landscape</category></item></channel></rss>