<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - gqview</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/gqview/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-06-05T03:50:00+02:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>My application base: geekie</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/06/my-application-base-geekie/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-05T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-06-05T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-06-05:/2013/06/my-application-base-geekie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the past, when I had to manage my images (pictures) I used
&lt;a href="http://gqview.sourceforge.net/"&gt;GQview&lt;/a&gt; (which started back in
&lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2008/08/playing-with-gqview/"&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt;). But the
application doesn't get many updates, and if an application does not get
many updates, it either means it is no longer maintained or that it does
its job perfectly …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the past, when I had to manage my images (pictures) I used
&lt;a href="http://gqview.sourceforge.net/"&gt;GQview&lt;/a&gt; (which started back in
&lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2008/08/playing-with-gqview/"&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt;). But the
application doesn't get many updates, and if an application does not get
many updates, it either means it is no longer maintained or that it does
its job perfectly. Sadly, for GQview, it is the unmaintained reason
(even though the application seems to work pretty well for most tasks).
Enter Geeqie, a fork of GQview to keep evolution on the application up
to speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://geeqie.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Geeqie&lt;/a&gt; image viewer is a simple
viewer that allows to easily manipulate images (like rotation). I launch
it the moment I insert my camera's SD card into my laptop for image
processing. It quickly shows the thumbnails of all images and I start
processing them to see which ones are eligible for manipulations later
on (or are just perfect - not that that occurs frequently) and which can
be deleted immediately. You can also quickly set Exif information (to
annotate the image further) and view some basic aspects of the picture
(such as histogram information).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two features however are what is keeping me with this image viewer:
finding duplicates, and side-by-side comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the duplicate feature, geekie can compare images by name, size,
date, dimensions, checksum, path and - most interestingly, similarity.
If you start working on images, you often create intermediate snapshots
or tryouts. Or, when you start taking pictures, you take several ones in
a short time-frame. With the "find duplicate" feature, you can search
through the images to find all images that had the same base (or are
taking quickly after each other) and see them all simultaneously. That
allows you to remove those you don't need anymore and keep the good
ones. I also use this feature often when people come with their external
hard drive filled with images - none of them having any exif information
anymore and not in any way structured - and ask to see if there are any
duplicates on it. A simple checksum might reveal the obvious ones, but
the similarity search of geeqie goes much, much further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The side-by-side comparison creates a split view of the application, in
which each pane has another image. This feature I use when I have two
pictures that are taken closely after another (so very, very similar in
nature) and I need to see which one is better. With the side-by-side
comparison, I can look at artifacts in the image or the consequences of
the different aperture, ISO and shutter speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the moment I start working on images, Gimp and Darktable are just a
single click away.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Free Software"></category><category term="geeqie"></category><category term="gimp"></category><category term="gqview"></category><category term="images"></category><category term="mab"></category></entry></feed>