<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - structure</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/structure/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-06-04T03:50:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>My application base: freemind</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/06/my-application-base-freemind/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-04T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-06-04T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-06-04:/2013/06/my-application-base-freemind/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anyone who is even remotely busy with innovation will know what mindmaps
are. They are a means to visualize information, ideas or tasks in
whatever structure you like. By using graphical annotations the
information is easier to look through, even when the mindmap becomes
very large. In the commercial world …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Anyone who is even remotely busy with innovation will know what mindmaps
are. They are a means to visualize information, ideas or tasks in
whatever structure you like. By using graphical annotations the
information is easier to look through, even when the mindmap becomes
very large. In the commercial world, mindmapping software such as
&lt;a href="http://www.xmind.net/"&gt;XMind&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://www.mindjet.com/products/mindmanager/"&gt;Mindmanager&lt;/a&gt; are often
used. But these companies should really start looking into Freemind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://freemind.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/Main_Page"&gt;Freemind&lt;/a&gt;
software is a java-based mind map software, running perfectly on
Windows, Linux or other platforms. Installation is a breeze (if you are
allowed to on your work, you can just launch it from a USB drive if you
want, so no installation hassles whatsoever) and its interface is very
intuitive. For all the whistles and bells that the commercial ones
provide, I just want to create my mindmaps and export them into a format
that others can easily use and view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At my real-time job, we (have to) use XMind. If someone shares a mindmap
("their mind" map as I often see it - I seem to have a different mind
than most others in how I structure things, except for one colleague who
imo does not structure things at all) they just share the XMind file and
hope that the recipients can read it. Although XMind can export mindmaps
just fine, I do like the freemind approach where a simple java applet
can show the entire mindmap as interactively as you would navigate
through the application itself. This makes it perfect for discussing
ideas because you can close and open branches easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The
&lt;a href="http://freemind.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/Import_and_export"&gt;export/import&lt;/a&gt;
capabilities of freemind are also interesting. Before being forced to
use XMind, we were using Mindmanager and I could just easily import the
mindmaps into freemind. The file format that freemind uses is an
XML-based one, so translating those onto other formats is not that
difficult if you know some XSLT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally use freemind when I embark on a new project, to structure
the approach, centralize all information, keep track of problems (and
their solutions), etc. The only thing I am missing is a nice interface
for mobile devices though.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Free Software"></category><category term="freemind"></category><category term="java"></category><category term="mab"></category><category term="mindmanager"></category><category term="mindmap"></category><category term="structure"></category><category term="xmind"></category></entry></feed>