<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - book</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/book/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2021-01-06T20:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>SELinux System Administration 3rd Edition</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/01/selinux-system-administration-3rd-edition/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-06T20:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-06T20:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-01-06:/2021/01/selinux-system-administration-3rd-edition/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned previously, recently my latest installment of "SELinux System
Administration" has been released by Packt Publishing. This is already the
third edition of the book, after the first (2013) and second (2016) editions
have gotten reasonable success given the technical and often hard nature of
full SELinux administration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like with the previous editions, this book remains true to the public of
system administrators, rather than SELinux policy developers. Of course,
SELinux policy development is not ignored in the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What has changed&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, it of course updates the content of the previous edition
to be up to date with the latest evolutions within SELinux. There are no earth
shattering changes, so the second edition isn't suddenly deprecated. The examples
are brought up to date with a recent distribution setup, for which I used
Gentoo Linux and CentOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter is, given the recent announcement of CentOS stopping support for
CentOS version 8 in general, a bit confrontational, although it doesn't
really matter that much for the scope of the book. I hope that &lt;a href="https://rockylinux.org/"&gt;Rocky
Linux&lt;/a&gt; will get the focus and support it deserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I digress. A significant part of the updates on the existing content
is on SELinux-enabled applications, applications that act as a so-called object
manager themselves. While quite a few were already covered in the past, these
applications continue to enhance their SELinux support, and in the third edition
a few of these receive a full dedicated chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also a small set of SELinux behavioral changes, like SELinux' NNP
support, as well as SELinux userspace changes like specific extended attributes
for restorecon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the book though isn't about changes, but about new content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What has been added&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As administrators face SELinux-aware applications more and more, the book
goes into much more detail on how to tune SELinux with those SELinux-aware
applications. If we look at the book's structure, you'll find that it has
roughly three parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using SELinux, which covers the fundamentals of using SELinux and
   understanding what SELinux is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SELinux-aware platforms, which dives into the SELinux-aware application
   suites that administrators might come in contact with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Policy management, which focuses on managing, analyzing and even
   developing SELinux policies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By including additional content on SEPostgreSQL, libvirt, container
platforms like Kubernetes, and even Xen Security Modules (which is not
SELinux itself, but strongly influenced and aligned to it to the level
that it even uses the SELinux userspace utilities) the book is showing how
wide SELinux is being used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even on policy development, the book now includes more support than before.
While another book of mine, SELinux Cookbook, is more applicable to policy
development, I did not want to keep administrators out of the loop on how
to develop SELinux policies at all. Especially not since there are more
tools available nowadays that support policy creation, like udica.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SELinux CIL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the changes I also introduced in the book is to include SELinux
Common Intermediate Language (CIL) information and support. When we need
to add in a small SELinux policy change, the book will suggest CIL based
changes as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SELinux CIL is not commonly used in large-scale policy development. Or at
least, not directly. The most significant policy development out there,
the &lt;a href="https://github.com/SELinuxProject/refpolicy/wiki"&gt;SELinux Reference Policy&lt;/a&gt;,
does not use CIL directly itself, and the level of support you find for
the current development approach is very much the default way of working. So
I do not ignore this more traditional approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I did include more CIL focus is because CIL has a few advantages
up its sleeve that is harder to get with the traditional language. Nothing
major perhaps, but enough that I feel it should be more actively promoted
anyway. And this book is hopefully a nice start to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the book is a good read for administrators or even architects that
would like to know more about the technology.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="SELinux"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="packt"></category><category term="book"></category></entry><entry><title>SELinux System Administration, 2nd Edition</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2016/12/selinux-system-administration-2nd-edition/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-22T19:26:00+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-22T19:26:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2016-12-22:/2016/12/selinux-system-administration-2nd-edition/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While still working on a few other projects, one of the time consumers of the
past half year (haven't you noticed? my blog was quite silent) has come to an
end: the &lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/networking-and-servers/selinux-system-administration-second-edition"&gt;SELinux System Administration - Second Edition&lt;/a&gt;
book is now available. With almost double the amount of pages and a serious
update of the content, the book can now be bought either through Packt Publishing
itself, or the various online bookstores such as &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/SELinux-System-Administration-Sven-Vermeulen-ebook/dp/B01LWM02WI"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the holidays now approaching, I hope to be able to execute a few tasks
within the Gentoo community (and of the Gentoo Foundation) and get back on track.
Luckily, my absence was not jeopardizing the state of &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux"&gt;SELinux&lt;/a&gt;
in Gentoo thanks to the efforts of Jason Zaman.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="SELinux"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="gentoo"></category><category term="rhel"></category><category term="redhat"></category><category term="packt"></category><category term="book"></category><category term="publishing"></category></entry><entry><title>It has finally arrived: SELinux System Administration</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/09/it-has-finally-arrived-selinux-system-administration/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-09-27T15:10:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-09-27T15:10:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-09-27:/2013/09/it-has-finally-arrived-selinux-system-administration/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone has it - either physical or in their heads: a list of
things you want to do or achieve before you... well, stop existing. Mine
still has numerous things on it (I should get on it, I know) but one of
the items on that list has recently been …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Almost everyone has it - either physical or in their heads: a list of
things you want to do or achieve before you... well, stop existing. Mine
still has numerous things on it (I should get on it, I know) but one of
the items on that list has recently been removed: write and have a book
published. And the result is a book called &lt;a href="http://www.packtpub.com/selinux-system-administration/book"&gt;SELinux System
Administration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the second quarter of this year, &lt;a href="http://www.packtpub.com/"&gt;Packt
Publishing&lt;/a&gt; contacted me to see if I am
interested in authoring a book about SELinux, focusing on the usage of
SELinux (you know - handling booleans, dealing with file contexts, etc.)
in a short technical book (the aim was 100 pages). Considering that I'm
almost always busy with documentation and editing (for instance, I
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20031110-newsletter.xml#doc_chap2"&gt;joined
Gentoo&lt;/a&gt;
as documentation translator and editor beginning of 2003 if I remember
correctly) and am busy keeping SELinux support within Gentoo on a good
level, I of course said yes to the request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, 100 pages is not a lot for a topic as complex and diverse as
SELinux so was really challenging, but I do think I managed to get
everything in it while keeping it practical. The book first starts with
the fundamentals of SELinux - concepts you really need to grasp before
diving into SELinux. Then, it goes on about switching SELinux state
(disabling, permissive, granular permissive, etc.), logging, managing
SELinux users and roles, handling process domains, etc. Just take a look
at the table of contents and you'll see what I mean ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inside the book, examples are given based on Fedora (and thus also
RedHat Enterprise Linux) and Gentoo Hardened while ensuring that there
are few distribution specific sections in it, making it usable for Linux
administrators of systems with a different Linux distribution installed
to it. Take a look at the &lt;a href="http://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/9781783283170_Chapter-03.pdf?utm_source=packtpub&amp;amp;utm_medium=free&amp;amp;utm_campaign=pdf"&gt;sample
chapter&lt;/a&gt;
and, if you like it, put it on your wish list and let everyone know ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="SELinux"></category><category term="administration"></category><category term="book"></category><category term="fedora"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="packt"></category><category term="packtpub"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="system"></category></entry></feed>