<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - seunshare</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/seunshare/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2016-09-27T20:47:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>We do not ship SELinux sandbox</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2016/09/we-do-not-ship-selinux-sandbox/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-27T20:47:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-09-27T20:47:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2016-09-27:/2016/09/we-do-not-ship-selinux-sandbox/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago a vulnerability was reported in the SELinux sandbox user space
utility. The utility is part of the &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; package. Luckily, Gentoo's
&lt;code&gt;sys-apps/policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; package is not vulnerable - and not because we were
clairvoyant about this issue, but because we don't ship this utility.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago a vulnerability was reported in the SELinux sandbox user space
utility. The utility is part of the &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; package. Luckily, Gentoo's
&lt;code&gt;sys-apps/policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; package is not vulnerable - and not because we were
clairvoyant about this issue, but because we don't ship this utility.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the SELinux sandbox?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SELinux sandbox utility, aptly named &lt;code&gt;sandbox&lt;/code&gt;, is a simple C application which
executes its arguments, but only after ensuring that the task it launches is
going to run in the &lt;code&gt;sandbox_t&lt;/code&gt; domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This domain is specifically crafted to allow applications most standard privileges
needed for interacting with the user (so that the user can of course still use the
application) but removes many permissions that might be abused to either obtain 
information from the system, or use to try and exploit vulnerabilities to gain
more privileges. It also hides a number of resources on the system through
namespaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was &lt;a href="http://danwalsh.livejournal.com/28545.html"&gt;developed in 2009&lt;/a&gt; for Fedora
and Red Hat. Given the necessary SELinux policy support though, it was usable on
other distributions as well, and thus became part of the SELinux user space itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the vulnerability about?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SELinux sandbox utility used an execution approach that did not shield off
the users' terminal access sufficiently. In the &lt;a href="http://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2016/09/25/1"&gt;POC post&lt;/a&gt;
we notice that characters could be sent to the terminal through the &lt;code&gt;ioctl()&lt;/code&gt;
function (which executes the ioctl system call used for input/output operations
against devices) which are eventually executed when the application finishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's bad of course. Hence the CVE-2016-7545 registration, and of course also
a possible &lt;a href="https://github.com/SELinuxProject/selinux/commit/acca96a135a4d2a028ba9b636886af99c0915379"&gt;fix has been committed upstream&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why isn't Gentoo vulnerable / shipping with SELinux sandbox?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's some history involved why Gentoo does not ship the SELinux sandbox (anymore).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, Gentoo already has a command that is called &lt;code&gt;sandbox&lt;/code&gt;, installed through
the &lt;code&gt;sys-apps/sandbox&lt;/code&gt; application. So back in the days that we still shipped with
the SELinux sandbox, we continuously had to patch &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; to use a
different name for the sandbox application (we used &lt;code&gt;sesandbox&lt;/code&gt; then).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then we had a couple of security issues with the SELinux sandbox application.
In 2011, &lt;a href="http://www.cvedetails.com/cve/CVE-2011-1011/"&gt;CVE-2011-1011&lt;/a&gt;
came up in which the &lt;code&gt;seunshare_mount&lt;/code&gt; function had a security issue. And in 2014,
&lt;a href="http://www.cvedetails.com/cve/CVE-2014-3215/"&gt;CVE-2014-3215&lt;/a&gt; came up with - again -
a security issue with &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point, I had enough of this sandbox utility. First of all, it never quite worked
enough on Gentoo as it is (as it also requires a policy which is not part of the
upstream release) and given its wide open access approach (it was meant to contain
various types of workloads, so security concessions had to be made), I decided to
&lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2014/05/dropping-sesandbox-support/"&gt;no longer support the SELinux sandbox in Gentoo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the Gentoo SELinux users ever approached me with the question to add it back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is why Gentoo is not vulnerable to this specific issue.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="selinux"></category><category term="sandbox"></category><category term="gentoo"></category><category term="vulnerability"></category><category term="seunshare"></category></entry><entry><title>Dropping sesandbox support</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/05/dropping-sesandbox-support/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-09T21:03:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-05-09T21:03:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-05-09:/2014/05/dropping-sesandbox-support/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2014-3215"&gt;vulnerability in
seunshare&lt;/a&gt;,
part of &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt;, came to light recently (through &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=509896"&gt;bug
509896&lt;/a&gt;). The issue is
within &lt;code&gt;libcap-ng&lt;/code&gt; actually, but the specific situation in which the
vulnerability can be exploited is only available in &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; is not built by default on Gentoo. You need to define
&lt;code&gt;USE …&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2014-3215"&gt;vulnerability in
seunshare&lt;/a&gt;,
part of &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt;, came to light recently (through &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=509896"&gt;bug
509896&lt;/a&gt;). The issue is
within &lt;code&gt;libcap-ng&lt;/code&gt; actually, but the specific situation in which the
vulnerability can be exploited is only available in &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; is not built by default on Gentoo. You need to define
&lt;code&gt;USE="sesandbox"&lt;/code&gt;, which I implemented as an optional build because I
see no need for the &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; command and the &lt;em&gt;SELinux sandbox
(sesandbox)&lt;/em&gt; support. Upstream (Fedora/RedHat) calls it &lt;em&gt;sandbox&lt;/em&gt;, which
Gentoo translates to &lt;em&gt;sesandbox&lt;/em&gt; as it collides with the Gentoo sandbox
support otherwise. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The build of the SELinux sandbox support is optional, mostly because we
do not have a direct reason to support it. There are no Gentoo users
that I'm aware of that use it. It is used to start an application in a
chroot-like environment, based on Linux namespaces and a specific
SELinux policy called &lt;code&gt;sandbox_t&lt;/code&gt;. The idea isn't that bad, but I rather
focus on proper application confinement and full system enforcement
support (rather than specific services). The SELinux sandbox makes a bit
more sense when the system supports unconfined domains (and users are in
the &lt;code&gt;unconfined_t&lt;/code&gt; domain), but Gentoo focuses on strict policy support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn't the first vulnerability in &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;. In 2011,
another privilege escalation vulnerability was found in the application
(see &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=374897"&gt;bug 374897&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But having a vulnerability in the application (or its interaction with
&lt;code&gt;libcap-ng&lt;/code&gt;) doesn't mean an exploitable vulnerability. Most users will
not even have &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;, and those that do have it will not be able to
call it if you are running with SELinux in &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt; or have
&lt;code&gt;USE="-unconfined"&lt;/code&gt; set for the other policies. If &lt;code&gt;USE="unconfined"&lt;/code&gt; is
set and you run &lt;em&gt;mcs&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;targeted&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;mls&lt;/em&gt; (which isn't default either,
the default is &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt;) then if your users are still mapped to the
regular user domains (&lt;code&gt;user_t&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;staff_t&lt;/code&gt; or even &lt;code&gt;sysadm_t&lt;/code&gt;) then
&lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; doesn't work as the SELinux policy prevents its behavior
before the vulnerability is triggered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have a &lt;em&gt;targeted&lt;/em&gt; policy with users mapped to
&lt;code&gt;unconfined_t&lt;/code&gt; and you have built &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; with
&lt;code&gt;USE="sesandbox"&lt;/code&gt; or you run in SELinux in permissive mode, then please
tell me if you can trigger the exploit. On my systems, &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; fails
with the message that it can't drop its privileges and thus exits
(instead of executing the exploit code as it suggested by the reports).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I mentioned that most user don't use SELinux sandbox, and because
I can't even get it to work (regardless of the vulnerability), I decided
to drop support for it from the builds. That also allows me to more
quickly introduce the new userspace utilities as I don't need to
refactor the code to switch from &lt;code&gt;sandbox&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;sesandbox&lt;/code&gt; anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils-2.2.5-r4&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils-2.3_rc1-r1&lt;/code&gt; are now
available which do not build &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; anymore. And now I can focus on
providing the full &lt;em&gt;2.3&lt;/em&gt; userspace that has been announced today.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="policycoreutils"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="seunshare"></category><category term="vulnerability"></category></entry></feed>