<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - visio</title><link href="http://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.siphos.be/tag/visio/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-06-03T03:50:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>My application base: draw.io</title><link href="http://blog.siphos.be/2013/06/my-application-base-draw-io/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-03T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-06-03T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-06-03:/2013/06/my-application-base-draw-io/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The next few weeks (months even) will be challenging my free time as I'm
working on (too many) projects simultaneously (sadly, only a few of
those are free software related, most are house renovations). But that
shouldn't stop me from starting a new set of posts, being &lt;em&gt;my
application base …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The next few weeks (months even) will be challenging my free time as I'm
working on (too many) projects simultaneously (sadly, only a few of
those are free software related, most are house renovations). But that
shouldn't stop me from starting a new set of posts, being &lt;em&gt;my
application base&lt;/em&gt;. In this series, I'll cover a few applications (or
websites) that I either use often or that I should use more. In either
case, the application does its job very well so why not give some input
on it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first on the agenda is the &lt;a href="http://www.draw.io"&gt;Draw.io&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Draw.io, you get a web-browser based drawing application for
diagrams, flowcharts, UML, BPMN etc. I came across this application
while looking for an alternative to &lt;a href="https://live.gnome.org/Dia"&gt;Dia&lt;/a&gt;,
which by itself was supposed to be an alternative to &lt;a href="https://office.microsoft.com/en-us/visio/"&gt;Microsoft
Visio&lt;/a&gt; (err, no). Don't get
me wrong, Dia is nice, but it lacks evolution and just doesn't feel
easy. Draw.io on the other hand is evolving constantly, and it is also
active on &lt;a href="https://plus.google.com/100634082864796769666/"&gt;Google Plus&lt;/a&gt;
where you can follow up on all recent developments and thoughts (I hope
I get the G+ link correctly, it's not that I don't like numbers, just
not in URLs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started using Draw.io while documenting free software IT architectures
(such as implementations of BIND, PostgreSQL, etc.) for which I needed
some diagrams. Although Draw.io is an online application (and its
underlying engine is not completely free software) you can easily work
with it from different locations. It integrates with &lt;a href="https://drive.google.com"&gt;Google
Drive&lt;/a&gt; to store the diagrams on if you want -
and if you don't, you can always save the diagrams in their native XML
format on your system and open them later again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interface is very easy to use, and I recently found out that it now
also supports mobile devices, which is perfect for tablets (the mobile
device support is recent afaik and still undergoing updates). The site
also works well in various browsers (tried IExplorer 10 at work, Firefox
and Google Chrome and they all seem to work nicely) - eat that stupid
commercial vendors that force me into using IExplorer 8 or Firefox 10 -
you know who you are!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A site/service to keep a close eye on. The service itself is free (and
doesn't seem too limited due to it), but Draw.io also has commercial
support if you want through Google Apps and Confluence integration. I
don't have much experience with those yet but that might change in the
near future (projects, projects).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Documentation"></category><category term="appbase"></category><category term="architecturing"></category><category term="dia"></category><category term="draw"></category><category term="draw.io"></category><category term="mab"></category><category term="visio"></category></entry></feed>