<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - word</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/word/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-06-08T03:50:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>My application base: LibreOffice</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/06/my-application-base-libreoffice/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-08T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-06-08T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-06-08:/2013/06/my-application-base-libreoffice/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Of course, working with a Linux desktop eventually requires you to work
with an office suite. Although I have used alternatives like AbiWord and
Calligra in the past, and although I do think that Google Docs might
eventually become powerful enough to use instead, I'm currently using
&lt;a href="https://www.libreoffice.org/"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Of course, working with a Linux desktop eventually requires you to work
with an office suite. Although I have used alternatives like AbiWord and
Calligra in the past, and although I do think that Google Docs might
eventually become powerful enough to use instead, I'm currently using
&lt;a href="https://www.libreoffice.org/"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of LibreOffice for Linux users is well known: it has decent
Microsoft Office support (although I hardly ever need it; most users
don't mind exporting the files in an open document format and publishers
often support OpenOffice/LibreOffice formats themselves) and its
features are becoming more and more powerful, such as the CMIS support
(for online collaboration through content management systems). It also
has a huge community, sharing templates and other documents that make
life with LibreOffice even much prettier. Don't forget to check out its
&lt;a href="https://www.libreoffice.org/get-help/documentation/"&gt;extensive
documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aspects of LibreOffice I use the most are of course its writer (word
processor) and calc (spreadsheet application). The writer-part is for
when I do technical writing, whereas the spreadsheet application is for
generating simple management sheets for startups and households that
want to keep track of things (such as budgets, creating invoices, data
for mail-merge, etc.). At my work, Excel is one of the most used "end
user computing" tools, so I happen to get acquainted with quite a few
spreadsheet tips and tricks that are beneficial for small companies or
organizations ;-) Also, Calc has support for macro-like enhancements,
which makes it a good start for fast application development (until the
requests of the user/client has been stabilized, after which I usually
suggest a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; application development ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I generally don't use its presentation part much though - if I get a
powerpoint, I first see if Google Docs doesn't show it sufficiently
well. If not, then I try it out in LibreOffice. But usually, if someone
sends me a presentation, I tend to ask for a PDF version.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Free-Software"></category><category term="excel"></category><category term="libreoffice"></category><category term="mab"></category><category term="openoffice"></category><category term="word"></category></entry></feed>