<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - policycoreutils</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/policycoreutils/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2014-05-09T21:03:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Dropping sesandbox support</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/05/dropping-sesandbox-support/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-09T21:03:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-05-09T21:03:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-05-09:/2014/05/dropping-sesandbox-support/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2014-3215"&gt;vulnerability in
seunshare&lt;/a&gt;,
part of &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt;, came to light recently (through &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=509896"&gt;bug
509896&lt;/a&gt;). The issue is
within &lt;code&gt;libcap-ng&lt;/code&gt; actually, but the specific situation in which the
vulnerability can be exploited is only available in &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; is not built by default on Gentoo. You need to define
&lt;code&gt;USE …&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2014-3215"&gt;vulnerability in
seunshare&lt;/a&gt;,
part of &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt;, came to light recently (through &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=509896"&gt;bug
509896&lt;/a&gt;). The issue is
within &lt;code&gt;libcap-ng&lt;/code&gt; actually, but the specific situation in which the
vulnerability can be exploited is only available in &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; is not built by default on Gentoo. You need to define
&lt;code&gt;USE="sesandbox"&lt;/code&gt;, which I implemented as an optional build because I
see no need for the &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; command and the &lt;em&gt;SELinux sandbox
(sesandbox)&lt;/em&gt; support. Upstream (Fedora/RedHat) calls it &lt;em&gt;sandbox&lt;/em&gt;, which
Gentoo translates to &lt;em&gt;sesandbox&lt;/em&gt; as it collides with the Gentoo sandbox
support otherwise. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The build of the SELinux sandbox support is optional, mostly because we
do not have a direct reason to support it. There are no Gentoo users
that I'm aware of that use it. It is used to start an application in a
chroot-like environment, based on Linux namespaces and a specific
SELinux policy called &lt;code&gt;sandbox_t&lt;/code&gt;. The idea isn't that bad, but I rather
focus on proper application confinement and full system enforcement
support (rather than specific services). The SELinux sandbox makes a bit
more sense when the system supports unconfined domains (and users are in
the &lt;code&gt;unconfined_t&lt;/code&gt; domain), but Gentoo focuses on strict policy support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this isn't the first vulnerability in &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;. In 2011,
another privilege escalation vulnerability was found in the application
(see &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=374897"&gt;bug 374897&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But having a vulnerability in the application (or its interaction with
&lt;code&gt;libcap-ng&lt;/code&gt;) doesn't mean an exploitable vulnerability. Most users will
not even have &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt;, and those that do have it will not be able to
call it if you are running with SELinux in &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt; or have
&lt;code&gt;USE="-unconfined"&lt;/code&gt; set for the other policies. If &lt;code&gt;USE="unconfined"&lt;/code&gt; is
set and you run &lt;em&gt;mcs&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;targeted&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;mls&lt;/em&gt; (which isn't default either,
the default is &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt;) then if your users are still mapped to the
regular user domains (&lt;code&gt;user_t&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;staff_t&lt;/code&gt; or even &lt;code&gt;sysadm_t&lt;/code&gt;) then
&lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; doesn't work as the SELinux policy prevents its behavior
before the vulnerability is triggered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have a &lt;em&gt;targeted&lt;/em&gt; policy with users mapped to
&lt;code&gt;unconfined_t&lt;/code&gt; and you have built &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; with
&lt;code&gt;USE="sesandbox"&lt;/code&gt; or you run in SELinux in permissive mode, then please
tell me if you can trigger the exploit. On my systems, &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; fails
with the message that it can't drop its privileges and thus exits
(instead of executing the exploit code as it suggested by the reports).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I mentioned that most user don't use SELinux sandbox, and because
I can't even get it to work (regardless of the vulnerability), I decided
to drop support for it from the builds. That also allows me to more
quickly introduce the new userspace utilities as I don't need to
refactor the code to switch from &lt;code&gt;sandbox&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;sesandbox&lt;/code&gt; anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils-2.2.5-r4&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils-2.3_rc1-r1&lt;/code&gt; are now
available which do not build &lt;code&gt;seunshare&lt;/code&gt; anymore. And now I can focus on
providing the full &lt;em&gt;2.3&lt;/em&gt; userspace that has been announced today.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="policycoreutils"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="seunshare"></category><category term="vulnerability"></category></entry></feed>