<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - viewpoint</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/viewpoint/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2021-08-27T21:10:00+02:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>Component view of infrastructure</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-08-27T21:10:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-27T21:10:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2021-08-27:/2021/08/component-view-of-infrastructure/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;IT architects try to use views and viewpoints to convey the target architecture
to the various stakeholders. Each stakeholder has their own interests in the
architecture and wants to see their requirements fulfilled. A core
role of the architect is to understand these requirements and make sure the
requirements are met, and to balance all the different requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architecture languages or meta-models often put significant focus on these
views. Archimate has a large annex on &lt;a href="https://pubs.opengroup.org/architecture/archimate3-doc/apdxc.html#_Toc10045495"&gt;Example
Viewpoints&lt;/a&gt;
just for this purpose. However, unless the organization is widely accustomed to
enterprise architecture views, it is unlikely that the views themselves are the
final product: being able to translate those views into pretty slides and
presentations is still an important task for architects when they need to
present their findings to non-architecture roles.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;IT architects try to use views and viewpoints to convey the target architecture
to the various stakeholders. Each stakeholder has their own interests in the
architecture and wants to see their requirements fulfilled. A core
role of the architect is to understand these requirements and make sure the
requirements are met, and to balance all the different requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architecture languages or meta-models often put significant focus on these
views. Archimate has a large annex on &lt;a href="https://pubs.opengroup.org/architecture/archimate3-doc/apdxc.html#_Toc10045495"&gt;Example
Viewpoints&lt;/a&gt;
just for this purpose. However, unless the organization is widely accustomed to
enterprise architecture views, it is unlikely that the views themselves are the
final product: being able to translate those views into pretty slides and
presentations is still an important task for architects when they need to
present their findings to non-architecture roles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infrastructure domain in viewpoints&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While searching for a way to describe the infrastructure domain,
I tend to align with certain viewpoints as well, as it allows architects
to decompose a complex situation into more manageable parts. So the question
is no longer "how do I show what the infrastructure domain is", but rather
"what different viewpoints do I need to cover the scope of (and
explanation on) the infrastructure domain".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I currently settle on five views:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;component view&lt;/em&gt;, which covers the vertical stack of an IT infrastructure
  component.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;location view&lt;/em&gt;, which is the horizontal stack for IT infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;process view&lt;/em&gt;, which covers the general enterprise requirements for IT
  infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;service view&lt;/em&gt;, which provides insights into what functional offerings are
  provided (and for which I posted a current view a short while ago, titled "&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2021/06/an-it-services-overview/"&gt;An
  IT services overview&lt;/a&gt;")&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;zoning view&lt;/em&gt;, which represents the IT environment landscape. A few years
  ago, I covered this as well in "&lt;a href="https://blog.siphos.be/2017/06/structuring-infrastructural-deployments/"&gt;Structuring infrastructural
  deployments&lt;/a&gt;"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these views are related to each other, but represent insights that are
particularly useful for certain discussions or representations. Some viewpoints
are even details for another. For instance, the &lt;em&gt;zoning view&lt;/em&gt; is a view that
provides more detail on a particular layer in the &lt;em&gt;location view&lt;/em&gt;. A simple
relationship between the above five views is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Relationship between the five infrastructure views" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202108/five-infra-views.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this isn't a proper meta-model, just a representation. It starts
with what the infrastructure domain has to accomplish (process view),
which defines the services the domain has to support. These services
comprise several components, and these are deployed in various
zones across the organization. The zone overview is part of the more
elaborate location views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components are a good introduction to infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a good coverage of the infrastructure domain would start with the
process view, I think it is not always the easiest. Not all stakeholders
are fully acquainted with processes and what they entail, and I feel it
might be easier to start with a more tangible view, i.e. a component
view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, when explaining what IT infrastructure is to an outsider
(say, a family member that isn't active in the IT world), I often start with
a component view (often using a cellphone as a starting example), then going
about the massive amount of components that need to be managed, hence the need
for proper processes. After elaborating a bit on the various processes involved,
we can then go to a service overview, to then move on to the hosting of all
those services in a structured and reliable environment (zoning), with the
various challenges related to locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is the component view that I reuse a lot? It is basically
the vertical stack that most hosting-related services use to explain where
their product is situated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Layered view on a component level" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202108/component-view.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you start with a cellphone view, then you can easily describe the hardware,
operating system, application, and data layers in the view. You can mention that
the hardware is an expensive one-time investment that the user hopes to use for
a few years (so you can explain &lt;em&gt;capital expenditures (CapEx)&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;operational
expenditures (OpEx)&lt;/em&gt;. The latter can be a cloud service that the
user synchronizes its data to, like Apple iCloud or Google Drive).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction between operating system and application, and its impact on
the users, can also be explained easily: operating system upgrades are
heavier, and users often want to choose when this occurs, as operating system
upgrades are not always fully backward compatible. Or, the user's hardware isn't
supported on the next operating system (e.g. upgrading Apple iOS 12 to iOS 13,
or Android 10 to Android 11). Applications, on the other hand, are often
automatically updated and are less intrusive. However, because there are
many applications, managing the application landscape can be more daunting than
the operating system one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we can move on to the scaling challenges that an organization has to
face, which will gradually build up more insights into the component layers. For
instance, if a company is developing and maintaining a mobile application, it
wants to test its new releases on different operating system
versions.  But it would not be sensible to have each developer walk around with
six phones because they need to test the application on iOS 12, iOS 13, iOS 14,
Android 9, Android 10, and Android 11. Instead, testing could be done on
emulators (which can be considered hypervisors, albeit often not that exhaustive
in features).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This introduces concepts of optimizing resources for cost, but also the
benefits of having these services available 'at distance' (remote access
to the emulation environments) as well as first steps in virtualization.
You can state that this emulation is something the user can do on their
laptops, but that in enterprise environments this is done with either
cloud services or on the enterprise servers, as that facilitates collaboration
with team members, and simplifies managing these assets when the teams get
larger or smaller. And these servers, well, they too are virtualized for
resource optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also discuss the data layer, and the challenge that a regular user
has when their phone is near its limits (e.g. storage is full), the options the
user has (add SD card if the phone supports it, or use cloud storage services),
and compare that with larger enterprises where data hosting is often either
centralized or abstracted, so that systems are not bound to the limits of their
device's storage capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Component views enable scalability and cost insights&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The layered view on components, of course, is a meta-view rather than an actual
one: it shows how a stack can be built up, but the actual benefit is when
you look at the component view of a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, if we were to assess a Kubernetes cluster, it could be represented
as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Kubernetes component view" src="https://blog.siphos.be/images/202108/k8s-component-view.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going bottom-up on this view, we can identify (and thus elaborate on) the
various layers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the hardware level, we see four physical servers (named sppc01 to sppc04).
  These servers are of a particular brand and have 32 Gb of memory each (which
  isn't a lot, the cluster is rather small).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KVM is used as the hypervisor. The hypervisor combines the four physical
  servers in a single cluster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;KVM then provides eight virtual systems (named svpc01 to svpc08) from the
  cluster. The first three are used for the Kubernetes control plane, the others
  are the worker nodes. Note that it is recommended to host the nodes of the
  control plane on different physical machines so that a failure on one physical
  machine doesn't jeopardize the cluster availability. This can be configured on
  the hypervisor, but that is outside the scope of this article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The physical servers use a hardened Gentoo Linux operating system using the
  musl C library, whereas the virtual servers use a regular Gentoo Linux
  installation as their operating system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The orchestration layer is Kubernetes itself, using the CRI-O container
  runtime as middleware.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The applications depicted are those of the Kubernetes ecosystem, with the main
  control plane applications and worker node applications listed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we were to host an application inside the Kubernetes cluster, it would
be deployed on the worker nodes. The logical design of a Kubernetes cluster
is not something to be represented in a component view (that's more for
the location view, as there we will talk about the topology of services).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With such component views, we can have some insights into the costs. Of course,
this is just a simple Kubernetes cluster, and built with pure open-source
software, so the costs are going to be on the hardware side (and the resources
they consume). In larger enterprises, however, the hypervisor is often a
commercially backed one like Hyper-V (Microsoft) and vSphere (VMware), which
have their specific licensing terms (which could be the number of machines or
even CPUs).  Also, enterprises often use a commercially backed Kubernetes, like
Rancher or OpenShift (Red Hat, part of IBM), which often have per-node licensing
terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Component views are just the beginning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I use a component view to explain what infrastructure is about,
it is merely the beginning. It provides a rudimentary layered view, which most
people can easily relate to. Content-wise, it is reasonably understandable (or
easy enough to explain) for people that aren't IT savvy, and is something that
you can easily find a lot of material for online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we delve into the processes of (or related to) infrastructure, it becomes
more challenging to keep the readers/listeners with you. Processes can (will)
often be very abstract, and going into the details of each process is a lengthy
endeavor. I'll cover that in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feedback? Comments?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I've dropped Disqus as comment engine from my blog site, mainly
for concerns about my visitor's security, as well as the advertisements that it
embedded. I want my blog to be simple and straightforward, so I decided to not
have any other third-party services with it for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you have feedback or comments, don't hesitate to &lt;a href="mailto:sven.vermeulen@siphos.be"&gt;drop me an
email&lt;/a&gt;, or join the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/infrainsight/status/1431332634370711552"&gt;discussion on
Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Architecture"></category><category term="architecture"></category><category term="component"></category><category term="viewpoint"></category></entry></feed>