<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - toolchain</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/toolchain/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-08-01T22:43:00+02:00</updated><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title>And now, 31 days later...</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/08/and-now-31-days-later/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-01T22:43:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-08-01T22:43:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-08-01:/2013/08/and-now-31-days-later/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;... the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened"&gt;Gentoo Hardened&lt;/a&gt; team
had its monthly online meeting again ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the agenda were the usual suspects, such as the &lt;em&gt;toolchain&lt;/em&gt;. In this
category, Zorry mentioned that he has a fix for GCC 4.8.1 for the
&lt;code&gt;hardenedno*&lt;/code&gt; and vanilla &lt;code&gt;gcc-config&lt;/code&gt; options which will be added to
the tree …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;... the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened"&gt;Gentoo Hardened&lt;/a&gt; team
had its monthly online meeting again ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the agenda were the usual suspects, such as the &lt;em&gt;toolchain&lt;/em&gt;. In this
category, Zorry mentioned that he has a fix for GCC 4.8.1 for the
&lt;code&gt;hardenedno*&lt;/code&gt; and vanilla &lt;code&gt;gcc-config&lt;/code&gt; options which will be added to
the tree after some more testing. The problem is that with GCC 4.8,
certain settings need to be set sooner than before (in the code path),
which is what the fix focuses on. The ASAN issue is still unresolved,
but otherwise GCC 4.8 is working fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;, the policycoreutils package has been bumped to include
support for &lt;code&gt;mcstrans&lt;/code&gt;, a translation daemon that visualizes humanly
readable strings instead of the standard sensitivity/category sets in
case of MCS/MLS policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding documentation, the wiki team (most notably a3li) is working
hard to support project pages on the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo
Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. Once we can, we will be moving our
project page with all related documentation to the wiki, allowing for
easier documentation development and a more modern look. To support
this, an XML-to-wiki stylesheet is available that translates ProjectXML
and GuideXML to the wiki language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the meeting, we also mentioned the stabilization policy (or at
least, no-longer-stabilization) of the vanilla sources (plain kernel.org
Linux kernel sources). This doesn't immediately effect the hardened
project, but is important to know nonetheless, especially for users of
hardened technologies that are in the main kernel already (like SELinux
or IMA/EVM) as they have to be aware to either use the latest
(regardless of the keywords in use) or switch to gentoo-sources or
(preferably) hardened-sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For uclibc support, the stages will be provided every 2 months rather
than every month as this is a resource-intensive process that isn't
fully automated yet (except for amd64 and x86 which are automated).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on PaX and grSecurity support, the XATTR patch for tmpfs is now
in the kernel, and the problem about loosing PaX markings during
installation is fixed as Portage (2.1.12.9 and higher) now preserves the
flags during installation (a wrapper on &lt;code&gt;install&lt;/code&gt; is used that preserves
&lt;code&gt;usr.pax.flags&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="grsecurity"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="irl"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="minutes"></category><category term="pax"></category><category term="project"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="toolchain"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened progress meeting of march 2013</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/03/gentoo-hardened-progress-meeting-of-march-2013/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-03-07T22:46:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-03-07T22:46:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-03-07:/2013/03/gentoo-hardened-progress-meeting-of-march-2013/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another month has passed, so time for a new progress meeting...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toolchain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC v4.7 has been unmasked, allowing a large set of users to test out
the new GCC. It is also expected that GCC 4.8-rc1 will hit the tree next
week. In the hardened-dev overlay, hardened support …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another month has passed, so time for a new progress meeting...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Toolchain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC v4.7 has been unmasked, allowing a large set of users to test out
the new GCC. It is also expected that GCC 4.8-rc1 will hit the tree next
week. In the hardened-dev overlay, hardened support for x86, amd64 and
arm has been added (SPEC updates) and the remainder of architectures
will be added by the end of the week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kernel and grSecurity/PaX&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kernel 3.7.5 had a security issue (local root privilege escalation) so
3.7.5-r1 which held a fix for this was stabilized quickly. However,
other (non-security) problems have been reported, such as one with
dovecot, regarding the VSIZE memory size. This should be fixed in the
3.8 series, so these are candidate for a faster stabilization. This
faster stabilization is never fun, as it increases the likelihood that
we miss other things, but they are needed as the vulnerability in the
previous stable kernel was too severe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding XATTR_PAX, we are getting pretty close to the migration. The
eclass is ready and will be announced for review on the appropriate
mailinglists later this week. A small problem still remains on
Paludis-using systems (Paludis does not record NEEDED.ELF.2 information
- linkage information - so it is hard to get all the linkage information
on a system). A different revdep-pax and migrate-pax toolset will be
built that detects the necessary linkage information, but much slower
than on a Portage-running system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SELinux&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 11th revision of the policies are now stable, and work is on the way
for the 12th revision which will hit the tree soon. Some work is on the
way for setools and policycoreutils (one due to a new release - setools
- and the other one due to a build failure if PAM is not set). Both
packages will hit the hardened-dev overlay soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new "edition" of the selinuxnode virtual image has been pushed to the
mirror system, providing a SELinux-enabled (enforcing) Gentoo Hardened
system with grSecurity and PaX, as well as IMA and EVM enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Profiles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 13.0 profiles have been running fine for a while at a few of our
developer systems. No changes have been needed (yet) so things are
looking good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;System Integrity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The necessary userland utilities have been moved to the main tree. The
documentation for IMA/EVM has been updated as well to reflec the current
state of IMA/EVM within Gentoo Hardened. IMA, even with the custom
policies, seems to be working well. EVM on the other hand has some
issues, so you might need to run with EVM=fix for now. Debugging on this
issue is on the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the user oriented documentation (integrity and SELinux) have
been moved to the Gentoo Wiki for easier user contributions and
simplified management. Other documents will follow soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="grsecurity"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="kernel"></category><category term="pax"></category><category term="profiles"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="toolchain"></category></entry></feed>