<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - report</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/report/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-08-29T20:27:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened progress report</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/08/gentoo-hardened-progress-report/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-29T20:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-08-29T20:27:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-08-29:/2013/08/gentoo-hardened-progress-report/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, we had our monthly online meeting to discuss the progress amongst
the various Gentoo Hardened projects. As usual, here is a small
write-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead election&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As every year, we also reviewed the current project leads. No surprises
here, everybody is happy with the current leads so they are re-elected …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, we had our monthly online meeting to discuss the progress amongst
the various Gentoo Hardened projects. As usual, here is a small
write-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead election&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As every year, we also reviewed the current project leads. No surprises
here, everybody is happy with the current leads so they are re-elected
for another term. We did have two candidates for the lead position, but
even the other candidate vote for Zorry - so we had a unanimous vote ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC version 4.8.1 will be unmasked pretty soon, and the &lt;code&gt;hardenedno*&lt;/code&gt;
specs on it will work. However, there is still no progress on the asan
(Address Sanitizer) support together with UDEREF. As mentioned in a
previous post, UDEREF "reduces" the address space a bit which doesn't
play well with asan. Still, it isn't inevitable, since PowerPC also has
a reduced address space and so does Windows. So perhaps we can use the
same model for UDEREF enabled kernels? We'll send the suggestion and the
already-existing fixes upstream and hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In GCC 4.8.1, the &lt;code&gt;-fstack-check&lt;/code&gt; option might be enabled by default,
but the question is for which architectures and platforms. We know a few
packages, such as &lt;em&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;libav&lt;/em&gt; have problems with it. In those
cases, the ebuild will be modified to use &lt;code&gt;-fno-stack-check&lt;/code&gt; (if
hardened). We opt to enable it for all as we don't really expect much
(if any) breakage that can't be dealt with swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support for hardened uClibc is still going steadily. Blueness is heating
his room a bit with it, seeing that mips32r2 takes about 2 weeks to
build hardened and vanilla stages - he is using an Ubiquity router
station for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel and Grsecurity/PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to some boot freezes, as explained in bugs
&lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/482010"&gt;482010&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/481790"&gt;481790&lt;/a&gt;, we don't have a stable 3.10.x
kernel yet. However, most of the issues should be resolved and we're
waiting for confirmation, so we can be looking at a stable 3.10.x kernel
soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3.10 kernel will probably not be a long-term support kernel for PaX
and Grsecurity - such LTS kernel will be picked next year, most likely
the same kernel version that Ubuntu LTS settles on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small update on &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; has been made that updates &lt;strong&gt;rlpkg&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;selocal&lt;/strong&gt;. Other than that, our policies are in nice shape. A new
revision will be pushed to the tree soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Integrity side, recent kernels support custom IMA policies
(again) so our documentation is accurate again. Next to IMA/EVM, I'll be
working on documentation for cryptographically signed kernel module
support soon as well as SCAP-based security baselines for Gentoo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blueness added a MUSL-based Gentoo profile (&lt;code&gt;hardened/linux/musl&lt;/code&gt;). Musl
is an even more slim libc and its profile is extremely experimental for
now. The profile structure is still a bit off though, a reorganization
will be suggested soon so that the profile inheritance is clear and
predictable, starting off with a non-hardened one
(&lt;code&gt;default/linux/{uclibc,musl}&lt;/code&gt;) and then a hardened specific one that
inherits from the default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Documentation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened"&gt;Gentoo Hardened
project&lt;/a&gt; now has its main
project page on the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;, and all
(most) documentation is moved to there as well for the Gentoo Hardened
subprojects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also explained to the folks that I have authored a book on SELinux
System Administration (for Packt Publishing), which was why I was less
active the last few months. However, that is now done so I'm back on
track. More information about the book follows later on my blog ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as usual, klondike has been tweeting the entire meeting through our
&lt;code&gt;@GentooHardened&lt;/code&gt; twitter account ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="minutes"></category><category term="progress_report"></category><category term="report"></category></entry></feed>