<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - irc</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/tag/irc/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2014-08-29T16:43:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened august meeting</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/08/gentoo-hardened-august-meeting/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-08-29T16:43:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-08-29T16:43:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-08-29:/2014/08/gentoo-hardened-august-meeting/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another month has passed, so we had another online meeting to discuss
the progress within Gentoo Hardened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead elections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The yearly lead elections within Gentoo Hardened were up again. Zorry
(Magnus Granberg) was re-elected as project lead so doesn't need to
update his LinkedIn profile yet ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;blueness (Anthony G …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another month has passed, so we had another online meeting to discuss
the progress within Gentoo Hardened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead elections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The yearly lead elections within Gentoo Hardened were up again. Zorry
(Magnus Granberg) was re-elected as project lead so doesn't need to
update his LinkedIn profile yet ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;blueness (Anthony G. Basile) has been working on the uclibc stages for
some time. Due to the configurable nature of these setups, many
&lt;code&gt;/etc/portage&lt;/code&gt; files were provided as part of the stages, which
&lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=519686"&gt;shouldn't&lt;/a&gt; happen. Work
is on the way to update this accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the musl setup, blueness is also rebuilding the stages to use a
symbolic link to the dynamic linker (&lt;code&gt;/lib/ld-linux-arch.so&lt;/code&gt;) as
recommended by the musl maintainers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel and grsecurity with PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=520198"&gt;bug&lt;/a&gt; has been
submitted which shows that large binary files (in the bug, a chrome
binary with debug information is shown to be more than 2 Gb in size)
cannot be pax-mark'ed, with &lt;code&gt;paxctl&lt;/code&gt; informing the user that the file is
too big. The problem is when the PAX marks are in ELF (as the
application mmaps the binary) - users of extended attributes based PaX
markings do not have this problem. blueness is working on making things
a bit more intelligent, and to fix this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been making a few changes to the SELinux setup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The live ebuilds (those with version 9999 which use the repository
    policy rather than snapshots of the policies) are now being used as
    "master" in case of releases: the ebuilds can just be copied to the
    right version to support the releases. The release script inside the
    repository is adjusted to reflect this as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The SELinux eclass now supports two variables, &lt;code&gt;SELINUX_GIT_REPO&lt;/code&gt;
    and &lt;code&gt;SELINUX_GIT_BRANCH&lt;/code&gt;, which allows users to use their own
    repository, and developers to work in specific branches together. By
    setting the right value in the users' &lt;code&gt;make.conf&lt;/code&gt; switching policy
    repositories or branches is now a breeze.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another change in the SELinux eclass is that, after the installation
    of SELinux policies, we will check the reverse dependencies of the
    policy package and relabel the files of these packages. This allows
    us to only have &lt;code&gt;RDEPEND&lt;/code&gt; dependencies towards the SELinux policy
    packages (if the application itself does not otherwise link with
    &lt;em&gt;libselinux&lt;/em&gt;), making the dependency tree within the package manager
    more correct. We still need to update these packages to drop the
    &lt;code&gt;DEPEND&lt;/code&gt; dependency, which is something we will focus on in the next
    few months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In order to support improved cooperation between SELinux developers
    in the Gentoo Hardened team - perfinion (Jason Zaman) is in the
    queue for becoming a new developer in our mids - a &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:SELinux/CodingStyle"&gt;coding style for
    SELinux
    policies&lt;/a&gt;
    is being drafted up. This is of course based on the coding style of
    the reference policy, but with some Gentoo specific improvements and
    more clarifications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;perfinion has been working on improving the SELinux support in
    OpenRC (release 0.13 and higher), making some of the additions that
    we had to make in the past - such as the &lt;code&gt;selinux_gentoo&lt;/code&gt; init
    script - obsolete.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meeting also discussed a few bugs in more detail, but if you really
want to know, just hang on and wait for the IRC logs ;-) Other usual
sections (system integrity and profiles) did not have any notable topics
to describe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened July meeting</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/08/gentoo-hardened-july-meeting/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-08-01T21:48:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-08-01T21:48:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-08-01:/2014/08/gentoo-hardened-july-meeting/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I failed to show up myself (I fell asleep - kids are fun, but deplete
your energy source quickly), but that shouldn't prevent me from making a
nice write-up of the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.9 gives some issues with kernel compilations and other components.
Lately, breakage has been reported with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I failed to show up myself (I fell asleep - kids are fun, but deplete
your energy source quickly), but that shouldn't prevent me from making a
nice write-up of the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.9 gives some issues with kernel compilations and other components.
Lately, breakage has been reported with GCC 4.9.1 compiling MySQL or
with debugging symbols. So for hardened, we'll wait this one out until
the bugs are fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For GCC 4.10, the
&lt;a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/ml/gcc-patches/2014-07/msg02231.html"&gt;--enable-default-pie&lt;/a&gt;
patch has been sent upstream. If that is accepted, the SSP one will be
sent as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In uclibc land, stages are being developed for PPC. This is the final
architecture that is often used in embedded worlds that needed support
for it in Gentoo, and that's now being finalized. Go blueness!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;code&gt;libpcre&lt;/code&gt; upgrade broke relabeling operations on SELinux enabled
systems. A fix for this has been made part of libselinux, but a little
too late, so some users will be affected by the problem. It's easily
worked around (removing the &lt;code&gt;*.bin&lt;/code&gt; files in the &lt;code&gt;contexts/files/&lt;/code&gt;
directory of the SELinux configuration) and hopefully will never occur
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2.3 userland has finally been stabilized (we had a few dependencies
that we were waiting for - and we were a dependency ourselves for other
packages as well).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, some &lt;a href="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.hardened/6266"&gt;thought
discussion&lt;/a&gt;
is being done (not that there's much feedback on it, but every
documented step is a good step imo) on the SELinux policy within Gentoo
(and the principles that we'll follow that are behind it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel and grsecurity / PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to some security issues, the Linux kernel sources have been
stabilized more rapidly than usual, which left little time for broad
validation and regression testing. Updates and fixes have been applied
since and new stabilizations occurred. Hopefully we're now at the right,
stable set again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The C-based &lt;code&gt;install-xattr&lt;/code&gt; application (which is performance-wise a big
improvement over the Python-based one) is working well in "lab
environments" (some developers are using it exclusively). It is included
in the Portage repository
^(if\ I\ understand\ the\ chat\ excerpts\ correctly)^ but as such
not available for broader usage yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An update against &lt;code&gt;elfix&lt;/code&gt; is made as well as there was a dependency
mismatch when building with &lt;code&gt;USE=-ptpax&lt;/code&gt;. This will be corrected in
elfix-0.9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, blueness is also working on a GLEP (Gentoo Linux Enhancement
Proposal) to export VDB information (especially &lt;code&gt;NEEDED.ELF.2&lt;/code&gt;) as this
is important for ELF/library graph information (as used by revdep-pax,
migrate-pax, etc.). Although Portage already does this, this is not part
of the PMS and as such other package managers might not do this (such as
Paludis).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updates on the profiles has been made to properly include multilib
related variables and other metadata. For some profiles, this went as
easy as expected (nice stacking), but other profiles have inheritance
troubles making it much harder to include the necessary information.
Although some talks have arised on the gentoo-dev mailinglist about
refactoring how Gentoo handles profiles, there hasn't been done much
more than just talking :-( But I'm sure we haven't heard the last of
this yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Documentation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blueness has added information on &lt;code&gt;EMULTRAMP&lt;/code&gt; in the kernel
configuration, especially noting to the user that it is needed for
Python support in Gentoo Hardened. It is also in the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Hardened/PaX_Quickstart"&gt;PaX
Quickstart&lt;/a&gt;
document, although this document is becoming a very large one and users
might overlook it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened, June 2014</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/06/gentoo-hardened-june-2014/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-06-15T21:28:00+02:00</published><updated>2014-06-15T21:28:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-06-15:/2014/06/gentoo-hardened-june-2014/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Friday the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt; project had its
monthly online meeting to talk about the progress within the various
tools, responsibilities and subprojects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;strong&gt;toolchain&lt;/strong&gt; part, Zorry mentioned that GCC 4.9 and 4.8.3 will
have SSP enabled by default. The hardened profiles will still have a
different …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Friday the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt; project had its
monthly online meeting to talk about the progress within the various
tools, responsibilities and subprojects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;strong&gt;toolchain&lt;/strong&gt; part, Zorry mentioned that GCC 4.9 and 4.8.3 will
have SSP enabled by default. The hardened profiles will still have a
different SSP setting than the default (so yes, there will still be
differences between the two) but this will help in securing the Gentoo
default installations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zorry is also working on upstreaming the PIE patches for GCC 4.10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next to the regular toolchain, blueness also mentioned his intentions to
launch a &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened_musl"&gt;Hardened
musl&lt;/a&gt; subproject
which will focus on the musl C library (rather than glibc or uclibc) and
hardening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;strong&gt;kernel&lt;/strong&gt; side, two recent kernel vulnerabilities in the vanilla
kernel Linux (pty race and privilege escalation through futex code)
painted the discussions on IRC recently. Some versions of the hardened
kernels are still available in the tree, but the more recent
(non-vulnerable) kernels have proven not to be as stable as we'd hoped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pty race vulnerability is possibly not applicable to hardened
kernels thanks to grSecurity, due to its protection to access the kernel
symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest kernels should not be used with KSTACKOVERFLOW on production
systems though; there are some issues reported with virtio network
interface support (on the guests) and ZFS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, on the &lt;strong&gt;Pax&lt;/strong&gt; support, the &lt;code&gt;install-xattr&lt;/code&gt; saga continues. The
new wrapper that blueness worked in dismissed some code to keep the
&lt;code&gt;PWD&lt;/code&gt; so the &lt;code&gt;$S&lt;/code&gt; directory knowledge was "lost". This is now fixed. All
that is left is to have the wrapper included and stabilized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;SELinux&lt;/strong&gt; side, it was the usual set of progress. Policy
stabilization and user land application and library stabilization. The
latter is waiting a bit because of the multilib support that's now being
integrated in the ebuilds as well (and thus has a larger set of
dependencies to go through) but no show-stoppers there. Also, the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux"&gt;SELinux documentation portal&lt;/a&gt; on
the wiki was briefly mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the &lt;a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2014-3215"&gt;policycoreutils
vulnerability&lt;/a&gt;
has been &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2014/05/dropping-sesandbox-support/"&gt;worked
around&lt;/a&gt; so it
is no longer applicable to us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the hardened &lt;strong&gt;profiles&lt;/strong&gt;, we had a nice discussion on enabling
capabilities support (and move towards capabilities instead of setuid
binaries), which klondike will try to tackle during the summer holidays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I didn't take notes during the meeting, this post might miss a few
(and I forgot to enable logging as well) but as Zorry sends out the
meeting logs anyway later, you can read up there ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category></entry><entry><title>Online hardened meeting of March</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2014/03/online-hardened-meeting-of-march/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-03-27T23:44:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-03-27T23:44:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2014-03-27:/2014/03/online-hardened-meeting-of-march/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm back from the depths of the unknown, so time to pick up my usual
write-up of the online Gentoo Hardened meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.9 is being worked on, and might be released by end of April (based
on the amount of open bugs). You can find the &lt;a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-4.9/changes.html"&gt;changes …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm back from the depths of the unknown, so time to pick up my usual
write-up of the online Gentoo Hardened meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.9 is being worked on, and might be released by end of April (based
on the amount of open bugs). You can find the &lt;a href="http://gcc.gnu.org/gcc-4.9/changes.html"&gt;changes
online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of GCC, pipacs asked if it is possible in the upcoming 4.8.2
ebuilds to disable the SSP protection for development purposes (such as
when you're developing GCC plugins that do similar protection measures
like SSP, but you don't want those to collide with each other). Recent
discussion on Gentoo development mailinglist had a consensus that the
SSP protection measures (&lt;code&gt;-fstack-protector&lt;/code&gt;) can be enabled by default,
but of course if people are developing new GCC plugins which might
interfere with SSP, disabling it is needed. One can use
&lt;code&gt;-fno-stack-protector&lt;/code&gt; for this, or build stuff with &lt;code&gt;-D__KERNEL__&lt;/code&gt; (as
for kernel builds the default SSP handling is disabled anyway, allowing
for kernel-specific implementations).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than those, there is no direct method to make SSP generally
unavailable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blueness is also working on &lt;a href="http://www.musl-libc.org/"&gt;musc-libc&lt;/a&gt; on
Gentoo, which would give a strong incentive for hardened embedded
devices. For desktops, well, don't hold your breath just yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel grSec/PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like kernel 3.13 will be Ubuntu's LTS kernel choice, which also
makes it the kernel version that grSecurity will put the long term
support for in. And with Linux 3.14 almost out, the grsec patches for it
are ready as well. Of the previous LTS kernels, 3.2 will probably finish
seeing grsec support somewhere this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The C wrapper (called &lt;strong&gt;install-xattr&lt;/strong&gt;) used to preserve xattr
information during Portage builds has not been integrated in Portage
yet, but the development should be finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the chat session, we also discussed the
&lt;a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/274859/"&gt;gold&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Gold"&gt;linker&lt;/a&gt; and how it might be used by
more and more packages (so not only by users that explicitly ask for
it). udev version 210 onwards is one example, but some others exist. But
other than its existence there's not much to say right here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The
&lt;a href="http://oss.tresys.com/projects/refpolicy/wiki/DownloadRelease"&gt;20140311&lt;/a&gt;
release of the reference policy is now in the Portage tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, prometheanfire caught a vulnerability
(&lt;a href="https://web.nvd.nist.gov/view/vuln/detail?vulnId=CVE-2014-1874"&gt;CVE-2014-1874&lt;/a&gt;)
in SELinux which has been fixed in the latest kernels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;System Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a few updates to the &lt;a href="http://dev.gentoo.org/~swift/docs/security_benchmarks/"&gt;gentoo hardening
guide&lt;/a&gt; in
XCCDF/OVAL format. Nothing major, and I still need to add in a lot of
other best practices (as well as automate the tests through OVAL), but I
do intend to update the files (at least the gentoo one and ssh as
OpenSSH 6 is now readily available) regularly in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few minor changes have been made to &lt;code&gt;hardened/uclibc&lt;/code&gt; to support
multilib, but other than that nothing has been done (nor needed to be
done) to our profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it for this months hardened meeting write-up. See you next time!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category></entry><entry><title>December hardened meeting</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/december-hardened-meeting/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-20T10:20:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-20T10:20:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-20:/2013/12/december-hardened-meeting/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening (UTC, that is) the members of the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt; project filled
the #gentoo-hardened IRC channel again - it was time for another online
follow-up meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few patches on the toolchain need to be created to mark SSP as
default, but this is just a minor workload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening (UTC, that is) the members of the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt; project filled
the #gentoo-hardened IRC channel again - it was time for another online
follow-up meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few patches on the toolchain need to be created to mark SSP as
default, but this is just a minor workload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And on the &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/p/address-sanitizer/"&gt;ASAN (Address
Sanitizer)&lt;/a&gt; debacle;
well... still the same. Doesn't work with PaX. I think there is a
standstill on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel, grsecurity/PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not clear yet what the next LTS (Long Term Stable) kernel will be
that the &lt;a href="https://grsecurity.net/"&gt;grSecurity&lt;/a&gt; team will support. This
depends on the Ubuntu LTS support, and as it is not clear which kernel
that distribution will use for LTS, the grSecurity team can also not say
what kernel it will be. (So please stop asking ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;grsecurity 3.0 is out, with the following commit message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;commit 4f48151d49f2697c3e2e108a50513a8d61fb150d
Author: Brad Spengler 
Date:   Sun Nov 24 17:47:14 2013 -0500

    Version bumped to 3.0 (we&amp;#39;d been on 2.9.1 for way too long and numerous
    features have been added since then)

    Introduce new atomic RBAC reload method, developed as part of sponsorship
    by EIG

    This is accompanied by an updated 3.0 gradm which will use the new reload
    method when -R is passed to gradm.  The old method will still be available
    via gradm -r (which is what a 2.9.1 gradm will continue to use).

    The new RBAC reload method is atomic in the sense that at no point in the
    reload process will the system not be covered by a coherent full policy.
    In contrast to previous reload behavior, it also preserves inherited subjects
    and special roles.

    The old RBAC reload method has also been made atomic.  Both methods have
    been updated to perform role_allowed_ip checks only against the IP tagged
    to the task at the time its role was first applied or changed.  This resolves
    long-standing usability problems with the use of role_allowed_ip and matches
    the policies created by learning.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new version requires the use of &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;=gradm-3.0&lt;/code&gt;. Some hardened-sources
packages already contain the 3.0 patchset (currently in testing). In a
few days, a final hardened-sources with a 2.9.1 patchset will be
stabilized; after that, only 3.0 patchset sources will be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another open issue (for a while) is the &lt;code&gt;install.py&lt;/code&gt; wrapper used to
properly pax-mark binaries during package building (instead of
post-merge changes). Although it works functionally well, it has serious
performance regressions when hundreds of files need to be merged and
marked. For each file, the Python interpreter is launched again, making
this a very time-consuming effort. Blueness is currently working on a
C-based wrapper which should load much faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The live repository of the Gentoo Hardened policies is well up to date
with the latest evolutions of the reference policy. If you want to use
these, use the &lt;code&gt;-9999&lt;/code&gt; ebuilds for the SELinux policy packages. This can
be accomplished with the following line in
&lt;path&gt;package.accept_keywords&lt;/path&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;sec-policy/* **
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, revision 5 of the SELinux policies has been pushed to the tree
(currently in testing). This one also contains a few required changes to
the policy for the new userspace utilities which are also now available
in the tree. An important update on the new userspace utilities is that
they contain many of the patches we needed in Gentoo and of course the
necessary updates, patches and improvements all-round. Once the SELinux
policies are stabilized, the userspace utilities will be too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few successful runs with SELinux on ARM devices, we will most
likely be tagging our SELinux packages (policies and userspace
utilities) as &lt;code&gt;~arm&lt;/code&gt;. Documentation will need to be updated on this as
well, not only to cater for the additional keyword, but also because of
one (perhaps a few) changes needed, like fixing the SELinux binary
policy (as most ARM systems come with a lower kernel version).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SELinux support on ZFS also seems to work well, with the last patches in
(thanks to prometheanfire).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final aspect, the SELinux eclass in Gentoo Linux now also supports
fetching the latest policy sources from git through HTTP (instead of
git/ssh).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much to discuss here; IMA/EVM and kernel signing all work well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next few days/weeks, I will be working on a &lt;a href="http://dev.gentoo.org/~swift/docs/security_benchmarks/gentoo.html"&gt;Gentoo Security
Benchmark&lt;/a&gt;
as a sort-of follow-up (improvement) of the current &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/security/"&gt;Gentoo Security
Handbook&lt;/a&gt;, now using SCAP
methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been discussion about supporting a &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/security/"&gt;hardened desktop
profile&lt;/a&gt; in Gentoo again. This
does come with the nasty surprise that these profiles don't play well
together, so a solution needs to be brought in place. This could be a
"hardened desktop" profile separate from the gentoo desktop one (and as
such manually synchronized), or an improved approach on profile
stacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One idea was to support stacking with a maximum depth, allowing to use
changes made by a profile without inheriting the changes that that
profile inherited to a certain extend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another idea is to use a more dependency-based syntax (similar to OpenRC
dependency system for init scripts), which not only allows for proper
stacking and the necessary flexibility, but also improves readability:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;before {
  hardened/linux/amd64
}
after {
  default/linux/amd64
}
depends {
  targets/desktop/gnome
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next few months will be interesting to see how this will evolve ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Documentation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All our documents are on the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt;, so if you
notice gaps or see possibilities for improvement - by all means, do
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all a good session. Thanks for the good work guys!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="online"></category></entry><entry><title>November online hardened meeting</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/12/november-online-hardened-meeting/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-11T12:12:00+01:00</published><updated>2013-12-11T12:12:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-12-11:/2013/12/november-online-hardened-meeting/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Later than usual, as I wasn't able to make the meeting myself (thus had
to wait for the meeting logs in order to draft up this summary), so here
it is. The next meeting is scheduled for next week, btw ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 4.8.2 ebuild for GCC is available …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Later than usual, as I wasn't able to make the meeting myself (thus had
to wait for the meeting logs in order to draft up this summary), so here
it is. The next meeting is scheduled for next week, btw ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 4.8.2 ebuild for GCC is available in the tree, currently still
masked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel and grSecurity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grSecurity project has made the patches for the 3.12 kernel
available; a hardened 3.12 kernel is available in the
&lt;code&gt;hardened-development&lt;/code&gt; overlay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew is working on &lt;a href="https://github.com/zfsonlinux/zfs/pull/1835"&gt;ZFSonLinux and
SELinux&lt;/a&gt; support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew and Steev have been working on SELinux and ARM support. It seems
to work, but kernel versions matter greatly. We might want to open up
ARM keywords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's about it. As blueness wasn't there as well, the topics were
discussed quite fast. The full logs can be found &lt;a href="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.hardened/6117"&gt;on the gentoo-hardened
mailinglist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="online"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened meeting 201310</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/10/gentoo-hardened-meeting-201310/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-10-24T23:25:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-10-24T23:25:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-10-24:/2013/10/gentoo-hardened-meeting-201310/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We gathered online again to talk about the progress, changes and other
stuff related to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Developer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcomed Zero_Chaos as a new addition to our team. Big welcome, with
the usual IRC kick in between, ensued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.8.x is unmasked and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We gathered online again to talk about the progress, changes and other
stuff related to the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Developer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcomed Zero_Chaos as a new addition to our team. Big welcome, with
the usual IRC kick in between, ensued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.8.x is unmasked and ready for testing. The ASAN problem however is
not resolved and it doesn't look like upstream wants to provide the fix
for this. As a result, if you want to use ASAN, you will need to disable
UDEREF in the kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A difficult problem here is that, if a user forgets to disable UDEREF,
then building with ASAN will fail. If he disabled UDEREF and uses ASAN,
then booting into a UDEREF enabled kernel will fail. If he starts
building with ASAN on UDEREF kernels, things will break. Its ugly, and
unless the ASAN code is changed to support other technologies using the
address space layout information, it will remain mutually exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, we'll properly document the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.9 will end its stage1 development phase on November 21st.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uclibc stages are currently built with GCC-4.7.3-r1, except for the
MIPS architectures which use GCC 4.8.1-r1.&lt;br&gt;
The stages are built once every two months, give or take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel grSec/PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standard maintenance, such as keeping up with upstream changes, has
taken place. The XATTR problems with the &lt;strong&gt;install&lt;/strong&gt; binary/phase has
not been resolved yet due to time constraints. First focus will be on
writing the C-based wrapper to see if this significantly speeds things
up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;USE=pax_kernel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is ambiguity of the meaning or use of the &lt;code&gt;pax_kernel&lt;/code&gt; USE flag.
It seems to be used for multiple, exclusive things, like limiting builds
on PaX kernels or limiting run-time behavior on PaX kernels. To build
Gentoo images, developers need to set &lt;code&gt;pax_kernel&lt;/code&gt; on some packages and
disable it on others in order for the image to build properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;@blueness&amp;gt; USE=pax_kernel in the case of userland should apply patches etc, that fix the code
            so that it won&amp;#39;t trip pax protection eg mprotect
&amp;lt;@blueness&amp;gt; in the case of kernel modules, it can&amp;#39;t mean that obviously!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the mentioned problems is that some ebuilds only enable pax
markings when &lt;code&gt;pax_kernel&lt;/code&gt; is set. However, that shouldn't be done
conditionally. PaX markings can be done even without a PaX kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zero_Chaos (new developers always have the necessary energy) will try
to update ebuilds where applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux and System Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing worth mentioning here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many users were using hardened profiles on the desktop. In the past, we
had the desktop/hardened profiles removed (referring users to the
regular hardened profiles and asking them to update their system with
the USE flags (and other settings) they want for their desktop.
Apparently, this is giving some problems for some users, so the idea is
to reinstate the desktop/hardened profiles where the hardened settings
overrule the desktop settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we should take care of tackling the issues we had in the past
(which is the reason why we removed the profiles in the first place). It
is recommended that we discuss this outside the IRC meeting to make sure
we don't reintroduce the issues again while using a flexible approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's it. A big thanks to the developers, contributors and thousands of
users!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="online"></category></entry><entry><title>Aaaand we're back - hardened monthly meeting</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/09/aaaand-were-back-hardened-monthly-meeting/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-09-26T22:22:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-09-26T22:22:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-09-26:/2013/09/aaaand-were-back-hardened-monthly-meeting/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It almost feels like we had our monthly online meeting just a week ago.
Below a small write-up of the highlights. If you want to know the gory
details, just wait a few hours/days until the IRC logs are sent out ;-)
Now remember, the project does more than what …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It almost feels like we had our monthly online meeting just a week ago.
Below a small write-up of the highlights. If you want to know the gory
details, just wait a few hours/days until the IRC logs are sent out ;-)
Now remember, the project does more than what the highlights tell you -
there is lots of maintenance done "under the hood", allowing everyone to
keep using the various
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Hardened/Introduction_to_Hardened_Gentoo"&gt;technologies&lt;/a&gt;
supported through our project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per a discussion on the Gentoo development mailinglist, GCC 4.8 will
most likely have SSP enabled as default. Gentoo Hardened will still
enable full SSP (&lt;code&gt;-fstack-protector-all&lt;/code&gt;) whereas Gentoo by default will
probably work with &lt;code&gt;-fstack-protector&lt;/code&gt;). We will also still provide GCC
specifications that disable stack protection completely (the
&lt;code&gt;hardened-nossp&lt;/code&gt; specs) for when developers or users need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel and grsec/PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blueness informed us about one issue with XATTR_PAX implementation,
being the &lt;code&gt;install.py&lt;/code&gt; wrapper that we need in order to set the right
attributes as early as possible. The problem is that it is very slow (as
it is invoked over and over again, so the overhead of it being an
interpreted script becomes huge). A solution for this still has to be
defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some ideas are to use a compiled version, but other possible solutions
such as hooking into Portage directly or using lists have been suggested
as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing big - standard maintenance stuff, such as pushing our own
patches upstream for others to benefit (and hopefully have the master
projects include the patches so we don't need to maintain them
ourselves). Also, revision 3 of the 2.20130424 policies are now in the
tree (\~arch'ed for now).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;System Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within Gentoo, we have a couple of SCAP scanners/software available,
such as open-scap and ovaldi. Recently, openscap-9999 is made available
(allowing users to directly use the latest openscap release) which is
used to validate and evaluate security benchmarks I am developing for
Gentoo and related services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next to the SCAP-related developments, a
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Signed_kernel_module_support"&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; has
been put on the Gentoo wiki about using signed kernel modules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hardened profiles have been updated to use EAPI-5 so we can benefit
from its features, such as improved multilib support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Documentation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before, I'm working a bit on a &lt;a href="http://dev.gentoo.org/~swift/docs/security_benchmarks/"&gt;Gentoo Security
Benchmark&lt;/a&gt; that
can be used with SCAP software. The sources are in the
&lt;a href="http://git.overlays.gentoo.org/gitweb/?p=proj/hardened-docs.git;a=tree;f=xml/SCAP;hb=HEAD"&gt;hardened-docs&lt;/a&gt;
repository for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, most/all hardened documentation is moved from the
(developer-editable only) &lt;code&gt;Project:&lt;/code&gt; namespace to the general one,
allowing users and contributors to help us with the documents as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened progress report</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/08/gentoo-hardened-progress-report/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-29T20:27:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-08-29T20:27:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-08-29:/2013/08/gentoo-hardened-progress-report/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, we had our monthly online meeting to discuss the progress amongst
the various Gentoo Hardened projects. As usual, here is a small
write-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead election&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As every year, we also reviewed the current project leads. No surprises
here, everybody is happy with the current leads so they are re-elected …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, we had our monthly online meeting to discuss the progress amongst
the various Gentoo Hardened projects. As usual, here is a small
write-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lead election&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As every year, we also reviewed the current project leads. No surprises
here, everybody is happy with the current leads so they are re-elected
for another term. We did have two candidates for the lead position, but
even the other candidate vote for Zorry - so we had a unanimous vote ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC version 4.8.1 will be unmasked pretty soon, and the &lt;code&gt;hardenedno*&lt;/code&gt;
specs on it will work. However, there is still no progress on the asan
(Address Sanitizer) support together with UDEREF. As mentioned in a
previous post, UDEREF "reduces" the address space a bit which doesn't
play well with asan. Still, it isn't inevitable, since PowerPC also has
a reduced address space and so does Windows. So perhaps we can use the
same model for UDEREF enabled kernels? We'll send the suggestion and the
already-existing fixes upstream and hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In GCC 4.8.1, the &lt;code&gt;-fstack-check&lt;/code&gt; option might be enabled by default,
but the question is for which architectures and platforms. We know a few
packages, such as &lt;em&gt;ffmpeg&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;libav&lt;/em&gt; have problems with it. In those
cases, the ebuild will be modified to use &lt;code&gt;-fno-stack-check&lt;/code&gt; (if
hardened). We opt to enable it for all as we don't really expect much
(if any) breakage that can't be dealt with swiftly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support for hardened uClibc is still going steadily. Blueness is heating
his room a bit with it, seeing that mips32r2 takes about 2 weeks to
build hardened and vanilla stages - he is using an Ubiquity router
station for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel and Grsecurity/PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to some boot freezes, as explained in bugs
&lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/482010"&gt;482010&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://bugs.gentoo.org/481790"&gt;481790&lt;/a&gt;, we don't have a stable 3.10.x
kernel yet. However, most of the issues should be resolved and we're
waiting for confirmation, so we can be looking at a stable 3.10.x kernel
soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 3.10 kernel will probably not be a long-term support kernel for PaX
and Grsecurity - such LTS kernel will be picked next year, most likely
the same kernel version that Ubuntu LTS settles on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small update on &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt; has been made that updates &lt;strong&gt;rlpkg&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;selocal&lt;/strong&gt;. Other than that, our policies are in nice shape. A new
revision will be pushed to the tree soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Integrity side, recent kernels support custom IMA policies
(again) so our documentation is accurate again. Next to IMA/EVM, I'll be
working on documentation for cryptographically signed kernel module
support soon as well as SCAP-based security baselines for Gentoo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blueness added a MUSL-based Gentoo profile (&lt;code&gt;hardened/linux/musl&lt;/code&gt;). Musl
is an even more slim libc and its profile is extremely experimental for
now. The profile structure is still a bit off though, a reorganization
will be suggested soon so that the profile inheritance is clear and
predictable, starting off with a non-hardened one
(&lt;code&gt;default/linux/{uclibc,musl}&lt;/code&gt;) and then a hardened specific one that
inherits from the default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Documentation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Hardened"&gt;Gentoo Hardened
project&lt;/a&gt; now has its main
project page on the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;, and all
(most) documentation is moved to there as well for the Gentoo Hardened
subprojects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also explained to the folks that I have authored a book on SELinux
System Administration (for Packt Publishing), which was why I was less
active the last few months. However, that is now done so I'm back on
track. More information about the book follows later on my blog ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as usual, klondike has been tweeting the entire meeting through our
&lt;code&gt;@GentooHardened&lt;/code&gt; twitter account ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="minutes"></category><category term="progress_report"></category><category term="report"></category></entry><entry><title>And now, 31 days later...</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/08/and-now-31-days-later/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-01T22:43:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-08-01T22:43:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-08-01:/2013/08/and-now-31-days-later/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;... the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened"&gt;Gentoo Hardened&lt;/a&gt; team
had its monthly online meeting again ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the agenda were the usual suspects, such as the &lt;em&gt;toolchain&lt;/em&gt;. In this
category, Zorry mentioned that he has a fix for GCC 4.8.1 for the
&lt;code&gt;hardenedno*&lt;/code&gt; and vanilla &lt;code&gt;gcc-config&lt;/code&gt; options which will be added to
the tree …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;... the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened"&gt;Gentoo Hardened&lt;/a&gt; team
had its monthly online meeting again ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the agenda were the usual suspects, such as the &lt;em&gt;toolchain&lt;/em&gt;. In this
category, Zorry mentioned that he has a fix for GCC 4.8.1 for the
&lt;code&gt;hardenedno*&lt;/code&gt; and vanilla &lt;code&gt;gcc-config&lt;/code&gt; options which will be added to
the tree after some more testing. The problem is that with GCC 4.8,
certain settings need to be set sooner than before (in the code path),
which is what the fix focuses on. The ASAN issue is still unresolved,
but otherwise GCC 4.8 is working fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;, the policycoreutils package has been bumped to include
support for &lt;code&gt;mcstrans&lt;/code&gt;, a translation daemon that visualizes humanly
readable strings instead of the standard sensitivity/category sets in
case of MCS/MLS policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding documentation, the wiki team (most notably a3li) is working
hard to support project pages on the &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo
Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. Once we can, we will be moving our
project page with all related documentation to the wiki, allowing for
easier documentation development and a more modern look. To support
this, an XML-to-wiki stylesheet is available that translates ProjectXML
and GuideXML to the wiki language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the meeting, we also mentioned the stabilization policy (or at
least, no-longer-stabilization) of the vanilla sources (plain kernel.org
Linux kernel sources). This doesn't immediately effect the hardened
project, but is important to know nonetheless, especially for users of
hardened technologies that are in the main kernel already (like SELinux
or IMA/EVM) as they have to be aware to either use the latest
(regardless of the keywords in use) or switch to gentoo-sources or
(preferably) hardened-sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For uclibc support, the stages will be provided every 2 months rather
than every month as this is a resource-intensive process that isn't
fully automated yet (except for amd64 and x86 which are automated).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on PaX and grSecurity support, the XATTR patch for tmpfs is now
in the kernel, and the problem about loosing PaX markings during
installation is fixed as Portage (2.1.12.9 and higher) now preserves the
flags during installation (a wrapper on &lt;code&gt;install&lt;/code&gt; is used that preserves
&lt;code&gt;usr.pax.flags&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="grsecurity"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="irl"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="minutes"></category><category term="pax"></category><category term="project"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="toolchain"></category></entry><entry><title>Hardening is our business... new monthly report ;-)</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/06/hardening-is-our-business-new-monthly-report/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-27T23:03:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-06-27T23:03:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-06-27:/2013/06/hardening-is-our-business-new-monthly-report/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're back with another report on the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt; project. Please excuse
my brevity, as you've noticed I'm not that active (yet) due to work on
an external project - I'll be back mid-July though. I promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt; side, GCC 4.8.1 is in the tree and has …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We're back with another report on the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt; project. Please excuse
my brevity, as you've noticed I'm not that active (yet) due to work on
an external project - I'll be back mid-July though. I promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt; side, GCC 4.8.1 is in the tree and has the GCC plugin
header fix. Also, for IA64 and ARM, the necessary PIE patches are
available as well to make this work on those architectures too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For uclibc, blueness is continuing the necessary support for everything
so far. He has also added mips64 n32 uclibc because new router boards
use this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his time, blueness is also playing with a uclibc-powered desktop and
another C library called &lt;a href="http://www.musl-libc.org/"&gt;musl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;em&gt;Kernel&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;grSecurity&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;PaX&lt;/em&gt; side, we are having troubles
with the 3.8+ kernels and UEFI machines when the machines have ltitle
memory available (for instance when it is limited with &lt;code&gt;mem=&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PaX extended attribute support is still on-going, mainly because we
need to have support for the &lt;code&gt;user.pax&lt;/code&gt; attributes in common tools like
&lt;strong&gt;install&lt;/strong&gt;, which is heavily used in Gentoo's ebuilds. The merge phase,
where the data is moved from the image location to the root, has been
supporting xattr moves for a while thanks to zmedico and arfrever, but
other installation phases still needed to be fixed or worked around. We
tried with a common patch on this, but there was little interest in this
approach, so we settled with a wrapper around &lt;strong&gt;install&lt;/strong&gt; inside of
Portage. This will be soon released and we again have full end-to-end
xattr pax flag support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt; support, the latest userland and policy releases have
been stabilized in the Gentoo tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;, blueness added a musl subprofile for testing of the
musl C library.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="progress"></category></entry><entry><title>Gentoo Hardened spring notes</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/05/gentoo-hardened-spring-notes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-16T22:54:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-05-16T22:54:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-05-16:/2013/05/gentoo-hardened-spring-notes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We got back together on the &lt;code&gt;#gentoo-hardened&lt;/code&gt; chat channel to discuss
the progress of &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt;, so it's time for
another write-up of what was said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.8.1 will be out soon, although nothing major has occurred with it
since the last meeting. There is a plugin …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We got back together on the &lt;code&gt;#gentoo-hardened&lt;/code&gt; chat channel to discuss
the progress of &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened"&gt;Gentoo
Hardened&lt;/a&gt;, so it's time for
another write-up of what was said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GCC 4.8.1 will be out soon, although nothing major has occurred with it
since the last meeting. There is a plugin header install problem in 4.8
and its not certain that the (trivial) fix is in 4.8.1, but it certainly
is inside Gentoo's release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blueness is also (still, and hopefully for a long time ;-) maintaining
the uclibc hardened related toolchain aspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel and grSecurity/PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The further progress on the XATTR_PAX migration was put on a lower
level the past few weeks due to busy, busy... very busy weeks (but this
was announced and known in advance). We still need to do XATTR copying
in &lt;em&gt;install&lt;/em&gt; for packages that do pax markings before &lt;em&gt;src_install()&lt;/em&gt;
and include the &lt;code&gt;user.pax&lt;/code&gt; XATTR patch in the gentoo-sources kernel.
This will silence the errors for non-hardened users and fix the loss of
XATTR markings for those packages that do pax-mark before install.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The set then needs to be documented further and tested on vanilla and
hardened systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zorry asked if a separate script can be provided for those ebuilds that
directly call &lt;strong&gt;paxctl&lt;/strong&gt;. These ebuilds might want to switch to the
eclass, but if they need to call &lt;strong&gt;paxctl&lt;/strong&gt; or similar directly (for
instance because the result is immediately used for further building), a
separate script or tool should be made available. Blueness will look
into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On &lt;code&gt;hardened-sources&lt;/code&gt;, we are now with stable 2.6.32-r160, 3.2.42-r1 and
3.8.6 due to some vulnerabilities in earlier versions (in networking
code). There is still some bug (nfs-related) that is fixed in 3.2.44 so
that part might need a bump as well soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The
&lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2013/04/introducing-selocal-for-small-selinux-policy-enhancements/"&gt;selocal&lt;/a&gt;
command is now available for Gentoo SELinux users, allowing them to
easily enhance the policy without having to maintain their own SELinux
policy modules (the script is a wrapper that does all that).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setools package now also uses the &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2013/04/sloting-the-old-swig-1/"&gt;SLOT'ed
swig&lt;/a&gt;, so no more
dependency breakage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On SELinux userspace and policy, both have seen a new release last
month, and both are already in the Gentoo portage tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the SELinux policy ebuilds now also call
&lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2013/05/overriding-the-default-selinux-policies/"&gt;epatch_user&lt;/a&gt;
so users can customize the policies even further without having to copy
ebuilds to their overlay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that &lt;strong&gt;tar&lt;/strong&gt; supports XATTR well, we might want to look into SELinux
stages again. Jmbsvicetto did some work on that, but the builds failed
during stage1. We'll look into that later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing much to say, we're waiting a bit until the patches proposed by
the IMA team are merged in the main kernel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two no-multilib fixes have been applied to the
&lt;code&gt;hardened/amd64/no-multilib&lt;/code&gt; profiles. One was a QA issue and quickly
resolved, the other is due to the profile stacking within Gentoo
profiles, where we missed a profile and thus were missing a few masks
defined in that (missed) profile. But including the profile creates a
lot of duplicates again, so we are going to copy the masks across until
the duplicates are resolved in the other profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blueness will also clean up the experimental &lt;code&gt;13.0&lt;/code&gt; directory since all
hardened profiles now follow 13.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Docs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest changes on SELinux have been added to the Gentoo SELinux
handbook. Also, I've been slowly (but surely) adding topics to the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux/Tutorials"&gt;SELinux tutorials
listing&lt;/a&gt; on the Gentoo
wiki.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grSecurity 2 document is very much out of date, blueness hopes to
put some time in fixing that soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that's about it for the short write-up. Zorry will surely post the
log later on the appropriate channels. Good work done (again) by all
team members!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="monthly"></category><category term="online"></category></entry><entry><title>Public support channels: irc</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/05/public-support-channels-irc/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-16T03:50:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-05-16T03:50:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-05-16:/2013/05/public-support-channels-irc/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2012/12/why-would-paid-for-support-be-better/"&gt;said
it&lt;/a&gt;
before - support channels for free software are often (imo) superior to
the commercial support that you might get with vendors. And although
those vendors often try to use "modern" techniques, I fail to see why
the old, but proven/stable methods would be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the "Chat …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've &lt;a href="http://blog.siphos.be/2012/12/why-would-paid-for-support-be-better/"&gt;said
it&lt;/a&gt;
before - support channels for free software are often (imo) superior to
the commercial support that you might get with vendors. And although
those vendors often try to use "modern" techniques, I fail to see why
the old, but proven/stable methods would be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the "Chat with Support" feature that many vendors have on their
site. Often, these services use a webbrowser, AJAX-driven method for
talking with support engineers. The problem with this that I see is that
it is difficult to keep track of the feedback you got over time (unless
you manually copy/paste the information), and again that it isn't
public. With free software communities, we still often redirect such
"online" support requests to IRC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Internet Relay Chat&lt;/em&gt; has been around for ages
(&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRC"&gt;1988&lt;/a&gt; according to wikipedia) and
still quite active. Gentoo has all of its support channels on the
&lt;a href="http://www.freenode.net"&gt;freenode&lt;/a&gt; IRC network: a community-driven,
active &lt;code&gt;#gentoo&lt;/code&gt; channel with often crosses the 1000 users, a
&lt;code&gt;#gentoo-dev&lt;/code&gt; development-related channel where many developers
communicate, the &lt;code&gt;#gentoo-hardened&lt;/code&gt; channel for all questions and
support regarding Gentoo Hardened specifics, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using IRC has many advantages. One is that logs can be kept (either
individually or by the project itself) that can be queried later by the
people who want to provide support (to see if questions have already
been popping up, see what the common questions are for the last few
days, etc.) or get support (to see if their question was already
answered in the past). Of course, these logs can be made public through
web interfaces quite easily. For users, such log functionality is
offered through the IRC client. Another very simple, yet interesting
feature is &lt;em&gt;highlighting&lt;/em&gt;: give the set of terms for which you want to
be notified (usually through a highlight and a specific notification in
the client), making it easier to be on multiple channels without having
to constantly follow-up on all discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another advantage is that there is such a thing like "bots". Most Gentoo
related channels do not allow active bots on the channels except for the
project-approved ones (such as &lt;em&gt;willikens&lt;/em&gt;). These bots can provide
project-specific help to users and developers alike:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give one-line information about bugs reported on bugzilla (id,
    assignee, status, but also the URL where the user/developer can view
    the bug etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Give meta information about a package (maintainer, herd, etc.), herd
    (members), GLSA details, dependency information, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow users to query if a developer is
    &lt;a href="https://dev.gentoo.org/devaway/"&gt;away&lt;/a&gt; or not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create notes (messages) for users that are not online yet but for
    which you know they come online later (and know their nickname or
    registered username)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notify when commits are made, or when tweets are sent that match a
    particular expression, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the IRC protocol has many features that are very
interesting to use in free software communities as well. You can still
do private chats (when potentially confidential data is exchanged) for
instance, or even exchange files (although that is less common to use in
free software communities). There is also still some hierarchy in case
of abuse (channel operators can remove users from the chat or even ban
them for a while) and one can even quiet a channel when for instance
online team meetings are held (although using a different channel for
that might be an alternative).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRC also has the advantage that connecting to the IRC channels has a
very low requirement (software-wise): one can use console-only chat
clients (in case users cannot get their graphical environment to work -
example is irssi) or even &lt;a href="http://webchat.freenode.net/"&gt;webbrowser&lt;/a&gt;
based ones (if one wants to chat from other systems). Even smartphones
have good IRC applications, like &lt;a href="http://www.andchat.net/"&gt;AndChat&lt;/a&gt; for
Android.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IRC is also distributed: an IRC network consists of many interconnected
servers who pass on all IRC traffic. If one node goes down, users can
access a different node and continue. That makes IRC quite
high-available. IRC network operators do need to try and keep the
network from splitting ("netsplit") which occurs when one part of the
distributed network gets segregated from the other part and thus two
"independent" IRC networks are formed. When that occurs, IRC operators
will try to join them back as fast as possible. I'm not going to explain
the details on this - it suffices to understand that IRC is a
distributed manner and thus often much more available than the "support
chat" sites that vendors provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So although IRC looks archaic, it is a very good match for support
channel requirements.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Free-Software"></category><category term="chat"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="support"></category></entry><entry><title>Another Gentoo Hardened month has passed</title><link href="https://blog.siphos.be/2013/04/another-gentoo-hardened-month-has-passed/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-18T23:36:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-04-18T23:36:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-04-18:/2013/04/another-gentoo-hardened-month-has-passed/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another month has passed, so time to mention again what we have all been
doing lately ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version 4.8 of GCC is available in the tree, but currently masked. The
package contains a fix needed to build hardened-sources, and a fix for
the asan (address sanitizer).
&lt;a href="http://www.internetnews.com/blog/skerner/open-source-gcc-4.8-compiler-including-address-sanitizer-security.html"&gt;asan&lt;/a&gt;
support in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another month has passed, so time to mention again what we have all been
doing lately ;-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Toolchain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Version 4.8 of GCC is available in the tree, but currently masked. The
package contains a fix needed to build hardened-sources, and a fix for
the asan (address sanitizer).
&lt;a href="http://www.internetnews.com/blog/skerner/open-source-gcc-4.8-compiler-including-address-sanitizer-security.html"&gt;asan&lt;/a&gt;
support in GCC 4.8 might be seen as an improvement security-wise, but it
is yet unclear if it is an integral part of GCC or could be disabled
with a configure flag. Apparently, asan "makes building gcc 4.8 crazy".
Seeing that it comes from Google, and building Google Chromium is also
crazy, I start seeing a pattern here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it turns out that PaX/grSec and asan do not get along yet (ASAN
assumes/uses hardcoded userland address space size values, which breaks
when UDEREF is set as it pitches a bit from the size):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;ERROR: AddressSanitizer failed to allocate 0x20000001000 (2199023259648) bytes at address 0x0ffffffff000
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that this is hardcoded in the resulting binaries, it isn't
sufficient to change the size value from 47 bits to 46 bits as hardened
systems can very well boot a kernel with and another kernel without
UDEREF, causing the binaries to fail on the other kernel. Instead, a
proper method would be to dynamically check the size of a userland
address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, GCC 4.8 also brings along some nice enhancements and features.
uclibc profiles work just fine with GCC 4.8, including armv7a and
mips/mipsel. The latter is especially nice to hear, since mips used to
require significant effort with previous GCCs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kernel and grSecurity/PaX&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recent kernels have now been stabilized to stay close to the
grSecurity/PaX upstream developments. The most recent stable kernel now
is hardened-sources-3.8.3. Others still available are hardened-sources
versions 3.2.40-r1 and 2.6.32-r156.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The support for XATTR_PAX is still progressing, but a few issues have
come up. One is that non-hardened systems are seeing warnings about
&lt;strong&gt;pax-mark&lt;/strong&gt; not being able to set the XATTR_PAX on tmpfs since vanilla
kernels do not have the patch to support &lt;code&gt;user.*&lt;/code&gt; extended attribute
namespaces for tmpfs. A second issue is that the &lt;strong&gt;install&lt;/strong&gt;
application, as provided by &lt;code&gt;coreutils&lt;/code&gt;, does not copy extended
attributes. This has impact on ebuilds where pax markings are done
before the install phase of a package. But only doing pax markings after
the install phase isn't sufficient either, since sometimes we need the
binaries to be marked already for test phases or even in the compile
phase. So this is still something on the near horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most likely the necessary tools will be patched to include extended
attributes on copy operations. However, we need to take care only to
copy over those attributes that make sense: &lt;code&gt;user.pax&lt;/code&gt; does, but
security ones like &lt;code&gt;security.evm&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;security.selinux&lt;/code&gt; shouldn't as
those are either recomputed when needed, or governed through policy. The
idea is that USE="pax_kernel" will enable the above on &lt;code&gt;coreutils&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SELinux&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SELinux support in Gentoo has seen a fair share of updates on the
userland utilities (like policycoreutils, setools, libselinux and such).
Most of these have already made the stable tree or are close to be
bumped to stable. The SELinux policy also has been updated a lot: most
changes can be tracked through bugzilla, looking for the
&lt;code&gt;sec-policy r13&lt;/code&gt; whiteboard. The changes can be applied to the system
immediately if you use the live ebuilds (like &lt;code&gt;selinux-base-9999&lt;/code&gt;), but
I'm planning on releasing revision 13 of our policy set soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;System Integrity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the "early adopter" problems we've noticed on Gentoo Hardened
have been integrated in the repositories upstream and are slowly
progressing towards the main Linux kernel tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Profiles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All hardened profiles have been moved to the 13.0 base. Some people
frowned when they noticed that the uclibc profiles do not inherit from
any architecture-related profile. This is however with reason: the
architecture profiles are (amongst other reasons) focusing on the glibc
specifics of the architecture. Since the profile intended here is for
uclibc, those changes are not needed (nor wanted). Hence, these are
collapsed in a single profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Documentation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For SELinux, the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/selinux/selinux-handbook.xml"&gt;SELinux
handbook&lt;/a&gt;
now includes information about USE="unconfined" as well as the
&lt;code&gt;selinux_gentoo&lt;/code&gt; init script as provided by &lt;code&gt;policycoreutils&lt;/code&gt;. Users who
are already running with SELinux enabled can just look at the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/selinux/selinux-handbook.xml?part=2&amp;amp;chap=7"&gt;Change
History&lt;/a&gt;
to see which changes affect them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A set of &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/SELinux/Tutorials"&gt;tutorials&lt;/a&gt;
(which I've blogged about earlier as well) have been put online at the
&lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org"&gt;Gentoo Wiki&lt;/a&gt;. Next to the SELinux tutorials,
an article pertaining to &lt;a href="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/AIDE"&gt;AIDE&lt;/a&gt; has
been added as well as it fits nicely within the principles/concepts of
the &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/integrity/index.xml"&gt;System
Integrity&lt;/a&gt;
subproject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't do it already, start following
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/GentooHardened"&gt;@GentooHardened&lt;/a&gt; ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="asan"></category><category term="gcc"></category><category term="Gentoo"></category><category term="grsecurity"></category><category term="hardened"></category><category term="integrity"></category><category term="irc"></category><category term="meeting"></category><category term="pax"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="uderef"></category></entry></feed>