<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - tablet</title><link href="http://blog.siphos.be/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.siphos.be/tag/tablet/feed/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.siphos.be/</id><updated>2013-08-15T20:58:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Today was a productive day</title><link href="http://blog.siphos.be/2013/08/today-was-a-productive-day/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-15T20:58:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-08-15T20:58:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-08-15:/2013/08/today-was-a-productive-day/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fixed 14 bugs today, with a few more pending (those for packages only
get marked as FIXED if it is moved to the stable state). One of the
changes is the
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=1&amp;amp;chap=10#grub2"&gt;GRUB2&lt;/a&gt;
support in the Gentoo Handbook (yes, finally, sorry about that). That
opens up the road for the stabilization …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fixed 14 bugs today, with a few more pending (those for packages only
get marked as FIXED if it is moved to the stable state). One of the
changes is the
&lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=1&amp;amp;chap=10#grub2"&gt;GRUB2&lt;/a&gt;
support in the Gentoo Handbook (yes, finally, sorry about that). That
opens up the road for the stabilization of GRUB2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also added a dozen fixes to the Gentoo SELinux policy repository and
sent a few others upstream that have been lingering in our policy for
quite some time. But the highlight for me was that I got to play with my
Wacom Bamboo pen and touch which, I must say, integrated easily with my
system. I only had to build the &lt;code&gt;wacom.ko&lt;/code&gt; kernel module and install the
&lt;code&gt;xf86-input-wacom&lt;/code&gt; package, but that's all - no reboot needed. Even GIMP
immediately detected the new device and I can start drawing and fixing
pictures more easily (I work on pictures often and a mouse just isn't
that obvious).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the huge benefits is that the pressure you put on the drawing pad
is related (and configurable) to a drawing function in GIMP, something
you don't have with mice. For instance, if you need to Dodge or Burn on
layers, you don't need to continuously switch between the amount - just
adjust the pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="gimp"></category><category term="tablet"></category><category term="wacom"></category></entry><entry><title>Some things sound more scary than they are</title><link href="http://blog.siphos.be/2013/08/some-things-sound-more-scary-than-they-are/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-08-15T10:02:00+02:00</published><updated>2013-08-15T10:02:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Sven Vermeulen</name></author><id>tag:blog.siphos.be,2013-08-15:/2013/08/some-things-sound-more-scary-than-they-are/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I finally got to the next thing on my &lt;em&gt;Want to do this
year&lt;/em&gt; list: put a new android
(&lt;a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.org/"&gt;Cyanogenmod&lt;/a&gt;) on my tablet, which was
still running the stock Android - but hasn't seen any updates in more
than a year. Considering the (in)security of Android …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I finally got to the next thing on my &lt;em&gt;Want to do this
year&lt;/em&gt; list: put a new android
(&lt;a href="http://www.cyanogenmod.org/"&gt;Cyanogenmod&lt;/a&gt;) on my tablet, which was
still running the stock Android - but hasn't seen any updates in more
than a year. Considering the (in)security of Android this was long
overdue for me. But the fear of getting an unbootable tablet ("bricked"
as it is often called) was keeping me from doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when I finally got the nerves, I first had to run around screaming
for hours because the first step in the instructions didn't work. The
next day I read that it might have to do with the cable - and indeed,
tried with a different cable and the instructions just went along just
fine. So today I'm happily running with a more up-to-date Android again
on my tablet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because my systems run Gentoo Hardened with SELinux, I did had to do
some small magic tricks to get the
&lt;a href="http://www.clockworkmod.com/"&gt;Clockworkmod&lt;/a&gt; recovery on the tablet: the
&lt;strong&gt;wheelie&lt;/strong&gt; binary (yes, I couldn't find the sources - if they are even
available) that I had to run required me to disable size overflow
detection in the kernel (a PaX countermeasure), allowed executable
memory (both through &lt;strong&gt;paxctl-ng&lt;/strong&gt; as well as in SELinux using the
&lt;code&gt;allow_execmem&lt;/code&gt; boolean) and had to temporarily add in the
&lt;code&gt;dev_rw_generic_usb_dev&lt;/code&gt; right (refpolicy macro) to my user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also &lt;strong&gt;adb&lt;/strong&gt; had to be pax-marked, although I now know I don't need
&lt;strong&gt;adb&lt;/strong&gt; at all - I can just download the latest Android ZIP file from
the phone itself and refer to it from the recovery manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all nothing to worry about - everything worked like a charm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit:&lt;/em&gt; (so I remember next time), if the system is stuck in CMR
(recovery), reboot with VolDown+Pwr, but don't select recovery. After 5
seconds, it will ask if you want a cold boot. Select it, and things work
again ;-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="SELinux"></category><category term="android"></category><category term="grsecurity"></category><category term="pax"></category><category term="selinux"></category><category term="tablet"></category></entry></feed>