<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Simplicity is a form of art... - hadoop</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 20:55:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Comparing Hadoop with mainframe</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2016/06/comparing-hadoop-with-mainframe/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;At my work, I have the pleasure of being involved in a big data project that
uses Hadoop as the primary platform for several services. As an architect, I
try to get to know the platform's capabilities, its potential use cases, its
surrounding ecosystem, etc. And although the implementation at work is not in
its final form (yay agile infrastructure releases) I do start to get a grasp of
where we might be going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many analysts and architects, this Hadoop platform is a new kid on the block
so I have some work explaining what it is and what it is capable of. Not for the
fun of it, but to help the company make the right decisions, to support management
and operations, to lift the fear of new environments. One thing I've once said is
that "Hadoop is the poor man's mainframe", because I notice some high-level
similarities between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2016 20:55:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2016-06-15:/2016/06/comparing-hadoop-with-mainframe/</guid><category>Hadoop</category><category>hadoop</category><category>mainframe</category></item><item><title>Switching focus at work</title><link>https://blog.siphos.be/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, I was at work responsible for the infrastructure architecture of 
a couple of technological domains, namely databases and scheduling/workload 
automation. It brought me in contact with many vendors, many technologies
and most importantly, many teams within the organization. The focus domain
was challenging, as I had to deal with the strategy on how the organization,
which is a financial institution, will deal with databases and scheduling in
the long term.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sven Vermeulen</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 13:29:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blog.siphos.be,2015-09-20:/2015/09/switching-focus-at-work/</guid><category>Architecture</category><category>work</category><category>hadoop</category><category>docker</category></item></channel></rss>